<?xml version="1.0"?>
<updateList>
  <updateTitle>AUTECHRE'D</update-title>
  <artist ref="autechre">
    <name>Autechre</name>
    <text><![CDATA[
<p>Someone created the genre IDM, which stands for Intelligent Dance Music, and put Autechre in it. Certainly wasn't me, for I wouldn't create a genre with a name as silly as "Intelligent Dance Music". You can feel like ripping my head off if you will, but I really <em>do</em> think it's a silly name for a genre, and a silly <em>idea</em> for a genre. Want it or not, Aphex Twin agrees with me. Why, so there's "Intelligent" dance music, and the rest is "Stupid" dance music? Sorry, I don't buy that, and in art, intelligence is WAY too subjective a criteria to create a genre based on it. And applying it to Autechre... well, you can dance to their music. Certainly you can, but you don't <em>have</em> to; and they don't make music only with that purpose. Sometimes, I even have serious doubt whether they make music for dancing <em>at all</em>, but hey, there are so many forms and styles of dancing unknown to me that I'd better shut up and talk about whether I like the music or not.</p>

<p>And IDM or not, I really like Autechre. Yes, I'll be a jerk and say they only got better as their "evolution" went by. The dance music fiddlings of their early carreer is all fine and dandy, but it's just not as rewarding as their more complex, sophisticated albums. That's all elitist talk, of course, but I'm honest and serious. For the unenlightened, Autechre's music got pretty damn <em>strange</em> as time went by; not "weird" or "goofy", but very unusual for their own standards. On the surface, it sounds like all they're doing is purposefully ruin any trace of rhythm (in a genre that's highly based on rhythm, notice), but that's too simplistic a way to see it. I don't feel exactly comfortable by saying their latter albums are "experimental", but they are certainly very adventurous, exploratory, and demonstrate a lot of possibilities. And in addition, it can easily be seen as "art", and very entertaining art. At least for me.</p>

<p>Those who don't like that kind of stuff don't need to turn away from Autechre in disgust, though! Their carreer is relatively varied in terms of style, and those who are just up for some music for dancing can pick up [a]Incunabula[/a], while those interested in the crossover between electronic rhythms and abstract landscapes can get [a]Amber[/a] and/or [a]Tri Repetae[/a]. Anyone that has a mild interest in "dance" music that doesn't go "doof, doof, doof" for sixty minutes straight should check these guys out. They're talented, creative, interesting... what else could you ask for?</p>]]>
    </text>
    <album ref="incunabula">
      <title>Incunabula</title>
      <year>1993</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Bike[/s], [s]444[/s], [s]Eggshell[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Kalpol Introl</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Bike</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Autriche</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Bronchus 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Basscadet</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Eggshell</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Doctrine</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Maetl</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Windwind</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Lowride</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>444</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Well, so this might be dance music alright (some of it, that is), and it certainly is intelligent, but I've already ranted about those who decided to make that a <em>musical genre</em>, and I'll let it rest. [a]Incunabula[/a], in terms of Autechre, might not be the best place to look at to see what's so "innovative" about them, but it certainly caused a big stir back then, and even today it's considered as a prime instance of the more sophisticated, cerebral yet entirely energetic and rhythmic electronica. It's not a stretch to compare this with Aphex Twin's [a]Selected Ambient Works 85-92[/a], and keeping in mind that the tracks from this album were also collected from the previous few years, it shows that Autechre were not mere "disciples of the masters", not even at this stage.</p>

<p>Structurally and texturally, most songs are pretty simple and straightforward, but even those songs display a lot of skill, creativity and beauty. The most "experimental" tracks here include the dark, eerie [s]Kalpol Introl[/s], based on a rumbling bass riff, a sparse rhythm drenched in reverb, and other atmospheric layers. [s]Bronchus 2[/s] is far less melodic, based mostly on a "bubbling" rhythmic pattern. Those songs are relatively short, and definitely meant not to detract from the <em>real</em> beefy stuff here. Of all these tracks, the only one that could <em>seriously</em> count as a hardcore dance track is [s]Basscadet[/s], and I'm probably not spewing garbage, as the band even released an EP consisting solely of mixes of that single track. It is much more on the rhythmic and noisy side, but it is <em>very</em> rhythmic, with lots of percussion layers shaking and grooving in all directions, and <em>very</em> noisy, made to really make your head spin. This track truly shows that Autechre could tear the house down if they wanted to and <em>when</em> they wanted to.</p>

<p>Most of it, though, goes for the "ambient" side, and the results are truly impressive. That is, sometimes. All songs are perfectly listenable and pleasant while they're on, and I am quite fond of the breezy, catchy atmosphere and tunes of the lengthy [s]Eggshell[/s], the more herky-jerky [s]Doctrine[/s] (this group <em>really</em> has some idiosyncratic rhythms going!) and the very lengthy and atmospheric [s]Windwind[/s], but as for songs that <em>really<em> stand out, only a few of them qualify. [s]Bike[/s] is very uplifting and tuneful, with a bubbling melody to kill for, and a great flow that keeps all eight minutes of it interesting. One eyebrow raiser is [s]Lowride[/s], that's somewhere between faux-bossa-nova and proto-trip-hop, brilliantly melodic and catchy, with a groovy middle section to boot. To close the album, [s]444[/s] couldn't have been a better choice, with a heavy, stately melody underpinning and extremely evocative piece. It's a fantastic track.</p>

<p>Some of the more "advanced" electronic music enthusiasts and the more "forward" Autechre fans may tell you that this was the duo mostly "getting the hang of it": this stuff is miles, miles behind the more innovative and cutting-edge music they'd be making in a few years, but would you <em>seriously</em> expect <em>EVERY</em> artist to enter the scene innovating and turning the world upside down with their first album? And think of it, this wasn't even a <em>proper album</em>: it was more like a collection of assorted songs made for Warp Records' <em>Artificial Intelligence</em> series, and it just so happened to turn into Autechre's debut. But say what you will, it's a great record, not a single track can be counted as bad, it displays a load of skills many an artist would cut his pinky finger off for, and it's only "flaw" is that very modest in terms of new proposals. Yeah, combining jerky and syncopated rhythms with atmospheric synthesizers in <em>this</em> way wasn't terribly common, but overall they were mostly building on the foundations laid out by Aphex Twin and the likes. It would take some time for them to find a language of their own, but without seeing this as a mere "warming up" for the "real stuff", yeah, this record has high merits.</p>
]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>Now [l]send your comments[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="anti">
      <title>Anti</title>
      <year>1994</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Anti[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Lost</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Djarum</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Flutter</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>This EP stands as probably the only Autechre release with an <em>actual meaning</em>, or goal, or whatever you wish. Released about one month prior to the release of their second LP, [a]Anti[/a] is a sarcastic protest against the ban on raves in the United Kingdom, raised with the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act of 1994, and based on the definition of music with "repetitive beats". You won't expect <em>me</em> to give my opinion on the Act, being that I wasn't there at the time, so I can only comment on the EP. For the casual listener, the "protest" aspect of the music won't matter the least &mdash; but it's quite fun sticking to it. In a distinctively British tone, side A of the EP is built on "repetitive beats", and is issued with a warning that its performance in public will result in imprisonment. Side B, formed by the track [s]Flutter[/s], is described as having "non-repetitive beats", and it's assured that its performance in public is safe, though the presence of a musicologist and a lawyer would be strongly recommended (ha!). Sort of. The most striking aspect of this release, by this time, is that they were aiming it <em>specifically</em> for raves, which I assume wasn't the case with their following LP's and EP's.</p>

<p>In a way, this EP already displays a progression from the [a]Incunabula[/a] era. There isn't that sense of "amateurishness" in their music anymore (which really wasn't that much of a harm). Instead, there's more atmosphere and sense of space. [s]Lost[/s], the track dedicated to the eponymous TV series even before the show was conceived, is already a good example of that, with echoey percussion sounds and a moving, shaky rhythm that grooves along nicely. It's a good track, and the slow melody that accompanies it is a nice touch, even though it might feel a bit "tacked on". It doesn't meld in as well as the riffs in [a]Incunabula[/a] did. But that rhythm is a good one. [s]Djarum[/s] surprises us with metallic, almost industrial broken rhythms and scary high pitched squeaks and low pitched basses. A very interesting song, for sure. But the centrepiece is [s]Flutter[/s], with its tricky-as-hell percussion work and a beautiful melodic work. Man, the effort Autechre put in making a track without "repetitive beats" is <em>obvious</em> here. It's an impressive work. The track keeps changing at every moment, it's danceable, and the rhythm never, ever stands still. In a way, it predates the complex rhythm work in future works, but the focus here was in making something that could be played in raves. The song loses a little in the atmosphere department, but heck, who am I to complain?</p>

<p>Truthfully, this isn't an EP I'd recommend for the casual fan: unless these guys <em>really</em> interest you, there's no need for you to go hunting down for it. It's, in other words, <em>non essential</em>. Electronic music enthusiasts and folks who are <em>really</em> getting into the band are well advised to check this out, though: the tracks are good, especially [s]Flutter[/s], and you'll hardly be disappointed. The rating is relatively low, though, because it's too short and slight. But it is interesting, and the sole fact that this is, in a way, <em>protest music</em> already justifies its existence.</p> 
]]>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <commentPhrase>Any comments? [l]Send them in[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="amber">
      <title>Amber</title>
      <year>1994</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Slip[/s], [s]Piezo[/s], [s]Further[/s], [s]Nine[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Foil</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Montreal</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Silverside</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Slip</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Glitch</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Piezo</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Nine</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Further</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Yulquen</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Nil</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Teartear</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Aside from being one of the very few Autechre records with a name you can properly comprehend and a cover you can properly distinguish, [a]Amber[/a] is what you can call a full fledged <em>album</em>, intended to pack up the band's style and vision as neatly and accurately as possible. And what can be said? This album is incredible. For one, the loop-based nature of their music is... well, <em>still</em> there, but if on [a]Incunabula[/a] they'd amass a dozen loops and switch between them to showcase the interesting interactions between them, here, they amass... um, one or two loops and let them interact with <em>you</em>. Sounds dull? Well, the album <em>is</em> much more minimal, mantraic and repetitive than [a]Incunabula[/a], but in these tracks, Autechre manages to secure a ground fully of their own, and a language they definitely dominate. Of course there are still echoes of "ambient techno", Aphex Twin and whatever other forefathers they could have, but those are echoes you're bound to hear in any artist, even on Aphex Twin's own tracks; after all, he didn't create a whole new kind of music out of thin air, did he? And here, Booth and Brown manage to create an interesting, exciting vision that you can float through, interact with and experience yourself. But who knows <em>what</em> exactly that vision is? Vast landscapes and natural formations, like on the album cover? Synthetic machinery working like mad at the top of their speed? Abstract, surrealistic fractals and sonic slipstreams? Who knows! It's all up to you, basically, and the album just leaves a <em>hint</em> of what's going on. You fill in the blanks the way you desire.</p>

<p>In short, it's quite an interactive album. But it's a <em>long</em>, samey interactive album. A test of your patience, if you will. But guess what, I am patient, and I enjoy everything in the album to some extent. And fans of [a]Incunabula[/a]'s melodies will have to be satisfied with the, um, <em>occasional</em> hints of melody in this album. Yes, it <em>is</em> the kind of album that values the <em>sound</em> more than melodic content, and it's also the kind of album that proves that texture and feel <em>can</em> make a melody absolutely dismissable. And <em>all</em> tracks &mdash; and I repeat, <em>all</em> tracks &mdash; achieve their aim, whatever it is, and in one way or another. The final result is a rich, immersive, nocturnal album, very good for playing loud in a darkened room at night.</p>

<p>It's not exactly diverse, notice. Most songs follow a bit of a pattern. The basic idea is to set up a 4/4 foundation and then enchance it with the <em>perfect</em> sounds, little tunes and riffs and percussion effects &mdash; which are sometimes sparse and minimal, and other times rich and full. As such, you have examples of repetitive, circular tunes with tricky rhythms and spaced-out sounds such as [s]Foil[/s], which just keeps sinking in its own ocean of humming drones, phased percussive effects and echoey sparse percussion, and [s]Glitch[/s], which features sounds like bells ran through a ring modulator. [s]Montreal[/s] also goes that way, but features a very simple, but catchy two-note bass line under a super groovy rhythm augmented by a "dime on a counter" effect, and later joined by high-pitched, toy-piano-like little melodies. It's really cool and imaginative. And [s]Silverside[/s] goes the "eerie" path with haunting synth-string notes and low-pitched effects (one of them which was already used on [s]Kalpol Introl[/s], oddly enough) on a slow, ominous rhythm. Cool stuff.</p>

<p>The tracks I like the most are the more tuneful ones, though the concept of "tunefulness" in this album is a bit strange. For example, the main feature of [s]Slip[/s] is a strange, elastic synth line with is <em>fantastically</em> catchy, in spite of being so weird &mdash; oh, scrap that, it's catchy <em>because</em> it's weird, but it's also tuneful and (relatively) cheery. [s]Slip[/s] is without a doubt the cheeriest song here, and fits in marvellously well with the darker material. [s]Nine[/s], the shortest song at three minutes, is made up almost entirely of similarly elastic, echoed synths, but the patterns it forms are more complex and hard to follow, and the music is formed by the way they come together and complete the puzzle. For <em>me</em>, it could have been longer, and I would find it absolutely delightful all the way through, but I don't know if many other people'd feel like that. Yes, the songs are pretty long, overall, and we have [s]Further[/s] which <em>is</em> pretty long, and [s]Yulquen[/s], which <em>feels</em> pretty long. The latter is <em>one</em> hushed electric-piano-like loop in 10/4 for the entire song. It's a melodic loop, but heck, it's <em>only one</em> &mdash; no beats, no synth pads, very few effects. That's minimalism for ya! And it works, because the band enhances the mood as the loop goes through a few effects, and later slowly vanishes. The former is made up mostly of a haunting loop of high-pitched marimba-like sounds, which is later joined by all sorts of synth effects to create haunting, rich waves of texture and crap &mdash; "crap" being the terms with I came up to describe the song, of course, because the song is magnificent and I love following its slow, lengthy, delightful development. Those sounds are so wonderfully dark and so wonderfully warm it's actually quite hard to imagine them.</p>

<p>Another favourites of mine are [s]Nil[/s], with its sparse, vague, imaginative synth chords, and [s]Piezo[/s], which starts off with weird little percussion loops and effects, and then turns in with really haunting and gorgeous synth chords. Especially creepy, though, is [s]Teartear[/s], which is nearly downright <em>scary</em>, with its deep string sounds and pounding rhythm, which later <em>slows down</em> and becomes even more pounding and scarier. Hey, who said there's no emotional resonance in electronic music? There <em>is</em> feeling in this music &mdash; or, at least, there <em>can</em> be, if the listener tries hard enough. And [a]Amber[/a] is to me one of Autechre's most emotional albums ever. Maybe fans of [a]Incunabula[/a] will speak in the latter's favour, and I won't argue. They're both very tangible records, [a]Incunabula[/a] much more than this one, but guess what? I love Autechre when they're abstract, and I really, really dig this record, and [s]Teartear[/s] reminds me of the Cure. Try singing the lyrics of [s]One Hundred Years[/s] over that.</p>
]]></review>
      <rating>14</rating>
      <commentPhrase>Comments? [l]I'm acceptin'[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="garbage">
      <title>Garbage</title>
      <year>1994</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Garbagemx36[/s], [s]VLetrmx21[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Garbagemx36</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>PIOBmx19</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Bronchuseven24</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>VLetrmx21</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Funny how the times change. For Autechre, in 1994, this 40 minute long release is an EP, when many other bands would be happy to call it an LP not too many years before it. But Autechre have their own reasons to call this an EP; for example, it's considerably shorter than their LP releases, has only four tracks, and it's basically a "companion" to [a]Amber[/a], since these songs are from those sessions and were left off the album mainly due to space constraints.</p>

<p>First and foremost: pretty strange song titles, huh? This is one of the few Autechre EP's with song titles following a "formula" of sorts. Don't ask me where the "mx" comes from, but the number at the end means the percentage of the EP's total running length the track takes. Of course, that's just a silly, irrelevant curiosity, but we all need that. Besides, it's important for you to know how long each song is. So do the math. Use the Windows calculator if you need. As for the music, well, I'm not surprised that <em>these</em> tracks were pulled out of [a]Amber[/a]. None of them are bad, but they lack the development, sense of growth and depth that the tracks from that album had. The only track that, in my opinion, could have been a mighty addition to the album is [s]Garbagemx36[/s], a fourteen minute piece with truly great tricks and changes added in for great justice. Starting off with an apparently bland rhythm, the song starts to grow with starts-and-stops, chord changes and different synth patterns and chord sequences added in. It never grows to the kind of loop layering [a]Incunabula[/a] presented, and it's dang fine as it is. It never gets dull, and it's a beautiful, enjoyable, and even danceable piece. Definitely a highlight for Autechre's early carreer.</p>

<p>The following tracks are far more minimal. And, in fact, both [s]PIOBmx19[/s] and [s]Bronchusevenmx24[/s] are based mainly on rhythm and percussion, with radically minimal melodic work. The former only brings up a sketch of a three-note melody below its ocean of bouncing, ping-pong, echoed percussion, which goes and goes without ever changing. The rhythm works well, I say, but I'm not sure if it holds my attention for six minutes straight. It really does get pretty close to overdoing it. The latter, at least, has a less overwhelming rhythm. Indeed, it's worthy of carrying the "Bronchus" title, as it brings back the bubbling sounds from [s]Bronchus 2[/s], this time on a straight, less syncopated 4/4 rhythm. It's even longer, though, and the only thing detracting from the rhythm are plaintive chords humming on the background. The percussion is good and mesmerising, but doesn't deliver the rich atmosphere that [a]Amber[/a] could create. The EP, though, ends on a pretty high note, with one of the most unusual traks in Autechre's repertoire. [s]VLetrmx21[/s] is the most genuinely "ambient" track they did, counting on no rhythm at all, with simple but beautiful waves of synth strings rising and falling, delivering an eternally looping melody. Very surprising track, almost dirgey, and also very, very beautiful. It's not <em>news</em>, of course, but its position at the end of the EP is perfect.</p>

<p>Though it might seem a little unfair to rate EP's and LP's on the same basis, this one is getting an 11. If you wish to think of a comparison, you can think of the 80 minutes of 11-worthy music on [a]Incunabula[/a] and the 40 minutes of 11-worthy music on [a]Garbage[/a]: both records have their share of pleasant-but-not-outstanding tracks, but both have excellent moments and make very good listening experiences. That about sums it up.</p>
]]>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>Treasure? [a]Garbage[/a]? [l]Send your opinions[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="vapre">
      <title>Anvil Vapre</title>
      <year>1995</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Second Bad Vilbel[/s], [s]Second Peng[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Second Bad Vilbel</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Second Scepe</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Second Scout</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Second Peng</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>A shorter EP, this time around. And again, it's an EP because it's a "companion" to an LP - in this case, [a]Tri Repetae[/a], which was released a month after this one. But it's not quite right to say this album will give you a good glimpse of how the LP is going to be: it has a strange sense of paranoia going behind it, and is quite dark. Less dark than [a]Amber[/a], but still carrying a sense of ambiguity. A <em>good</em> sense of ambiguity. And the good news is that the songs in this album are more developed and accomplished than those on [a]Garbage[/a]. The only song that doesn't rely in melody, curiously enough, is the first one, and my personal favourite. Why? Because of that devious rhythm! <em>And</em> because of the use of brown noise (at least I guess it's brown noise) as a percussion instrument. Damn cool, I say. The machine-like rhythm, followed by ghostly chords creates a hell of an atmosphere, and once again, the sudden slowdown in the middle of the track <em>does</em> make a difference. You see, those two tracks on [a]Garbage[/a] were reliant on atmosphere, while [s]Second Bad Vilbel[/s] is reliant on <em>movement</em>. And like hell does it move. In all directions. At once. Okay, not quite, but it's a heck of a song.</p>

<p>The others don't disappoint at all. The rhythms are sharp, groovy and catchy, and all backed by delicious snippets of melodies and riffs. [s]Second Scepe[/s] has a catchy bassline and fragments of a female voice serving as percussion. Awesome groove, too! The bass sound, in fact, reminds me a bit of [s]Dael[/s] from the next album, and the addition of the high pitched tinkling notes at the end is a fine, [a]Amber[/a]-ish touch. [s]Second Peng[/s] goes for a more [s]Teartear[/s] approach, with an ugly synth sound used for the main riff. All the other sounds are pretty airy and echoey, but they accumulate slowly into a dense atmosphere. Hooray for slow building! Isn't it <em>fun</em>? I mean it! [s]Second Scout[/s] is the weakest one, but by no means a disappointment. Its slower funky groove and bending bass sound make up a really cool "intermission" between the faster tracks and the final [s]Second Peng[/s].</p>

<p>None of the tracks have the development of [s]Garbagemx36[/s], but heck, this is Autechre, and repetition was already commonplace in their music by this time. So learn to deal with it and enjoy it. This is one of their finest EPs, and quite close to a 13. If you like [a]Tri Repetae[/a], be sure to try to get it, and vice versa. Though I wonder who would bother getting [a]Anvil Vapre[/a] <em>before</em> the mandatory [a]Tri Repetae[/a]. You?</p>]]>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]Second [l]Comment[/l][/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="repetae">
      <title>Tri Repetae</title>
      <year>1995</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Dael[/s], [s]Rsdio[/s], [s]Stud[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Dael</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Clipper</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Leterel</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rotar</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Stud</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Eutow</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>C.Pach</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Gnit</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Overand</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Rsdio</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>You should be well aware, by now, that Autechre's songs and albums have titles merely so you have <em>something</em> you can use to refer to them other than using descriptions like "the one with the strings", or "the one with the spinning sounds" or "the fast, eerie one". That's <em>me</em> speculating, of course, but what reason would Booth and Brown have to give their songs <em>meaningful</em> titles? What meanings could you find in music like that, and worse, meanings you could express in song/album titles? Tangerine Dream gave their pieces titles like [s]Mysterious Semblance at the Strand of Nightmares[/s] and [s]Origin of Supernatural Probabilities[/s]. Isn't that, like, the <em>goofiest</em> thing ever? With that in mind, you can hardly call titles like [s]IV VV IV VV VIII[/s], [s]Augmatic Disport[/s], [s]6IE.CR[/s]' and [s]Sim Gishel[/s] "goofy". And [a]Tri Repetae[/a], well, it's not accurate Latin. I can only guess they wanted something that gave the idea of "three", so "Tri" was a natural choice. But "Repetae"? I can only guess they wanted a word that had "ae" in it, because hey, Autechre refer to themselves as "Ae" quite often, and you can write that title as [a]Tri Repet&aelig;[/a] for the "coolness" factor if you wish.</p>

<p>So, with this record, Autechre shows more change and development, though this album doesn't really point the way towards which the band would eventually develop. This music is... <em>catchy</em>! As in head-bobbing, toe-tapping catchy electronic music. Instead of eerie, haunting sonic textures, the band here is occupied with creating tunes that invite you to a completely brand new, exciting world. It's <em>very</em> dehumanised, machine-like music, but it's damn friendly at times. It almost sounds like someone devised a computer more reliable than a Macintosh and more popular than an IBM PC and taught it how to make music on its own. And I suppose Autechre had an intention to make the album as "mechanic" as possible, with the "human" factor diminished as much as they could. The result is impressive.</p>

<p>For one, like I said, this stuff is catchy as heck. It's not serious; it's almost humourous at times. It's refined and sophisticated, but still accessible and technically outstanding. It's thoroughly listenable, and thoroughly enjoyable. This is the one Autechre album that I'd recommend to someone who only has a passing interest in electronic music &mdash; it's very "far out" in rhythmic and textural terms, though it is repetitive as hell, and like I said a dozen times already, it's catchy as hell. And it's <em>fun</em>! It's cheery and it's nifty! It's shiny, it has a completely plain cover, and one of its songs is named after a programming language. It's fun for all ages, social classes and creeds. Almost. Seriously, I <em>would</em> definitely recommend this record first to anyone. It's a good introduction to Autechre, and a landmark in electronic music.</p>

<p>So, what's all the big difference between this album [a]Amber[/a]? The main deal is that it's less serious and ominous. Though there are a few slightly creepy, dark songs like [s]Rotar[/s] and [s]Overand[/s], it's mostly pretty lighthearted and cheery. It's less repetitive; no, you can't call this Prog Rock, but it's less repetitive in the sense that it depends much less of those mantraic, samey rhythms and synth patterns. For example, if on the two previous albums, you could imagine a couple of percussionists bashing constantly on their instruments to create a pattern that would be repeated all the way through the song, here, you have a whole ensemble playing parts that, while being pretty sparse, create a very complex and dynamic overall sound. What you have here are magnificent waves of carefully interweaved, syncopated rhythm tracks that serve as an interesting, solid foundation to these catchy electronic tunes &mdash; be they slow and menacing, like [s]Rotar[/s], or upbeat and friendly like [s]Leterel[/s].</p>

<p>My favourite tracks are concentrated on the first two thirds or so of the album, which contains five tracks ranging from six to nine minutes long. Among these, the one I like the most is the opening track, [s]Dael[/s], which is a <em>perfect</em> example to the tricky percussion texture I talked about above &mdash; going from the "spinning plops" to the metallic hits to the drum machine, it slowly sets up an incredibly groovy, almost danceable rhythm. And on top of this, they lay those simple synth patterns, each one made of three or four notes, and it goes on a slow crescendo of riffs and rhythm. It really makes a difference from the band's previous material. On a quieter tone, I really like [s]Stud[/s], with its mesmerising, looping synth bass melody, which plays over an unbalanced, start-and-stop rhythm, which sounds like the very surface of what they call nowadays "drum 'n' bass", if you allow the poor analogy. It's nine minutes long, and definitely the most monotonous song in the album, but I like it lots. [s]Clipper[/s] is the definitive winner in the "groovy rhythm" department, though. I wonder if anyone can actually resist that rhythm, especially when the buzzing bass melody comes by, and [s]Leterel[/s] has <em>another</em> groovy rhythm, though slower, and accompanied by weird, airy synth pads which keep alternating between two chords in a brilliant ambiguity; only occasionally it breaks into a more elaborate synth progression, only to fall back into the same thing again. [s]Rotar[/s] is brilliantly haunting, with metallic percussion effects and eerie synth notes falling slowly everywhere and noises which sound like rusty gears rubbing against each other. It's a very mechanical song, that one.</p>

<p>After [s]Stud[/s], there's a small "intermezzo" with three short (to Autechre's standards) tracks. [s]Eutow[/s] is my favourite, starting off pleasantly enough with confused synth lines floating around, until the fast rhythm kicks in with ugly, disfigured synth chords bending up and down everywhere. [s]C.Pach[/s] isn't very impressive, compared to the stuff that came before it, but it's short and good enough and does no harm at all. [s]Gnit[/s] is more fun, with its strange "shaking" riff, and a flute-like sound playing little melodies over it. [s]Overand[/s] comes by as a quiet intermission. It's long, and it's a little bit reminescent of [s]Yulquen[/s] with its minimal synth loop (even more minimal and repetitive, this time around), but it's augmented with little tingly effects and a barely audible rhythm behind it. And just as it goes away, [s]Rsdio[/s] arrives with its breahtaking mix of odd, breathy, metallic sounds clanging and bumping around into everything. I'm a sucker for the way the "spinning" metallic beats interact with the three note bass loop, and what goes on top sounds somewhat like a weird symphony of air valves hissing like mad. It's slow, hypnotising, and downright brilliant, one of Autechre's finest creations ever.</p>

<p>Autechre fans can't live without this. Electronica fans can't live without this either, I suppose. I'd be hardpressed to say if <em>I</em> couldn't live without it, but I don't even think before agreeing that this is a brilliant record and everyone should own it. There are other Autechre albums that I personally dig more (I even think I enjoy [a]Amber[/a] slightly better), but this one gets a higher rating for being so clever, creative, original and entertaining. It's an objective thing, see. Sometimes objectivity has to speak louder than subjectivity, so there ya go. [a]Tri Repetae[/a] was released as [a]Tri Repetae++[/a] on the US, a double CD with the EP's [a]Garbage[/a] and [a]Anvil Vapre[/a] on the second CD. Make sure to get that one if you can't get the separate EP's.</p>]]>
      <rating>14</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[a]Tri [l]Commentae[/l][/a]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="envane">
      <title>Envane</title>
      <year>1997</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Draun Quarter[/s], [s]Goz Quarter[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Goz Quarter</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Latent Quarter</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Laughing Quarter</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Draun Quarter</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>EP again, and a good one. In fact, not just a "good" one, but one of my favourites. In fact, I like it so much that I'm kind of divided between awarding it a 13 and giving it a 12 with honours. But then again, in terms of excitement and texture, the record's less <em>dense</em> than [a]Amber[/a], so there. What matters is that the EP is, strangely enough, a bit torn between the "aural texture" based music of [a]Amber[/a] and the intense sonic abuse of their following releases. The outer tracks are the slowest and quieter ones, and the inner tracks are the opposite. Nifty, eh? Whether it's surprising or not, my favourite part of it is the "outer" one, with the quieter songs. Somehow, these are some of the most <em>beautiful</em> tracks Autechre ever put out. For real. And it's not even the inhuman, out-of-this-world beauty we're used to &mdash; some parts of it are almost human. Yes, [s]Goz Quarter[/s] is still quite mechanic, with a dull percussion track, which sounds like a scratched CD skipping, augmented by percussion effects and melodic bits. Similarly to [s]Garbagemx36[/s], it starts off in a different key, with strange synth sounds, before settling on a more comforting, pleasant atmosphere with multiple layers of melody and ambience. The most interesting thing, though, is the use of "turntable scratch" sounds and vocal samples used mostly on the first half. Unusual for Autechre, that.</p>

<p>[s]Draun Quarter[/s] is what I mean with "human beauty", in which the droning rhythm is almost challenged by the gentle, plaintive synth melodies. As usual, the development through its ten minutes is fabulous, and culminates in about two minutes of percussion-less atmosphere fading. This track would be a definitive inclusion in an "Autechre compilation" if I had to make one. The other two, well, they'd be candidates for inclusion if there was any space left to fill up (which would be rather difficult, I believe). Not just because I don't like noisy Autechre music, but compared to the others, they're weaker. Still good, though! [s]Laughing Quarter[/s], in particular, creates a mood that I can only describe as "psychotic" &mdash; weird chord progression, ugly synth sound, paranoid rhythms, you got it all. [s]Latent Quarter[/s] isn't as cool in that aspect, but its distorted percussion beats form a wicked, <em>danceable</em> groove. It's one of the few Autechre songs at this point that count on a groovy, straight rhythm that doesn't bounce all over the place. That isn't the song's intention, after all.</p>

<p>[a]Envane[/a] isn't really anything spectacular, considering Autechre's best releases, but among their EPs, it might be their most worth having one. It packs up the "soft" and "hard" side of Autechre in a balanced, smooth way. But the other EPs are also recommended, so check them out if [a]Envane[/a] interests you.</p>]]>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>And then, [l]send me comments[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="slide">
      <title>Chiastic Slide</title>
      <year>1997</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Cichli[/s], [s]Cipater[/s], [s]Nuane[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Cipater</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Rettic AC</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Tewe</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Cichli</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Hub</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Calibruc</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Recury</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Pule</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Nuane</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Allegedly, [a]Chiastic Slide[/a] isn't considered a "real" follow-up to [a]Tri Repetae[/a] &mdash; by none other than Autechre themselves. I can kinda see that, as [a]Chiastic Slide[/a] sounds like anything but a continuation of their work. It's like they consciously tore themselves away from the path they were going through and took an unexpected detour. Nothing wrong with <em>that</em>, mind. But the one thing that I can't understand is that some other people consider this as a weak rehash of [a]Tri Repetae[/a]. How come? This sounds <em>nothing</em>at all like [a]Tri Repetae[/a]. That album was accessible, friendly, cheery, fun and immediately engaging. This album is... well, definitely their most difficult release so far.</p>

<p>And I mean "difficult" as in "inaccessible for a newcomer". I mean, if [a]Chiastic Slide[/a] was my introduction to the band, I don't think I'd be so keen on going forwards &mdash; and it certainly isn't because the album is too "difficult". It's just... a bit aimless. See, the band seems here intent on doing something complex, as a way to challenge their own limits. But there isn't an overall direction to the music, and the final result falls like "complexity for complexity's sake". Of course, technically, it's highly impressive, and the music <em>is</em> intelligent, well-crafted and provides enough interesting tricks to keep me moderately satisfied. But the finished product fails to leave a concrete, tangible impression. It passes me by a bit &mdash; with the notable exception of a few excellent tracks.</p>

<p>There definitely are highlights. [s]Cichli[/s] achieves a kind of na&iuml;ve, honest beauty that very few &mdash; if any &mdash; Autechre songs so far managed to achieve, with its "jumping" melody and plaintive, minor key synth pads. It's really all about that looping melody and the syncopated, carefully sequenced rhythm track, which definitely owes a thing or two to [a]Tri Repetae[/a]. If the album were made of more tracks like <em>that</em>, I'd understand why people call it a repetition of its predecessor. But nah, that's the only song of its kind here: that is, honestly melodic and harmonically traditional. Elsewhere, you get [s]Cipater[/s], which features a semi-industrialoid rhythm made of a million metallic clanging sounds. Funny that "cipater" is the name of a part of a car, since it brings images of a complex engine-like machine working. It does have little glimpses of melody, especially in the first part, with the 4/4 groove. Halfway through, it switches into an even trickier 6/8 groove with a bass line underneath; a very exciting, refreshing change in the song.</p>

<p>And those are the more "accessible" songs. Everywhere else, the band introduces you to the world of strange, apparently incoherent rhythms, untrivial &mdash; sometimes almost nonexistent &mdash; harmonies and ugly, grating noises. When did [a]Tri Repetae[/a] present stuff like that? It didn't! If anything, [a]Chiastic Slide[/a] points the way to their more abstract releases like [a]Confield[/a] and [a]Draft 7.30[/a], but they still didn't have the right <em>chops</em> to do that kind of stuff. An example of that is [s]Tewe[/s], which features an unsettling "clanging" chord in each bar, and it built with those fast sequences of percussion sounds rollicking over a much slower rhythm, and almost random notes pinging around. It's quite cool and mesmerising, and it's a very fine moment in the album, but they are yet to do <em>much</em> better than that. There are further highlights: I really like [s]Hub[/s], with its irregular rhythmic patterns, loose percussion effects and eerie chords. It's <em>very</em> monotonous, but it gives me the feeling of being lost in space. Really! Pretty unique song. And [s]Nuane[/s], with its deranged harmonies and odd rhythms, starts out on a rage, shooting percussion and discordant brass-like notes everywhere, until it falls into quiet, eerie loops after the five minute mark or so. That kind of transition would be revisited on [s]Sublimit[/s] much later, and it works well here. The strange thing is that, of its thirteen minute length, the final 3 minutes are reserved to a single, irregular, and rather grating noise which is sort of like an old refrigerator engine; just that scraping and nothing more.</p>

<p>The other songs have varying degrees of success. [s]Calibruc[/s] is a short, weird onslaught of loud rhythm, siren-like noises and all sorts of unsettling stuff, which oddly dissolve into a sort of melody near the end, and [s]Recury[/s] is a <em>very</em> long and <em>very</em> monotonous groove, which is slowly augmented by creepy, wailing noises of sorts. The one song I could live without, sort of, is [s]Pule[/s], which reminds me a bit of the looping melody of [s]Slip[/s] as well as the clashing, near random half-melodies of [s]Nine[/s]. That's because it's made mainly of a weird synth patch playing a "melody" that <em>definitely</em> sounds like it was being randomly generated as it went. I mean, it's difficult for me to believe either Booth or Brown wrote it all by hand, but I wouldn't be surprised if they did. However, the song has little more than that to offer, and with the memories of [s]Nine[/s] and [s]Slip[/s] in my mind, it can't help but disappoint. Still, in face of all that, I enjoy the album enough &mdash; if only because it's witty enough, and does display talent. And its lack of vision is only a "lack of vision" when compared to its predecessors. It's a good, yet inaccessible, album, and I'm glad I have it. I wouldn't part with it, that's for sure; after all, it did give us [s]Cichli[/s].</p>]]>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]sendcomment[/l]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="cichlisuite">
      <title>Cichlisuite</title>
      <year>1997</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Characi[/s], [s]Pencha[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Yessland</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Pencha</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Characi</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Krib</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Tilapia</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The title to this release is explained by the fact that these five tracks were, in some way, originated from [a]Chiastic Slide[/a]'s [s]Cichli[/s], even though they sound <em>nothing</em> like it. And also because the title is pronounced like "sickly sweet", so there &mdash; another Autechre title with <em>some</em> sense behind the title. The most striking surprise about this EP, in comparison to the others, is how varied it is. The only tracks that sound somewhat alike are the opener and the closer, both based on a very similar rhythm but not much more. Aside from that, the EP manages to make a sensible, seamless stylistic link between [a]Tri Repetae[/a], [a]Chiastic Slide[/a] and [a]LP5[/a], which is really welcome at this point in their carreer.</p>

<p>Allow me to explain. Once you pass by the eighteen seconds of the scratched CD "chip chip chip chip" effect of [s]Yeesland[/s] (somewhat like the intro of [s]Goz Quarter[/s] sped up), the track starts to reminisce you of [a]Tri Repetae[/a], with an upbeat, mechanical, multilayered and joyful rhythm and delicately complex synth work beneath it. "Whoa! Autechre are turning accessible again!" you think, amazed. And indeed, it's a pretty, enjoyable song that still manages to keep that groovy ambivalence that Autechre can create so well, with its slightly ominous pads. And the spinning, creaking, scratching and whistling mechanical noises are really put to a sort of dance here, instead of the maniacal spinning of [a]Chiastic Slide[/a]. Just as you start getting into the groove, [s]Pencha[/s] arrives and whacks you in the head with dissonant synth plucking and percussion that bashes against the slow, pounding rhythm at lightning speed. It takes a little while to mount, of course, but the song is a bit of a crossover between [s]Tewe[/s] and the next album's [s]Arch Carrier[/s], and it isn't such a stretch to see traces of [a]Confield[/a] in it &mdash; except that there is <em>sense</em> in the rhythm. It stays tight &mdash; just hyperactive &mdash; and sketches of riffs are present in it too. Nonetheless, a big change from [s]Yeesland[/s] it is.</p>

<p>Without a clue of how the next song is going to be, you're not surprised to realise that [s]Characi[/s] is a lengthy (lengthiest track here, at seven minutes), mantraic, repetitive and awfully mesmerising track that stands out from most "repetitive" songs Autechre did to this point for having a much trickier rhythm, an understated and hypnotising riff and all sorts of cool sounds swirling all around it, slowly mounting the mood but never falling in unexciting repetition. It's my favourite in the album, though it doesn't really overshadows the other tracks. It's just one more excellent Autechre piece, and I'd gladly put it in a compilation if I ever make one. Well, so that leaves two tracks: [s]Tilapia[/s], a throwback to [s]Yeesland[/s] which still entertains me with moody synth chords, little melodies and an eerie ending, and perhaps the most unusual track here, the three minute slow, relaxed groove of [s]Krib[/s]. This might be the only Autechre song that is <em>truly</em> gentle and soothing with little or no ambiguity at all. It's groovy and nice, and still manages not to fall in pitfals of "chill out" music and such. Not that I know much of that kind of music anyway, but I like [s]Krib[/s], and every other track here as well. It's a pretty excellent release, and its short length (at last! An EP-length EP!) is in fact an asset, showing Autechre weren't willing to fall into dumb roboticness. One of their best EP's, and recommended to anyone with a moderate interest.</p>]]>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>Any opinions? [l]Send them in[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="lp5">
      <title>LP5</title>
      <year>1998</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Fold4, Wrap5[/s], [s]Acroyear2[/s], [s]Rae[/s], [s]Under BOAC[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Acroyear2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>777</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rae</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Melve</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Vose In</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Fold4, Wrap5</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Under BOAC</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Corc</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Caliper Remote</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Arch Carrier</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Drane2</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>As [a]Chiastic Slide[/a] is generally considered as a "non sucessor" to [a]Tri Repetae[/a], you'd think that THIS is a "return to form" of sorts. And, well, in a way, it might be. To be less cryptic, I might even say that, if you swapped [a]LP5[/a] and [a]Chiastic Slide[/a] in their chronological sequence, you'd have a more coherent transition from the "early carreer" to their "latter carreer", with those two albums in question forming the bridge. But since things are rarely coherent, [a]LP5[/a] stands as both an advance and a stepback &mdash; not a step<em>down</em> in terms of quality, but just a recapitulation of their more accessible, less daring style. And an advancement because it <em>does</em> spice up the formula with trickier, nastier twists and musical ideas.</p>

<p>If you're really willing to do so, you can visualise this album as somewhat divided between the more pleasant tracks and the more adventurous tracks. For reviewing the album, that can be useful, but for <em>listening</em> to it, there's no point. Fact is that this might very well be Autechre's defining "transitional album", though you can't immediately tell what's in store for the next album, judging only by it. There are multiple possibilities, and as it turned out, Autechre chose the boldest path &mdash; but that's forwarding too much. Fact is, I enjoy this album quite a bit. Quite a lot. Quite a bunch. I don't care. I enjoy it enough to make it worth having.</p>

<p>For one, there <em>is</em> pretty fresh music here. Nothing I feel comfortable calling <em>innovative</em>, but it does have [s]Fold4, Wrap5[/s], an ingenious track which makes use of an incredibly clever rhythmic trick, yelding a pleasant, beautiful and evocative song. The main idea is that the rhythm section is sequenced in such a way that its tempo <em>constantly decreases</em>, getting locked in a sort of tempo loop. But instead of throwing hundreds of rhythmic layers and buzzing synths coming from all sides, the song just gently swings you through a beautiful sonic landscape, made with the simplest synth layers one could make for a track like this. At four minutes, it's relatively short, but it goes straight to the point and does its business well. It's an extraordinary track, and even if someone tells me the rhythm trick was already done in the past, I'll still like it that much. As for the hundreds of rhythmic layers, they save that for other tracks.</p>

<p>For example, the opener [s]Acroyear2[/s] kicks in at warp speed, with what I imagine as a musical interpretation of a deranged, pissed off machine, buzzing, beating, blasting and beeping like a madman. The result is not "scary"; it's quite goofy, in fact, and it's dynamic and fun, and the beeping, whining synth notes give it a vague, ambiguous hint of melody. [s]777[/s] kicks in, then, and wipes the melody almost completely away. It's one of the few occasions, at this early period, in which Autechre makes use of an odd time signature (as indicated by the song title). The focus is entirely on the rhythm, as it bounces and grooves in all directions. Quite an impressive achievement, and though some people might not be too interested in it, I'm entertained. Yes, the catchy synth riffs are lacking, but hey, we can't demand Autechre to stay always the same, can we? [s]Under BOAC[/s] goes back to the straight 4/4, but conjures an even more impressive, syncopated, quasi-industrial symphony of metallic clanging and banging sounds. By this time, I don't even care about the lack of catchy synth melodies (though there's a bit of a riff at the beginning); the rhythm is brilliant enough for me.</p>

<p>The more melodic tracks sacrifice the "experimentalism" of the other tracks, but I like that, because it sets a balance in the album. Just as you have the wild [s]777[/s], you're greeted with the lengthy, but pleasant [s]Rae[/s]. Technically, it's not very new, and may even be nothing but a generic electronic excourse, but it works wonders in the context of the album &mdash; not to mention that it's rare to see such a tranquil, easy-going and nice song from Autechre. Traditional beauty, you say? Well, to counter that, they have [s]Vose In[/s], which gets itself stuck in an endless loop with pusating chords. To me, it isn't really very interesting, and sounds more like an extended introduction to [s]Fold4, Wrap5[/s], including the surge of seemingly random, mechanical noise at the end. [s]Arch Carrier[/s] settles a steady, droning base for strange, atonal synth arpeggios which just constantly keep hitting you on the head like a goddamn hammer. [s]Corc[/s] goes for a quieter, gentler approach, with a slow, sparse rhythm and eerie synth tunes. Quite a difference from [s]Under BOAC[/s], I assure you.</p>

<p>The closer, [s]Drane2'[/s], comes as a bit of a surprise. It's also a long closer, at ten minutes, and it's a gentle, soothing, pleasant soundscape of synth pads and "bouncing" percussion effects making the only glimpses of rhythm in the track. It's lengthy, yes, but I don't mind the length at all. It's a beautiful track, and for the really obsessed, there's about a minute and a half of "bonus" at the end of the song, after a portion of silence, which is made up of strange, tuneless synthesized sounds. For what reason? Who knows. What matters is the album itself, and it's a good one. It's up to par, though compared to better albums like [a]Amber[/a] and [a]Tri Repetae[/a], it might be disappointing. Still, maybe it's an interesting introduction to the band, since it shows both a bit of what Autechre used to be, and a bit of what they were yet to be.</p>]]>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]Send your comments[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="peel">
      <title>Peel Session</title>
      <year>1999</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Milk DX[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Milk DX</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Inhake 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Drane</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>If you're listening to Autechre albums chronologically, this recording will probably throw you off the loop for good. And the reason is that these recordings date back to 1995, and as the title indicates, were recorded for a John Peel programme broadcast on the same year. I really don't know why it took so long to release this material, but whatever, it's here. And is it good? Well, yes, surely. I wouldn't call it essential, though. Keeping in mind its chronological position, you can think of it as a "companion" to [a]Tri Repetae[/a]; and since there's already [a]Anvil Vapre[/a] to fit that position, if you only need the "essential" Autechre, you can skip this one without missing a lot.</p>

<p>But if you, like me, like to sink your teeth into an artist's output and get the maximum of it, make sure you get it; you won't be disappointed. You might be surprised, though, because most of this material is very firmly on the more experimental edge of Autechre's sound, especially for a 1995 recording. Also, the three tracks are very different from each other, which helps to create a nice balance. And as far as balance goes, [s]Inhake 2[/s] is the only track here that truly does not try to bend your brain in unpredictable directions. Actually, it is scarily straightforward and groove oriented for Autechre's standards. But the sound is amazing, crossing the grinding, metallic overtones of [a]Tri Repetae[/a] with some of the ambience and melody of [a]Amber[/a]. Go check it out on YouTube if you wish. The other two, now, stand at the opposite end of the spectrum. [s]Milk DX[/s] dares even to be unwelcoming, with disorienting, deeply intricate percussion patterns, and a moody, seasick ambience wavering on the bottom. But the effect is incredible, truly pushing the envelope without collapsing into all-out chaos. If there is <em>one</em> reason to get this record, this is it. But there is also [s]Drane[/s], which you definitely cannot miss. The similarities to [s]Drane2[/s] are fair enough to be noticed, but the song is solid and beautiful enough to stand on its own two feet, featuring intelligent (as always) drum patterns, and a lush, beautiful ambience. Halfway through, the duo starts to distort and twist that ambience around in many kinds of ways, and it just keeps going and going, and therefore all its 10 minutes of length are justified. Beautiful piece.</p>

<p>In short, don't expect a masterpiece, but you can get this one without fear that you'll just be listening to recycled old stuff. This is far, far from recycled, and worth your attention.</p>]]>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]Time to comment[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="ep7">
      <title>EP7</title>
      <year>1999</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Outpt[/s], [s]Maphive 6.1[/s], [s]Rpeg[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rpeg</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ccec</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Squeller</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Left Blank</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Outpt</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Dropp</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Liccflii</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Maphive 6.1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Zeiss Contarex</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Netlon Sentinel</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Pir</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>In spite of being labelled as an "EP", you can easily see this as another LP from the band. On vinyl, it was released in two parts ([a]EP7.1[/a] and [a]EP7.2[/a]), but the CD unified both parts. And yes, the title [a]EP7[/a] was given by the band (prompted by this, Warp Records "baptized" [a]LP5[/a] accordingly).</p>

<p>But all of that is petty nitpicking. What matters is the music, right? When it comes to Autechre, titles and labels become utterly irrelevant. The music here is... well, I'll be blunt. As an LP, this music feels eerily inessential. Following the pattern of LPs and EPs, you could think of this as a "companion" to [a]LP5[/a], but this time around, the album doesn't contribute much to "complement" the album. [a]LP5[/a] is fine the way it is. These tracks all have something going on, something pushing forwards, but the album as a whole seems to lack some kind of "push", you know? Some energy to propel it upwards. It doesn't suffer from the aimlessness of [a]Chiastic Slide[/a], though, which is good. Thing is: you may not enjoy [a]Chiastic Slide[/a], but most of the tracks certainly deserve some raised eyebrows. It was <em>interesting</em>. This time around, [a]EP7[/a] is more easily enjoyable, and the raised eyebrows will probably be there, but the album feels tame. Yes, <em>tame</em>. I know that's not necessarily bad, but considering the momentum of [a]LP5[/a], it might feel a bit underwhelming.</p>

<p>On the other hand, though, the album seems to have a fairly clear goal. It knows where it wants to go. This may result in a couple of these tracks sounding annoyingly alike, but I don't see a great trouble in that. I'm talking here specifically about a couple of tracks that are <em>very</em> percussion based, and basically wind those complex percussion patterns around each other, with some very vague (if any) ambience. They do sound cool, though, and despite the stylistic similarity, they're a great listen. I particularly like the aggressive metallic sound of [s]Squeller[/s] and the windy, hollow feel of [s]Left Blank[/s], which sort of feels like a wind tunnel or something. Those tracks, as well as the others that don't follow that pattern, do show one very strong tendency for Autechre: of experimenting with <em>sound itself</em>, in its more fundamental levels, breaking loose of the conventional notions of harmony and melody. If you take the more abstract and experimental releases, I believe you can find their roots in this release. Not that it sounds completely unmelodic and atonal: not at all. In fact, some of the highlights here are very harmony-centered. The opener [s]Rpeg[/s] is built on a catchy, quivering lead synth sound, which is explored in all its rhythmic and harmonic qualities in an upbeat groove. [s]Dropp[/s] is kind of a cross between a "pseudo-ambient" piece and their metallic percussion pieces, which works very impressively. [s]Outpt[/s] is sort of an oddity, featuring a very static, sparse rhythm, and moves solemnly along plaintive chord changes played on a pulsating, slowly disintegrating pad. It feels like the song was made to sound like the synthesizer is malfunctioning. The effect is strange, hypnotic and beatiful. But by far, the biggest oddity here is [s]Maphive 6.1[/s], which features synthesized reproductions of actual instruments (piano, chimes, timpani, etc.), but they are all bent and made to sound in very unnatural ways. I don't know if you agree, but I think it's very strange to hear Autechre playing with "realistic" samples, but it's strange in a <em>good</em> way.</p>

<p>I think it's a good approach to see this record as a "mixed bag", which is unusual for Autechre. I'm not saying the album is a random hodgepodge of odds and ends &mdash; far from that, and as I said before, there is a sort of overall direction for the album. But it's hard to imagine songs like [s]Ccec[/s] (which features fractured, stuttering samples of speech in it) and [s]Zeiss Contarex[/s] (a slow, dark, funky, crawling piece that sticks out like a sore thumb among the others) in other albums. The album is at times refreshing, at times predictable, but it never ceases to be interesting. It's far from a masterpiece, but it's easily recommended for listeners with a fledging interest for the many different aspects of the duo's music. Grab it and enjoy it.</p>
      ]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]Inpt[/l]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="peel2">
      <title>Peel Session 2</title>
      <year>2000</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Blifil[/s], [s]19 Headaches[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Gelk</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Blifil</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Gaekwad</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>19 Headaches</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Unlike the previous [a]Peel Session[/a], this release does not tear open such a huge hole in the space/time continuum, being in fact recorded and aired in 1999, a little more than a year before this release. A special feature about this album is that the tracks were titled by John Peel himself.</p>

<p>Anyway, these tracks date from the same period of the tracks from [a]EP7[/a], and as should be expected, there are quite a couple of stylistic parallels between the two releases. But the tracks here are considerably more adventurous and fearless. I find that a good way for describing the release: not necessarily innovative, not necessarily experimental, but <em>fearless</em>. If they rub you in a wrong way, well, that's your problem. In fact, the opening track here even dares to be deceptive: [s]Gelk[/s] starts out all melodic and cute, like it's going for a [a]Selected Ambient Works[/a] mood with more rhythmic syncopation and smartness, but halfway through, it slowly dismantles the melodic cuteness and then takes an abrupt left turn into a dark, cavernous slow funk sort of thing. A pretty unexpected contrast, creating a really interesting, lasting effect.</p>

<p>The other tracks move away from that kind of trickery and go straight into business. [s]Blifil[/s] is abrasive, fast, dissonant, metallic and disorienting, unlike anything from [a]EP7[/a]. In fact, it sounds like the evil sister of an [a]LP5[/a] track. The experimentation with rhythms and time signatures here are quite off the wall, too, but the band keeps sprinkling these little semblances of melody to create an ambivalence. For some reason, I never gave this track much attention, but now I realise it's probably the best one in here. [s]Gaekwad[/s] exchanges the busy, angry rhythms for strange, entwined little melodies, before they start playing around with really odd, off-beat percussion effects, while constantly changing rhythms and tempos. It's probably the most interesting track here, with its slow, restless transitions. As for the wittily titled [s]19 Headaches[/s], it's a lot less abrasive than you think, with very a understated, buzzy percussion section and notes running up and down these dissonant, "ugly" scales. That is, it's "headachy" in terms of harmony, and probably texture, and not in a predictable way. It's an odd, yet fitting close for this release. I believe this is one of the band's most intriguing releases, with a mixture of boldness and balance, of direction and adventurousness, that is not easily found in the duo's catalogue. Don't miss this if you're trudging forwards in the band's catalogue, and if you <em>started</em> in the latter part of their career, don't miss this either. The material here is quite unique.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]19 Comments[/l]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="confield">
      <title>Confield</title>
      <year>2001</year>
      <highpoints>[s]VI Scose Poise[/s], [s]Lentic Catachresis[/s], [s]Pen Expers[/s], [s]Uviol[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>VI Scose Poise</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Cfern</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Pen Expers</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Sim Gishel</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Parhelic Triangle</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Bine</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Eidetic Casein</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Uviol</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Lentic Catachresis</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>And here is where the critics go wild &mdash; either with gushing praise or with rabid panning. Pick your side. Myself, I don't pick sides, so stay tuned for a moderately balanced review.</p>

<p>[a]Confield[/a] is generally regarded as the starting point of Autechre's most experimental, abstract and avant-garde period. If you're following their releases in chronological order, without being aware of the stuff they would later do, this album will certainly sound pretty shocking and extreme to you. Now, if you <em>do</em> have some familiarity with their next releases, this album won't sound <em>all that</em> extreme. The primary reason for that is that a surprisingly large amount of tracks here are more in the "ambient" side of the field, going a lot more for texture and mood than rhythmic and sonic experimentation. But the tracks that are more on the abrasive side, well, those are guaranted to give you quite a shock.</p>

<p>The main distinguishing factors of [a]Confield[/a]'s are, firstly, a penchant for "ugly" sounds, used not as a contrast for the more pleasant and atmospheric sounds (like in [a]Tri Repetae[/a], [a]LP5[/a] and so on), but used in their own right. Sounds are used for what they are, and melody and harmony are sometimes discarded entirely (or almost entirely). We've heard traces of that on [a]Peel Session 2[/a], but here the stakes are much, much higher. But the second and, in my opinion, most radical factor is the disregard for rhythm. Yes, you've read that right. Just think for a minute about how daring that is for an "IDM" outfit. Just keep in mind that <em>nearly all<em> the modern electronic music (by that I'm referring to all the artists and all genres, sub-genres and sub-sub-genres that grew out of the 80's house movement, separating them from the academic electronic music of Ligeti and Stockhausen, as well as early pioneers like Perrey and Kingsley, Brian Eno, Tangerine Dream and so on) is based on the <em>pulse</em>, that is, in some form of steady, repetitive rhythm. This is, obviously, a stylistic choice, but that was also imposed by the drum machines and sequencers that those artists have used since day 1. Deconstructing melody was already commonplace for such artists. Deconstructing harmony was also nothing new, as Autechre was already displaying for a fairly long time. Deconstructing texture, one can say, is basically the whole point of the artists called "IDM". Even deconstructing rhythm was already been done, with artists like Venetian Snares playing around with odd time signatures (something Autechre themselves already did). But, now, <em>destroying the rhythmic stability</em>? Destroying <em>the pulse</em>? That is unthinkable! To destroy the pulse is to effecively destroy the center, core of electronic music. And in [a]Confield[/a], Autechre does exactly that.</p>

<p>The examples of such boldness are not as abundant as you may think, though. A couple of tracks here a very solid rhythmic foundation ([s]Cfern[/s], [s]Eidetic Casein[/s] and [s]Uviol[/s] come to mind), and the most they do is to up the ante in terms of syncopation, what with all those off-beat accents, delayed beats and so on. But at times, the band simply tears away the rhythmic foundation and let the texture spill all over the floor. This is displayed already from the very first track, [s]VI Scose Poise[/s], which is, however, a more "ambient" piece than anything else. But instead of beautiful chords and pad sounds, or "creepy" metallic ringing and echoes, the whole texture is dominated by a sound that's definitely reminiscent of water dripping on a metallic plate. But that very basic idea is pushed around and bent in unimaginable ways, as if time itself is being distorted. Eventually, the track finds its way to a very simple, but extraordinarily effective 4 note figure, giving it some tonal foundation with chord changes and so on. But the water keeps dripping and redripping, and the result must be heard to be believed. The track is basically a treatise on the band's philosophy from now on.</p>

<p>This "atmosphere" aspect returns in tracks like [s]Sim Gishel[/s], which boasts a heavy, pounding rhythm, but is intended more to put you in a trance than to invite you to dance (not that you can't dance to it, though; is there <em>any</em> music that can't be danced to? I don't think so), as the sounds beneath the rhythm keep whirring and whining, as if the sound files were accidentally corrupted by a malfunctioning hard drive. Yes, it definitely has that "glitch" flavour, but the effect is used solely for atmosphere and texture. Near halfway through, the rhythm starts suffering some severe transformations, as if it too is suffering from some hardware glitch. In fact, that's a pattern that's repeated in a handful of tracks here: the rhythm is stable for about half of the track, and then it starts to skip and stutter. The effect is amplified in [s]Parhelic Triangle[/s], except the percussive sounds used here are somehow harsher, and the atmosphere in the back feels more sinister and evocative. Eventually, the rhythmic basis is pretty much taken away, and the percussion sounds become just another element of texture. Elsewhere, [s]Bine[/s] simply refuses to establish any rhythm whatsoever, to the point where it's impossible to distinguish what are the "beats" and what is the "texture": everything fuses into a single, nightmarish spiral of sound. Some might complain about it beingt too long, in spite of being the shortest track in the album (about 5 minutes), but if you've listened to a fair share of Klaus Schulze records, you shouldn't be complaining about that.</p>

<p>But the album also has appeal for the fans of harder hitting electronic dance music, with the weirdly jazz-inspired [s]Cfern[/s], with its elegant, haunting harmonies and dissonances, and a rhythm that keeps expanding and contracting back to form, before falling into an understated, repetitive form. I really like this one, though not to the point of naming it one of my favourites. But its successor, [s]Pen Expers[/s], does earn that title, with its furious, relentless onslaught of fast, hard-hitting beats, and a massive emphasis on high frequency hisses and chirps. To me, that is the second most impressive track in terms of texture and structure, especially towards the middle, when a clear melody starts to rise from below the rhythm. I have noticed that the melody and chords sound somewhat like a transposed version of [s]An Ending (Ascent)[/s] from [a]Apollo: Atmospheres and Soundtracks[/a]. I wonder if it was intentional? Or it's just a distorted memory speaking in me? Whatever. The effect is extraordinary in this song. Towards the end, the album starts to become <em>really</em> unsettling, though, with pretty heavy and dark atmospheres, like in the endlessly plodding and menacing [s]Eidetic Casein[/s] and the cavernous [s]Uviol[/s]. Both tracks take the rhythmic experimentation a little lighter, but the harmonies and sounds are sufficiently unsettling. And yes, I am aware that this is entirely subjective: these tracks really evoke a feeling of dread. Finally, [s]Eidetic Casein[/s] brings this mood to a climax, with a slow rhythm and menacing background sounds, but suddenly the rhythm starts to oscillate wildly, and then the whole track collapses into a six minute long flurry of random percussion beating and atmospheric swirls. It's an unbelievable end to the album, equally fascinating and disturbing, almost like the track fell into quicksand and flails desperately for six minutes before pathetically sinking.</p>

<p>As much as I try to describe the album and overuse words like "texture" and "atmosphere", I don't think you can truly grasp what the album sounds like before giving it a listen. And I think that you <em>should</em> listen to it, if only to experience it, whether you enjoy it or not. For better or for worse, this album is a landmark.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]Comments![/l]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="graf">
      <title>Gantz Graf</title>
      <year>2002</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Gantz Graf[/s], [s]Cap.IV[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Gantz Graf</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Dial.</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Cap.IV</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The tradition of releasing a "companion EP" to every Autechre LP still lives on. This one EP is particularly odd, though: it's less than 20 minutes long, and was released as a single sided 12 inch record. But that's not the biggest deal. The thing about this album is that it's the wildest and most daring release the group has made this far. It's like [a]Confield[/a] was just a warming up, and here is the place where they let the steam burst out at full force.</p>

<p>The title track is only four minutes long, but it packs all the energy and all the challenge of the entire [a]Confield[/a]. It's like smashing a brick right in the middle of your face: it's noisy, filled with furiously grinding and clanging sounds, mininum amounts of melody, and a rhythm that's plainly impossible to tap your foot to. The song feels like it's going to burst at the seams at any moment, and it's as close to <em>pure chaos</em> as  the band has ever got. If you have heard [s]Bine[/s] and the ending to [s]Lentic Catachresis[/s], all I can say is that this is much more. In a word, it's <em>excessive</em>. But it's all to the band's merit; after all, who else was doing stuff like this back in that time? This is not experimentation just for the sake of experimentation: this is bringing an entire world of vision and expressiveness into electronic music. This music challenges all the "important works" of the 50's and such, because in spite of being to challenging, it's not a bit academic. [s]Gantz Graf[/s] is what happens when all the theory is put into practice, and I cannot fathom having any reaction other than praising it highly. And if you're wondering, <em>yes, I greatly enjoy listening to it</em>. While all the "brutal" and "aggressive" heavy metal in the world just leaves me cold, this does just the trick for me.</p>

<p>But we have more two tracks, right? They're not intended to match the level of frantic intensity of the title track, and instead they veer into a totally different direction. [s]Dial.[/s] is not very long, and it stablishes a herky-jerky and frantic, but steady rhythm, with all these dissonant chords bouncing all over the place. It's a song that lives somewhere in between [a]Peel Session 2[/a] and [a]Confield[/a], too tame for the latter, too paranoid for the earlier. For some reason, this track strikes me as somewhat humourous, like it's way to paranoid and scary to be taken seriously; but personally, I take that as a good thing, if you wouldn't guess.
]]></review>
      <rating>13</rating>
      <commentPhrase>And now, [l]your comments[/l].</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="oversteps">
      <title>Oversteps</title>
      <year>2010</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Treale[/s], [s]see on see[/s], [s]d-sho qub[/s], [s]ilanders[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>r ess</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>ilanders</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>known(1)</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>pt2pt8</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>qplay</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>see on see</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Treale</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>os veix3</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>O=0</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>d-sho qub</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>st epreo</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>redfall</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>krYlon</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Yuop</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>So it's definitive: Autechre does not want to fall into a formula anymore. If I once was anxious for [a]Quaristice[/a], expecting something following the line of [a]Untilted[/a], and eventually got shocked and subsequently blown away by how different and good it was, the same thing happened here with [a]Oversteps[/a], but in much higher degree... at least one order of magnitude higher, I believe.</p>

<p>The thing is, for some reason, the duo decided to retake two of the things they had nearly completely dropped from their pallete: <em>melody and harmony</em>. I'm not saying there was NO melody and NO harmony on their previous releases &mdash; they were, but they were always subdued and subordinated to something else. There was always one element speaking higher than them, and whenever you heard instances of harmony or melody, they were almost always subverted somehow. In this record, it's different: the focus is turned <em>completely towards them</em>, as if the music of Autechre has somehow turned inside out. You don't hear merely loose notes forming a dissonant pattern, or sketches of atmosphere crossing through the rhythmic jungles: you hear actual harmonic development, entwined lines of melody, atmosphere and harmony <em>ruling the rhythm</em>. Come to think of it, not even [a]Amber[/a] went that far! And if you want to make a case about [a]Incunabula[/a], well, the level of songcraft and development in that album doesn't even reach the feet of [a]Oversteps[/a].</p>

<p>For one, if [a]Quaristice[/a] was made almost entirely of "live" cuts and improvisations, [a]Oversteps[/a] is cleverly constructed right down to the nanosecond. In fact, it's so "crafted", that it is extremely easy to recognise the repeated loops and bars of music. This may be uncomfortable for the folks more used to the fearless and uncompromised boundary breaking of [a]Confield[/a] and [a]Untilted[/a]: here they'll have portions of music repeated <em>exactly</em> two or four times in a row, or even more. The focus here is not in tear down the very reality around you: they are clearly exploring the sonic fabric they're weaving as much as they can. They're not afraid of repetition here, and why should they? Isn't repetition one of the fundamentals of many kinds of electronic music, as well as other musics? Also, usually, one track will have a surprisingly small number of layers, counting bass lines, percussion, chords and melodies and so on, and the duo goes to extreme lengths to explore those layers as much as they can. So no more will it sound like the whole world is coming down and dissolving over you. ... well, maybe at times, but in general, not at all.</p>

<p>The result here is, plain and simple, one of the greatest triumphs in the entire career of Autechre. Okay, who am I kidding? This is my favourite Autechre album ever. This title once belonged to other albums, but at this stage, there is little doubt in my mind anymore. [a]Oversteps[/a] may not be their most innovative, the most cutting-edge or the most technically astounding release, but it definitely is the most gorgeous, the most precisely beautiful, the most intense, enriching, awe-inspiring, emotional and evocative album in their entire oeuvre. <em>Of course</em> this is a purely personal impression: music as abstract as this can hardly ever be described in absolute terms, and anything even remotely close to a consensus is nearly impossible. As much as some people think this is an awful stepback, a boring record with nothing new to say, others will say it's a huge advance, a promising step and stuff like that. Me, I just think this record is, in one word, gorgeous.</p>

<p>You could stick the label "ambient" to most tracks here, just as you could do with the tracks in [a]Amber[/a], but &mdash; surprise, surprise! &mdash; that would be a gross oversimplification. Even with all the repetitions, this isn't a static, "hovering-in-mid-air" kind of album. It has dynamics, however subtle, and the songs develop. Besides, the maximum track length here is a mere six minutes and a half: there are no huge, sprawling epics a la [s]Sublimit[/s] and [s]Surripere[/s], or even [s]Further[/s] and [s]Drane2[/s]. If you want to check out a practical example, [s]known(1)[/s] is one of the most iconic tracks here, with three different layers of piano-like melody (or harmony? Or rhythm? Actually, them seem midway towards melody, harmony <em>and</em> rhythm) being added one at a time, completed by a synth solo that is... well, I don't know what kind of person somehow figures that a solo that mixes sustained wavering notes with fragmented hiccups and choped buzzes can sound so beautiful and resonant, but either Booth or Brown (or both) <em>is</em> that kind of person. Those are the sole elements of the track, but it moves, it unfolds, it expands and moves forward.</p>

<p>To be frank, there are plenty of tracks here that repeat that thing of "different entwined layers of harmony/rhythm/melody all rolled up into one", and it annoyed me in first listens. But there's no reason to quibble about that when all tracks are so cleverly and carefully written: [s]see on see[/s] is probably the most proverbially beautiful of them all, featuring a sparkling, shimmering sound that seems to happily stroll along the line that separates it from "cheesy": it's very contemplative and uplifting, in spite of the haunting atmosphere. [s]O=0[/s] mixes quite bizarrely different sounds, such as bass lines sounding almost like old school analogue synths and a ring-modulated chime sound or something, that is [i]very[/i] rhythmically complex in spite of the 4/4 meter, and reaches a very dramatic and unexpected harmonic change halfway through. [s]redfall[/s] has a strangely meditative quality and emotional overtones &mdash; probably helped by that otherworldly reverb effect that makes the chimes fade into the vast unknown, while [s]krYlon[/s] is more melodic and boasts a "drier" sound, and its melodic development is something that must be heard to be believed, from the gradual, subtle harmonic motions to the dramatic, spine-tingling key change in the middle.</p>

<p>However, there are some pretty diverse tracks to shake things out of the "semi-ambient" sphere. [s]ilanders[/s], for example, seems to draw a little thing or to from what the kids call "dubstep" &mdash; it is completely defaced and transformed, however, with a very deep and growling bass line and chopped, fragmented yet seriously groovy drum sounds leading the song through all sorts of atmosphere and mood shifts. It's one of the band's most straightforwardly aggressive and heavy tracks, and it rules mercilessly. [s]qplay[/s] maintains that wonderous, introspective atmosphere, but mixed with bumpy rhythms and percussion sounds that sound like they were written by Venetian Snares after glomping a bottle of Valium. [s]d-sho qub[/s] is a true surprise, though, combining odd and disorienting sounds with a <em>disco-ish groove</em>, complete with a friendly synth riff. Yet, the whole groove slowly gets distorted and dismembered in classic [a]Confield[/a] fashion, before dissolving into a coda made with frightening chords by what sounds like a sampled male choir. Wow! Sounds like the soundtrack to a 70's horror film, underpinned by a deep, "underwater" percussion effect. Amazing: I would never imagine Autechre doing this before this record came out. The big highlight for me here, though, is [s]Treale[/s], a track that somehow brings together all the right sounds in just the perfect manner; if some songs here have that golden moment, when perspectives shift and hairs stand on end, this song is <em>chock full</em> of them. All these buzzing, noisy sounds and chopped percussion mingle amazingly with organ-like solos and chimy synthesizer patterns, and through its six minutes, it just never ceases to amaze. All the beauty and profoundness of the album is perfectly condensed in this track.</p>

<p>Those stand-out tracks occasionally bump into far more subdued and less remarkable tracks. [s]pt2ph8[/s] and [s]os veix3[/s] sound quite unfocused and never jump out of the speakers to truly grab the listener, but they fit perfectly along with the aesthetics of the album and are nice in their own right. The opening [s]r ess[/s] is extremely "introductory", featuring a <em>very long</em> fade-in, and a much more sparse atmosphere, but it serves greatly to let the listener sink into the album. I'm fond of [s]st epreo[/s] and the way its bumpy, stuttering rhythms bounce against the static and undisturbed melody, and [s]Yuop[/s] is an amazing closer, amassing huge, intricate and pounding layers and grow to huge heights and then gently fade away, as if bringing the listener back to the real world. All songs here, no exception, form an integral part of the experience overall. This may be the single most consistent and cohesive in Autechre's entire catalogue; as much as I love [a]Amber[/a] and [a]Untilted[/a] and [a]LP5[/a], none of them succeed in creating a single, cohesive experience as this album does.</p>

<p>Allow me to become defensive for a moment, now: I am, by not means, trying to say that Autechre is breaking a completely new ground here, that nobody did music like this before and that it's the best thing in the world. It's obvious that they are not creating a new style out of thin air, and I am just not able to mention similar excellent albums simply because of my lack of knowledge and experience. You may be led to believe that I love this album so much just because it is Autechre, and everything they do is genius. I assure you that is not the case: I was actually pretty sceptic towards this album for a few listens, and it was only when I decided to give myself away to it that these sounds truly burrowed under my brain and remained there. Would this have happened if this were any other artist or band other than Autechre? Yes, it would. If Autechre had released a truly lacklustre album, would I have tried hard to "get" it? I don't think so. It annoys me too that Autechre has such a fanatical following that is ready to bite into any bait they throw and proclaim it as genius, just as much as there are those who will damn the band forever if they try to deviate from the norm. Some fakes of this album were released, and all the fanatical fans fell in like ducks. It may seem like I'm a little duck who will fall for anything these guys do, but honestly, I really do think that this album <em>is all that good</em>. I like their early phase, and I also like their more experimental phase, and I don't think that qualifies me either as a "simpleton" or as an "elitist prick". So, please, don't let those prejudices affect you and do give this album a try. You may not adore it as much as I do, but I think it's one of their most important releases ever, and any person interested in electronic music should check it out. If anything, give a spin to [s]ilanders[/s] and [s]Treale[/s]. I doubt you'll be disappointed.</p>
]]></review>
      <rating>15</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s][l]qcomment[/l][/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
  </artist>
</update-list>