<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<update-list>
  <update-title>Squarepushing the circle</update-title>
  <update-link>http://sirmustapha.0sites.org/reviews/squarepusher</update-link>
  <update-text><![CDATA[Here you have a whole bunch o' Squarepusher reviews, counting his full-length LP's and several EP's. The omissions shall be filled in during the next weeks, but for now, there's plenty to enjoy, I hope!]]></update-text>
  <artist ref="squarepusher">
    <name>Squarepusher</name>
    <text><![CDATA[
<p>The great thing about history is that the garbage tends to be buried by the sands of time (wow, THAT was tacky! Since when have I been writing such horrible purple prose? Who am I now, Randall Munroe?), while the true gold remains in the surface. In one hand this is bad, because many people will <em>always</em> use that as "evidence" that music was perfect in the past and that is sucks now. That is compensated by the fact that, when you go read about electronic music, you're not flooded by the hacks and the cheapskates and the opportunists who took a ready formula and applied it a few times to make a couple of bucks; instead, you'll straight away meet names of true pioneers such as Richard D. James, Alex Patterson, Luke Vibert, Phil and Paul Hartnoll, Sean Booth and Rob Brown, and Tom Jenkinson. If you try to look for something in common in all those artists, you'll most likely figure out that they were not the kind of folks who'd stick to a formula and milk it 'till it ran dry. No, sir: they blurred limits between genres and sub-genres, tore down barriers and showed the world that music is a lot more interesting when, instead of dividing it, you stick all the bits together into one exciting, multicoloured world. And in this area, I'm pretty convinced that Tom Jenkinson stands out, tall and proud, among the rest.</p>

<p>In terms of being a good, interesting and revolutionary artist, Squarepusher gets some tough competition from the likes of Autechre and Aphex Twin, but the thing that makes him so different is that he didn't only stick to "electronic music": he brought so many outside influences and elements that, eventually, he'd turn his music into something you'd have a hard time qualifying as plain and simple "electronic" music. In one side of the spectrum, you have Kraftwerk: musicians who came out of the wildly experimental Krautrock scene, using electronics to enchance their flutes, guitars and whatnot, and eventually became a group determined to make the public believe they had implanted microchips in their brains: electronics <em>became</em> Kraftwerk, and the only thing they play in their live shows are laptops. Squarepusher went more or less the opposite way: coming out of the <em>jungle</em> territory, he embarked on a twisty journey to show that electronic music can not only mix-up, but <em>become one</em> with artsy avant-garde and fusion jazz, rock 'n' roll, classical music and anything else he could put his hands on. The difference is that Jenkinson was already into jazz and was already a true master of the bass guitar before he put out his first releases; so, his career wasn't really a "transition", but a slow, successful unfolding.</p>

<p>Already on his first major release, the album [a]Feed Me Weird Things[/a], you'll hear him making something you could call "electronic jazz fusion" or something, but on [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a], you could see that he was more at home making music for ravers and dancers and assorted party-going happy kids. After that, though, every album he put out was radically different from the previous one, and at this moment in time, it's pretty much impossible to tell what he's going to do next. In retrospect, his trajectory has been quite logical, but if you manage to predict his next move, you'll deserve a prize (not that <em>I</em> can give you one, though, but that goes without saying &mdash; ask Warp Records for one). So, when adventuring into the guy, be careful: if you are absolutely specific in your tastes, read carefully about every album before getting it. If, however, you're an adventurer and willing to go on a ride, either take his albums in order, or select one randomly and go for it. I'll try to give a clear guide on his releases on here to try to introduce his music to the novice reader; so, if you're allergic to anything danceable, of if you're horrified of anything even slightly jazzy, this page is (I hope) for you! But if you like everything, or if you're a veteran fan, there's still a lot of stuff for you. So go ahead, without further delays. Except if you want to go and get a cup of coffee or something; the page will be waiting. Unless there is a black-out, of course, but unfortunately that's beyond my reach.</p>]]></text>
    <album ref="conumber">
      <title>Conumber</title>
      <year>1995</year>
      <high-points>[s]Conumber[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Conumber</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Eviscerate</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Male Pill 5</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>213 (Maritime.epsosis)</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Eviscerate (Version)</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Spymania Theme</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The earliest release ever put out under the Squarepusher moniker is this EP released on the small Spymania label. This is the tricky thing about electronic music: there are so many labels, so many monikers for the same artist, so many weird releases before (and sometimes even <em>after</em>) the artist secures a contract with a big label (e.g. Warp Records), that getting an artist's complete catalogue can be a true pain, if not virtually impossible. This EP is really hard to find, but all the important tracks were later released on a compilation called [a]Burningn'n Tree[/a], so you don't need to hunt for the vinyl in order to hear this stuff. The only tracks that weren't rereleased are [s]213 (Maritime.epsosis)[/s] and [s]Spymania Theme[/s], and each are only 5 seconds long: the former is Jenkinson speaking through a distortion effect (<em>can somebody lend me a fiver?</em> or something to that effect), and the latter is a single bass riff. So yeah, if you skip this and go straight for the aforementioned compilation, you won't be missing much. I like the riff on [s]Spymania Theme[/s], though.</p>

<p>As for the other tracks, this is definitely good stuff. The style here is firmly grounded on drum 'n' bass and breakcore, with a little bit of jazz influence, and very little live bass playing. Most of the record serves as a showcase for Jenkinson's skills at programming breakneck, complicated-as-hell drum sequences. [s]Eviscerate[/s] is the most solid example: four minutes of drums going forwards, backwards, sideways, with snare rushes left and right and just a ghostly bass appearing here and there. Its ferocity and viciousness is what makes it an entertaining piece, instead of a cold genre exercise. [s]Male Pill 5[/s] has a more solid groove, and the variety of sounds and bass sounds keeps it entertaining during its eight minutes, and [s]Eviscerate (Version)[/s] doesn't really have much to do with the second track here: the drums aren't so visceral, and are countered by jazzy, contemplative synth chords.</p>

<p>The title track, though, is the one in which Jenkinson's talent shines the brightest: it's eleven minutes long, but never slacks, as it's constantly switching between mellower parts and more kick-in-your-face parts; beautiful and harmonic synth semi-melodies and dissonant jazzy licks and crashing chords. It has swing and dynamics, the grooves are all excellent, and the drum sounds are punchy and exciting. If Jenkinson really wanted to tell the world something cool was arriving, he succeeded with this track. It's also surprisingly sofisticated considering the more laid-back and humourous nature of the other tracks, meaning that he was really pouring all his skill on this one. It's no joke, baby.</p>

<p>The rating for this album is very high, considering this is an early and non essential release, but it's not high enough to convince you that you <em>must</em> go out in every second-hand store and every shop smelling of dust and cardboard looking for this release: it's a solid career start (though it technically isn't: Jenkinson had already put out some records under his name) but it's not really representative, and it's only a prelude for much, much better stuff to come. Get the compilation, or go looking for some digital rips if you <em>really</em> want to hear those two 5-second-long tracks. Or, if you're a frenzied collector, do try to get it, of course... though if that's your case, you probably already have it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Caaan sooomebody seeend me a [l]cooooooment[/l]?</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="things">
      <title>Feed Me Weird Things</title>
      <year>1996</year>
      <high-points>[s]Squarepusher Theme[/s], [s]Windscale 2[/s], [s]Tundra[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Squarepusher Theme</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tundra</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Swifty</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Dimotane Co</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Smedley's Melody</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Windscale 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>North Circular</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Goodnight Jade</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Theme from Ernest Borgnine</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>U.F.O.'s Over Leytonstone</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Kodack</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Future Gibbon</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>With groovy, odd guitar chords, almost Bossa Nova style, Tom Jenkinson welcomes you into his first full length Squarepusher LP. And really, [s]Squarepusher Theme[/s] alone guarantees this album ain't at all a waste of vinyl. The groovy, odd guitar chords make way for a tricky, mindbending mixture of funky bass and stuttering drum machine patterns, which eventually results in this beautiful texture of synthetic sounds and guitars over Jenkinson's beloved jungle-esque lightning fast rhythm. It's a hoot of a tune, and well deserving of being an "introduction" to the man's work.</p>

<p>It also lays the album's intentions quite clear. The moments when Jenkinson digests the "weird things" fed to him are surprisingly few &mdash; eventually, those lightning fast, stuttering drum machine patterns reach their epitome in [s]Dimotane Co[/s], which barely uses any other instruments. Not only it works as a "display" of his skill with programming those freaky machines, but it <em>is</em> a pretty cool song on its own, and indicates a path he'd keep on following for a long while. [s]North Circular[/s] goes a similar way, albeit with a less abrasive sound. It's certainly a nice way to get your legs working and maybe your shoulders jerking along, but personally, I'm more impressed by Jenkinson's jazzy workouts; after all, the man's really special gift is in combining those lightning fast jungle-esque beats with his twitchy, exploratory bass exercises, isn't it? And on that note, we're blessed by the incredibly cool [s]The Swifty[/s], which sets up a hell of an entertaining drum solo and follows it up with a "cool jazz" workout with Jenkinson soloing with his bass guitar over nice, soothing electric piano chords. Sounds like a recipe for any other kind of jazz, except this one is greatly sped up and carried forwards by synthetic drums. This approach, funnily enough, is given a far more humourous and lightweight in the short, jumpy [s]Smedley's Melody[/s], complete with wacky noises at the end. Yeah, the guy has a sense of humour, after all. Either way, [s]Squarepusher Theme[/s] and [s]The Swifty[/s] are probably how I'd personally summarise this album. Of course, the rest of the album has a lot to offer, but those two tracks are somehow special.</p>

<p>I don't want to sound like I am dismissing everything that is not "jazz meets breakcore", and I want to have my head struck by lightning and all my hair burnt off before I dare to reduce the 'Pushah to a "one trick pony". God forbid! But the fact is that this style <em>is</em> very unique and interesting, so interesting that it nearly overshadows the rest. But only nearly, because more careful listens manage to peel off all the interesting layers of Jenkinson's talent and creativity. The most "jungle" oriented track here is probably [s]Tundra[/s], and it's an incredible combination of atmosphere and rhythm, with untrivial harmonies and intricate layers of speedy drums that, instead of stumbling all over the place like the most chaotic breakcore workouts, try to stablish an interesting and engaging rhythmic flow. It's excellent. Even more impressive is [s]Windscale 2[/s], that features an incredible "battle" between the slower, more atmospheric layers of synths and bass guitar and the angry sounding drums that try to tear down the song into breakcore chaos; the atmosphere, here, is far more haunting and distressing than that of [s]Tundra[/s], and the effect is just beautiful. As you see, the things that interest me more are the moments in which Jenkinson is trying to blur the frontiers between electronic subgenres, and even between musical genres in a macroscopic scale &mdash; it is creativity and boldness at work! The few tracks that are less interested in breaking down barriers sound far less interesting; the two aforementioned "purely rhythmic" tracks [s]Dimotane Co[/s] and [s]North Circular[/s], as well as the melodic [s]Theme from Ernest Borgnine[/s] (which sounds to me like a jungle adaptation of some outtake from Aphex Twin's [a]Selected Ambient Works 85-92[/a], and I <em>don't</em> say this derogatorily) and the downtempo [s]U.F.O.'s Over Leytonstone[/s] just hold no comparison to the rest. But then again, does an artist have to <em>constantly</em> tear down barriers and break down expectations? He is already proving his worth in several tracks here; is it fair to condemn his less interesting efforts as something "unworthy"?</p>

<p>Nah, I don't think so. This record is a hell of a solid offering. It just isn't "impressive" because it doesn't pack all its innovation into a single solid punch, but I don't think that is a demerit. Of course I could say something like "this would have been an AMAZING 40 minute album", but do I have to? That's about as petty and annoying as saying "yeah, [a]Come to Daddy[/a] is a fine EP, but it would have made an AMAZING single". Making the long story short: if you want to get into Squarepusher, you can't miss this album. He has better ones, he has worse ones, but this one record is representative, diverse <em>and</em> good. And it's a lot of fun.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[a]Feed Me Weird [l]Comments[/l][/a]. No, wait...</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="rhombus">
      <title>Port Rhombus</title>
      <year>1996</year>
      <high-points>[s]Problem Child[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Port Rhombus</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Problem Child</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Significant Others</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Now here's one forgettable Squarepusher release if I've ever seen one. This 3-track EP sound very, very weak, especially considering that releases like this are commonly used by artists or labels to put out truly stand-out tracks, padded-out with a few filler tracks. You'd be led to believe that [s]Port Rhombus[/s] is really such stand-out track, but it pales in comparison with the stronger tracks from [a]Feed Me Weird Things[/a]. Okay, so it does have the jazzy touch of that beautiful electric piano line and that gentle bossa nova touch of the slow guitar chords and shoothing synth chords, but I can't find <em>anything</em> that makes this track more remarkable than [s]Squarepusher Theme[/s] or [s]Tundra[/s]. It <em>is</em> very good, of course, but good enough to justify a whole EP? Not for me.</p>

<p>In fact, the track that attracts my attention the most is the groovy, aggressive [s]Problem Child[/s], and it's mostly because of that funky bass riff and the strong, insistent drums accompanying it. It's a fun, humourous track. At the other end of the spectrum, [s]Significant Others[/s] has a much more haunting and dark atmosphere, with a deep reverb effect applied to the drums (an effect, in fact, that Jenkinson would use many times later) and strange synth effects, but it's way too insubstantial to truly cause a lasting impression. I apologise for the extremely short review, but there isn't much I can think of to say here; and in that case, it's better to not say anything, right? This EP is one I don't really recommend hunting for, but all the tracks here were included in the US edition of [a]Big Loada[/a], so you may be interested in getting that one.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Problem [l]Comment[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="plays">
      <title>Squarepusher Plays...</title>
      <year>1996</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="daddy">
      <title>Hard Normal Daddy</title>
      <year>1997</year>
      <high-points>[s]E8 Boogie[/s], [s]Coopers World[/s], [s]Papalon[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Coopers World</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Beep Street</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rustic Raver</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Anirog D4</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Chin Hippy</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Papalon</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>E8 Boogie</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Fat Controller</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Vic Acid</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Male Pill, part 13</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rat / P's and Q's</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rebus</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Now THIS is more like it! Definitely more like it! It's hard even to compare this album to [a]Feed Me Weird Things[/a] &mdash; not for being "so much better", but for taking every element from it and bringing it to absolutely superlative levels. The styles are perfected and built upon enormously, so what once was "underdeveloped", here is cranked up to 11 and set into hyperspace. Wanna see examples? Remember the percussion based excourses [s]North Circular[/s] and [s]Dimotane Co[/s]? Remember how they were rhythmic, odd, sometimes abrasive and hard-on-the-ears? Well, here, the 'Pushah allows himself to produce a single mere three minute track in the same style, [s]Chin Hippy[/s], but it's <em>so</em> far ahead of everything that it's even unfair to compare. The sounds attack you from all sides at once, fast and intricate as all hell, to the point where they're just downright smashed into each other and sound nearly chaotic.</p>

<p>It can be a hard listen, true &mdash; and I don't mean that in a "haha, you WUSSIES, you can't stand listening to REAL music!" &mdash; no, really, the sounds can be rather painful at times, and can induce you to call this guy a goddamn hack who is only able to produce random noise. But the minute you put your ears to work and listen carefully to all this "noise", you'll realise all that noise attack follow carefully built <em>patterns</em>, that actually repeat throughout the song and form a structure. You can even sketch "verses", "choruses" if you will &mdash; it's all there. It's just that it's so fast and complicated, crafted and perfected to such an extreme level of precision, that it sounds like hyperspace. That's pretty close to "breakcore", and would be brought to even more absurd and challenging levels by the likes of Venetian Snares. Even if you ignore all that, how can you call a "hack" a guy who wrote and recorded tracks like [s]Coopers World[/s], [s]Papalon[/s] and [s]Beep Street[/s]? Really, "noise" doesn't just magically turn into songs like these. As it's been documented, this album was more oriented towards rave and party music, and it's in fact true, as the album is more energetic, dynamic, readily uplifting and invigorating than the sometimes dark and obscure [a]Feed Me Weird Things[/a] (besides, there's no such thing as [s]Windscale 2[/s] and [s]U.F.O.'s Over Leytonstone[/s] here), but <em>at the same time</em> that the album pushes in that direction, it expands Jenkinson's skill at mixing breakbeats with jazz! Yes, <em>the same song</em> might have the two influences, not only "visible", but clearly developed. The prime example is the opening track, [s]Coopers World[/s], which unfolds out of a stuttering, fragmented, yet perfectly danceable drum rhythm with synchopated chords and exquisite harmonies. Along with the fizzy, swirling synths, you get the distinctive [a]Bitches Brew[/a]-y electric piano, wah-wah electric guitar and, of course, Tom's enchanted bass guitar. Aside from all that, it's catchy as all hell &mdash; from the beaty jazz themes at the first portion to the economic yet groovy solos in the middle. Without a doubt, this song is a great example of Squarepusher's incredible talent and skill.</p>

<p>Other songs follow its example, stressing different components. [s]Beep Street[/s] is a tad darker, more repetitive and insistent, and highlighting some <em>very</em> beautiful themes and riffs &mdash; sort of a more rhythmic, party-friendly, lighter [s]Tundra[/s]. There's no guitar and bass here, but on the other hand, you have a display of his incredible sense of coordination in setting multiple drum layers over each other and making them fit snugly. [s]Rustic Raver[/s], as the name might suggest, goes more firmly towards the rave crowds with a more chopped up, jerky rhythm and "acid"-like synth riffs. It works as a sort of "bridge" between the jazzier songs and [s]Chin Hippy[/s], and it's very nicely positioned. The album has a very logical progression, and the short, unsettling, melodic [s]Anirog D4[/s] seem to lead you towards somewhere safe before dunking you headfirst into [s]Chin Hippy[/s]. Wicked. And, of course, as it ends abruptly and jarringly, you're left with the 8 minute long, fantastic jazz excourse [s]Papalon[/s], in which the drum machine plays second fiddle to the way Jenkinson works those instruments into a sort of "jazz fusion for the 21st Century". It's just plain great, and he never gives too much credit to his own proficiency and focuses far more on the actual themes of the song, which aren't many and aren't too complex, but are solid and smart. Oddly enough, the moment when Jenkinson <em>does</em> let his playing skills take over almost completely produces my favourite track here: [s]E8 Boogie[/s]. Though it's not for the playing itself, but mostly the way it relentlessly hops and bops <em>everywhere at once</em>. This fast, punchy rhythm is bouncier and more invigorating than anything in the 'Pusher's entire catalogue, I believe. It's not just the drums: it's the funky clavinet, the synchopated breaks, the incredibly catchy synth riffs, and basically, everything else. This song gets me everytime, from the lonely guitar chords at the beginning to the drawn-out, hazy ending with the synth randomly bouncing around the scales.</p>

<p>The rest of the album goes back and forth among the things it already presented. [s]Fat Controller[/s] (PLEASE let that be a deliberate reference to <em>Thomas, the Tank Engine</em>) puts a halt on the fast rhythms and is possibly what you could call a "crowd pleaser", IF there could be such a thing. The rhythm is very cool, the main riff is fuzzed out beyond any possible recognition, it's filled with catchy samples and people chanting "pu-pu-pu-pump it up!" and even a moment for Jenkinson to show off his bass guitar pyrotechnics. It's just sort of overlong, I think, but this stuff must be AMAZING on a dancefloor &mdash; I am actually terrified of dancefloors, but if <em>this</em> track played out in a dance club, I'd go wild (don't picture that). [s]Vic Acid[/s], well, certainly is <em>not</em> overlong, and it might be Jenkinson's purest breakcore workout, framed by a claustrophobic acid synth part &mdash; perfect for raves but slightly underwhelming for the album as a whole. The final side revels on high speed jazz, with [s]Male Pill, part 13[/s] revisiting the "fusioncore" style with even more breakneck synchopated breaks and left turns, while [s]Rat / P's and Q's[/s] is quite awesomely unsettling and maniacal (comparisons with the <em>Psycho</em> theme, what with the rhythmic high pitched plucks, aren't at all over-the-top). If you see, yes, I definitely have a generall preference to the "Jazz" side of things than to the "Rave" side, but that's just me. I can understand someone being more blown away by [s]Vic Acid[/s] than by [s]E8 Boogie[/s] &mdash; and that only means they're <em>both</em> impressive. You're free to choose the side you want &mdash; and there's a high chance you'll end up absorbing and enjoying a bit of the other side as well. After all, I do enjoy a lot the "party music" aspect of the album, with very few exceptions. It's the thing as a whole, however, that wins me over.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>13</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Now [l]you send your comments[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="loada">
      <title>Big Loada</title>
      <year>1997</year>
      <high-points>[s]A Journey to Reedham (7.am Mix)[/s], [s]Come On My Selector[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>A Journey to Reedham (7.am Mix)</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Full Rinse (featuring MC Twin Tub)</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Massif (Stay Strong)</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Come On My Selector</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Body Builder (Dressing Gown Mix)</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Tequila Fish</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Jacques Mal Chance (Il n'a pas de chance)</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>This release was put out on the UK as an EP, with the exact running order listed above. Some may be familiar with the US release, which pushed [s]Come On My Selector[/s] all the way up to the first track, and included a few more tracks - the [a]Port Rhombus[/a] EP and two spare songs from the [s]Vic Acid[/s] single. Either way, to avoid redundancy and to stick to the "pure" (i.e. Elitist) side of things, I'm reviewing the original EP &mdash; which I feel is better, because there's just no other way to open this release than with the magnum opus [s]A Journey to Reedham[/s] &mdash; with the use of fast, rushing drum patterns, swirling synths and an insistent bass line, he creates a quite "epic" sounding track that, I assume, is meant to express the sensation of a journey by train. Of course, it's not all about the "sounds", and a large part of the song's success is that main theme that carries the song forwards, which showcases Jenkinson's ability to come up with untrivial, eccentric, yet extremely catchy melodies.</p>

<p>Now, as evidenced by this change in the US version, [s]Come On My Selector[/s] was the big hit of the record, even earning a Chris Cunningham video. It's a wild breakcore excourse, exquisite, crazy, speeding at breakneck pace through odd twists and breaks and synth riffs. It's definitely some of the wildest, most extreme stuff the 'Pushah has put out yet, and it feels maybe a wee bit too much like quirkiness for quirkiness' sake alone. Either way, the song <em>completely</em> wins me over at the end, when Jenkinson pulls out his bass guitar and does some solid riffing over the electronic noise fiesta. But then, this album also keeps expanding towards the electro-jazz style, with songs like [s]Massif[/s] and [s]Tequila Fish[/s]. The latter is particularly cool, with dissonant chords, a "laid back" riff popping up now and then, and a very cleverly designed, captivating structure. [s]Massif (Stay Strong)[/s] starts off very pleasantly, with a electric piano figure, and eventually builds a hell of a lot on top of that, including those wicked synth lines and the naturally amazing drum programming.</p>

<p>I guess the secret of the album, exactly like [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a], is the clever balance between the rhythm oriented material (which includes the frenzied [s]Full Rinse[/s] and the hazy, disorienting [s]The Body Builder[/s]) and the experimental jazzy stuff. Not that you should consider this as a "miniature" version of [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a], but it's definitely a fine accompaniment. The material here tends to be more upfront and defiant, and less "friendly". It's pretty great, either way &mdash; and even with the altered song arrangement, it's worth getting.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Come On My [l]Commentator[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="note">
      <title>Music Is Rotted One Note</title>
      <year>1998</year>
      <high-points>[s]Circular Flexing[/s], [s]My Sound[/s], [s]Theme from Vertical Hold[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Chunk-S</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Don't Go Plastic</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Dust Switch</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Curve 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>137 (Rinse)</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Parallelogram Bin</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Circular Flexing</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ill Descent</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>My Sound</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Drunken Style</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Theme from Vertical Hold</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ruin</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Shin Triad</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Step 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Last Ap Roach</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>It seems the 'Pushah got somewhat sick of working with sequencers. Well, at least that's what he acknowledges on the album's liner notes, but Jenkinson truthfully has a quirky sense of humour, and it seems sometimes that he is just willing to confuse people. Maybe he didn't get fed up with sequencers, and maybe he just wished to do something radically different, as this is what happens in this album: there is nothing, absolutely <em>nothing</em> here that could be called drum 'n' bass, breakcore, "intelligent dance music" or anything else that Jenkinson was doing with sequencers, samplers and synthesizers on his past releases. Instead, this album is chock full with jazz fusion! Actually, not quite: this album <em>IS</em> jazz fusion! It's a bass guitar, electric piano and <em>real drums</em> extravaganza. That's not to say that there are no electronics here, but they are mostly restricted to abstract sonic experimentations and some additional seasoning to the jazz pieces.</p>

<p>I believe this is one of those albums in which either you love the whole thing, or you just don't care about it, because there are very, VERY few tracks here that I'd count as stand-outs, and you'd only think of them as "stand-outs" if you dig the style. Only [s]My Sound[/s] could be salvaged by a casual fan who doesn't care much about Jenkinson's fusion jazz thing, as it is very mellow and much more melodic than anything else here. It is surprisingly beautiful, and <em>almost</em> doesn't fit the album; but I guess even the most hardcore fusion albums need a little ballad or two, right? As for the rest, don't expect any more ballads on here. The closest you get to a non-jazzy song here is, deceivingly enough, on the first track: [s]Chunk-S[/s] is funky, groovy and makes you want to dance on your chair. But then, [s]Don't Go Plastic[/s] throws you a cold water bucket of intense, free form rhythms, dissonant electric piano chords and bass improvisations, and THAT is the main rule here. Frankly, I far prefer the tracks there are based on a certain <em>theme</em>, like the cool, syncopated groove of [s]Theme from Vertical Hold[/s], and the incredible, tension building piano figure that drives forward [s]Circular Flexing[/s] and sort of return on the freaky [s]Ill Descent[/s].</p>

<p>On the other tracks, Jenkinson's style is, I feel, way too loose to spark anything truly amazing. Maybe it <em>is</em> his style, and I'm not confident enough to say he doesn't have competence to produce something truly good: he does, as the aforementioned [s]Circular Flexing[/s] proves. Points of interest are in the combinations between his most orthodox jazz and more experimental electronics, like in the unbelievable [s]Shin Triad[/s]. As for the "purely electronic" experiments, most times they are only there to make the album flow better, I believe. Exceptions include [s]Ruin[/s], which some quite terrifying synth explosions and crap like that, and the closing [s]Last Ap Roach[/s], which can be described as a darn good musical representation of a hangover, as some painful synth drones whine away as heavy drums keep banging away progressively slower and slower.</p>

<p>Frankly, if you are interested in Jenkinson as a musician, do not miss this album. Some of the stuff he does here is unique, and you'll hardly find it everywhere else. Do keep in mind that the styles displayed here <em>would</em> get revisited very often in his following records, so don't consider it a <em>necessity</em> if you're not a really interested fan. If you want just the essentials, don't feel obliged to get this one: the jazzier cuts in [a]Ultravisitor[/a] are likely to give you all the taste you need. I don't give this album anything higher than an 11 because it feels too much like an exercise and not like a real stab at making some seriously amazing music. He sounds restrained, like he's merely showing that he can do it, and not showing it all. I like my fusion jazz bold and daring; Squarepusher <em>is</em> bold and daring, but this isn't one of the best examples of that.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[a]Review Is Rotted One [l]Comment[/l][/a]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="mindphone">
      <title>Budakhan Mindphone</title>
      <year>1999</year>
      <high-points>[s]Fly Street[/s], [s]Iambic 5 Poetry[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Iambic 5 Poetry</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Fly Street</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Tide</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Splask</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Two Bass Hit (Dub)</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Varkatope</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Gong Acid</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The cover art describes this sort release as a "Mini-Album". Whatever; differences between LPs, EPs and whatnot don't matter much in this site. What matters, though, is that this record is a <em>fine, fine</em> release, and in my opinion is much more recommendable than [a]Music Is Rotted One Note[/a], even though it's not as groundbreaking. I mean, if you want to move from being "your fucking daddy" who does "lots of different styles of drum 'n' bass" to being a fusion jazz musician, there's no better way than doing a long, full length album with 15 tracks, right? Wrong: you do a double album with four 23-minute-long compositions. But that's for crazy people, and not for the 'Pushah. So, yeah, [a]Music Is Rotted One Note[/a] is a ballsy record in that aspect, but in the musical department, it's actually sort of tame.</p>

<p>It seems in THIS release, however, Jenkinson was willing to push boundaries he didn't push before, and is thus more recommendable for people who want to hear what electronic and breakcore-influenced jazz sounds like. I actually like this release quite a lot, even though there are truly no <em>OMG</em> amazing song and it doesn't amount to a true classic. It does, however, balance Jenkinson's chops with the drums and the bass guitar with a smart melodic sensibility with some truly wicked sound experimentation. Check out the <em>groovy as hell</em> [s]Fly Street[/s], arguably the best track here, with an irresistible rhythm carried forwards by electric piano and some "whistley" synthesized sounds. Likewise, there is the more drum 'n' bassy [s]Varkatope[/s], that seems to feature the 'Pushah's bass guitar plugged into a MIDI controller. It grooves fiercely, and the synthetic atmosphere in the background work really well. On a more mellow note, [s]Iambic 5 Poetry[/s] has a <em>really</em> beautiful melody played on mallets. I don't think we've had Jenkinson doing such a genuinely mellow and beautiful song yet. A quite surprising revelation.</p>

<p>Now, if you're interested in his bass playing, look no further than [s]Two Bass Hit (dub)[/s], which, as the name suggests, features two bass solos rocking over a steady, funky rhythm. It's entertaining as hell: he may be obsessed with his own playing, but he's trying to make you shake your body, and I won't be surprised if he succeeds. Another very important aspect here, though, is the successful marriage between his jazz intentions and his sonic experimentation. Check out [s]The Tide[/s], with its odd atmosphere and "hovering" feel, and the rhythmic concoction of [s]Splask[/s], featuring a really hypnotic metallic sound. As for [s]Gong Acid[/s], it's some of the most agressive and willingly defiant things Jenkinson has <em>ever</em> put out, consisting of many loops and samples of odd percussion creating conflicting, disorienting polyrhythms. To make matters worse, every thirty seconds or so, it switches tempo arbitrarily. It's likely you'll either be freaked out for all five minutes or it, or you'll rush to turn off the sound in horror; I am more leaning towards the first side, but I'm not <em>that</em> much of a freak, mind you. I just like the effect. So, consider yourself warned: even though I seriously recommend you to get this album, I won't guarantee you'll like <em>everything</em> here. And keep in mind it's only a half hour long: don't pay a fortune on it. If you want to pay a fortune for something, do it on [a]Ultravisitor[/a] &mdash; but we're yet to get there, right?</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Now [l]you send your comments[/l].</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="priest">
      <title>Maximum Priest</title>
      <year>1999</year>
      <high-points>[s]Song: Our Underwater Torch[/s], [s]Decathlon Oxide[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Song: Our Underwater Torch</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Decathlon Oxide</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>You're Going Down</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Cranium Oxide</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Two Bass Hit (AE Mix)</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Circular Flexing (Yee-King Mix)</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Shin Triad (Wagonchrist Mix)</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>If you're one of those guys who absolutely can't stand the thought of his favourite artist doing an album that is even merely remotely close to "sub-par", then you're going to hate this album; not much because it's bad, but because it's an obvious throwaway. It's less than 30 minutes long, only one side is made of original Pusher material, while the other is a set of remixes by assorted electronica artists. The original material is, overall, pretty standard and average considering Jenkinson's output so far, with the exception of one track: [s]Song: Underwater Torch[/s] is pretty much unlike anything he has done so far, a slow, dirge-like piece driven by Jenkinson's usual jazzy drums and a mournful, ghostly organ. While the "underwater" idea is carried well by the track, the overwhelming sensation here is of a dirge. It's absolutely strange, yet amazing.</p>

<p>As for the rest, there's a great, dark and atmospheric breakcore-ish workout in [s]Decathlon Oxide[/s], which reaches out back to [a]Big Loada[/a] in terms of style. [s]You're Going Down[/s] has a weird breakdown dance section with a strange vocal sample sandwiched between a <em>very</em> [a]Budakhan Mindphone[/a]-ish riff for vibraphone. It's not really very interesting, as it's just a combination of two relatively typical Jenkinson pieces. [s]Cranium Oxide[/s] is nothing but a deliberately moronic 30 second piece of what sounds like someone drilling a hole in someone's head. I have no idea if this is a sample from somewhere or is Jenkinson made it himself, but it doesn't matter. The second side has three mixes of tracks from [a]Music Is Rotted One Note[/a], and they're surprisingly good. [s]Two Bass Hit[/s] is remixed by Autechre, and it really sounds like it could fit [a]EP7[/a], with a cold and robotic beat underpinning heavily filtered and processed samples of Jenkinson's bass solos. It's less interesting than most of Autechre's solo affairs, but it works. Yee-King's remix of [s]Circular Flexing[/s] is good, one time using breakcore drums and acid bass lines, and other time using Jenkinson's own drum freakouts to carry forth the rhythm. My favourite here, though, is Luke Vibert's "Wagonchrist" remix of [s]Shin Triad[/s], which has a playful, dance-friendly rhythm, and Jenkinson's freaky solos and noises are used smartly. Overall, though, this record isn't at all mandatory for the non-obsessive Squarepusher fan, even though [s]Song: Our Underwater Torch[/s] DEFINITELY deserves a spin. Try to get it somehow if you can, but don't bother too much about the record.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]Your comments requested![/l]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="sixteen">
      <title>Selection Sixteen</title>
      <year>1999</year>
      <high-points>[s]Tomorrow World[/s], [s]Dedicated Loop[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The 'Eye</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Square Rave</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Time Borb</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Dedicated Loop</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tomorrow World</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Cool Veil</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Schizm Track #1</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Freeway</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Snake Pass</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Yo</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Mind Rubbers</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Tesko</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Acid Tape Track</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>8 Bit Mix #1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>8 Bit Mix #2</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Schizm Track #2 Mix</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Ceephax Mix</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>In his ongoing efforts to puzzle his followers as much as possible, Jenkinson releases this completely uncohesive and detached album. If [a]Budakhan Mindphone[/a] sounds like he's trying to smash all his influences together into something totally new, here it seems like he's trying to pull them apart: just as much as you get songs that are almost purely dance and rave oriented, you've got jokey, ultra-short jazz pastiches that almost sound like he's <em>making fun</em> of his jazzier ambitions. Either that or he inserted them there just to be obnoxious and remind his listeners that he's not some lowly "producer" of rave music. Or something. Hell, I don't know.</p>

<p>What I know is that, amazingly, this stuff works, and the "dance" oriented material is really, really good. Okay, so it does include the mindboggingly repetitive and dull [s]Snake Pass[/s]. Okay, I understand that people like to dance to repetitive, monotonous stuff, and that music is not bad by default, but come on. Whether he did this for contrast, or just for fun, or both, I don't know, but it contrasts here in a bad way and it's not terribly fun or danceable. But the others? They're pretty much all good! [s]Square Rave[/s] has some amazing, catchy atmospheric effects adding quite a lot of depth to an otherwise unsurprising acid influenced dance tune, while [s]Dedicated Loop[/s] is intelligently frantic and groovy &mdash; don't be misled by its "atmospheric" introduction! On the "not so dancey" line, we have the gorgeous [s]Tomorrow World[/s], that combines perfectly the Pusher's melodic skills with the machinegun-style drum programming, harking back to the finest moments from [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a] and [a]Feed Me Weird Things[/a]. This is a definite classic. [s]Schizm Track #1[/s], on the other hand, is just strange; strange in a good way, I mean. The rhythm is slow and almost bluesy, and the whole thing is carried by Jenkinson's bass playing and a vocal sample that works, oddly enough, as rhythm. It's definitely an unsual track, and that's coming from a guy who's already done bizarre stuff such as [s]Gong Acid[/s].</p>

<p>Towards the end of the album, we get a fair share of the more frantic breakcore a la [a]Come On My Selector[/a] with the vicious, frenzied [s]Mind Rubbers[/s] and the more repetitive, dance oriented [s]Acid Tape Track[/s], which, as the name suggests, combines an "acid" bass riff with machine-gun rhythms. Pretty cool, but not one of the most impressive tracks in the Pusher's repertoire. Now, if you're curious about the jazzy intermezzi, keep in mind that there's some definitely jokey stuff like the 30-second-long [s]Yo[/s] and the <em>20-second-long</em> [s]Tesko[/s], this one featuring weird vocal noises. But there's some cool, more rhythmic, yet short tunes like [s]Time Borb[/s] and [s]Freeway[/s], my favourite here. It definitely sounds like Jenkinson included them here to make the album more bumpy and whimsical, as they <em>in no means</em> echo the serious explorations of [a]Music Is Rotted One Note[/a] and [a]Budakhan Mindphone[/a]. The focus, definitely, is on the electronic songs, and there is plenty of great stuff here to be checked out. If you're a fan of [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a], try this one.</p>

<p>Nearly every release of the album includes an extra EP titled [a]Anti-Greylord Protection Scheme Prelude[/a], which... ehn, doesn't add much to the album. But then again, it's 12 minutes long. The two [s]8 Bit Mix[/s] tracks are 1-minute-long collages of pretty creepy sounds. [s]Schizm Track #2 Mix[/s] doesn't really have too much to do with the first [s]Schizm Track[/s], as it is a lot closer to a tradicional acid house track, only with a groovier, funkier rhythm instead of the straightforward four-to-the-floor rhythm of yore, and a lot of weird atmosphere added to it. Not particularly dance friendly, but interesting. As for [s]Ceephax Mix[/s], there's no way to know <em>which</em> track was remixed here, but it was done by Squarepusher's brother, Andy Jenkinson, also known as Ceephax Acid Crew, or simply Ceephax. His track is a good one, with a haunting, eerie feel, with stuttering and reverbered drums underpinning an acid bassline and synth chords. It's an interesting addendum to the album, but the "proper" album itself overshadows most of it. As far as Jenkinson's more electronic and dance-oriented albums go, this one is no [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a], but then again, what is? It is, however, diverse and interesting, and a great listen overall.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]Your comments requested[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="plastic">
      <title>Go Plastic</title>
      <year>2001</year>
      <high-points>[s]The Exploding Psychology[/s], [s]Go! Spastic[/s], [s]Tommib[/s], [s]My Red Hot Car[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>My Red Hot Car</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Boneville Occident</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Go! Spastic</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Metteng Excuske v1.2</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Exploding Psychology</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>I Wish You Could Talk</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Greenways Trajectory</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tommib</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>My Fucking Sound</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Plaistow Flex Out</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>If [a]Music Was Rotted One Note[/a] was the 'Pushah's jazz fusion extravaganza, then this his definitely his breakcore extravaganza. Funny how the earlier album had a statement about him being sick of sequencers and craving for a live sound, and featured a track called [s]Don't Go Plastic[/s], while this release has him claiming he got sick of live instruments and wanted to go back to electronics and is titled [a]Go Plastic[/a]. Either he was very clever in thinking of titles, or this whole thing was planned from the start; and from what I know of Jenkinson, this last hypothesis doesn't sound at all unlikely. Either way, if you're a fan of his freakier and more frantic electronic experiments like [s]Come On My Selector[/s] and [s]Chin Hippy[/s], then look no further than this album and get it now. The extent of Jenkinson's electronic craziness here is unsurpassed. Of course, it is all marked by his unusual sophistication and intellectuality, so you'll never hear him trying to rip your eardrums off like fellows such as Venetian Snares, but yes, this makes [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a] sound like fairground music.</p>

<p>The first track actually suggests otherwise, as [s]My Red Hot Car[/s] is basically a fair share of breakcoreish <em>pop</em>, with Jenkinson himself delivering some singing about something that is definitely much raunchier than a red hot <em>car</em>, if you know what I mean. But this isn't just some <em>pop</em> tune, as it is constantly fragmented, twisted and screwed up with electronic twists and turns, and the breakdown in the middle will either make you shake your bones for good or, at least, put your brain in a good, nice knot. Immediately afterwards, the album pulls all stops and throws you headfirst into a world of completely free form, uncompromised electronic freak outs. Sometimes the actual track separations don't matter much, as several tracks here are reaching out for the same direction, but each one using its own tricks and features. [s]Boneville Occident[/s] actually has a slightly more orthodox structure and a handful of electronic "melodies", but it's already a nice display of the rhythmic nightmare the 'Pushah conjures here. [s]Go! Spastic[/s] is looser and harder to pin down, and it goes as far as including a pseudo hip hop portion halfway through. [s]Greenways Trajectory[/s] has a truly mindbending part in which the whole things starts to progressively slow down all the way to a grinding stop, and [s]My Fucking Sound[/s] has considerably more disturbing and less danceable rhythms. I mean, I doubt I'd be able to dance to the rhythms of [s]Go! Spastic[/s], but I could at least try; with these two last tracks, though, I'd rather pass.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, there are quite a couple of different, interesting cuts in this record that sort of break free from the "formula". My definite favourite is [s]The Exploding Psychology[/s], which has a fast, frenzied dance section bookended by slower, oddly atmospheric portions. Towards the end, Jenkinson introduces a plaintive, strangely affecting melody that delivers the song towards a quite melancholy ending. I just <em>love</em> it how he mixes his furious rhythm with frighteningly beautiful melodies, and the result is amazing. To me, this is the highlight of the record. [s]I Wish I Could talk[/s] is more of a purely melodic song &mdash; the fast, incessant rhythm is there, but the focus is put on a beautiful descending chord pattern. Meanwhile, [s]Plaistow Flex Out[/s] is a sombre, slow closer to the album, featuring dark percussion sounds and a strange synth solo, which is probably Jenkinson's bass plugged into one of his magic boxes. It's a quite unexpected closer. But, even more unexpected, is the short [s]Tommib[/s], an utterly gorgeous and simple piece for electric piano. Even if it's just a few bars repeated through the track, the melody and the unusual sound of the piano are wonderfully evocative, and its place between two of the most vicious tracks here is admirable.</p>

<p>As annoyed as I am to say this, [a]Go Plastic[/a] is a record that defies any textual description. It <em>is</em> noisy, it is often plainly chaotic, and sometimes it simply wants to make you feel pain, but the sheer amount of craft and attention to detail here is breathtaking. Of course, I'm not one to enjoy the effort that went into a piece of music instead of the music itself; on the contrary, I'm one of those who says that, even if you spend years constructing an incredibly intricate tower of shit, it is <em>still shit</em>. The thing here is not that I'm admiring the effort: the effort is just a clear indication that Jenkinson was making <em>music</em>, not something openly defiant just for the shock value. The faint of the heart may stay the hell away from this, but I dub this one of Squarepusher's finest records. Yes, I <em>dig</em> the noise.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>13</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]SEND SOME FUCKING COMMENTS[/l] for the 'Pushah!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="squarepusher">
      <title>Do You Know Squarepusher</title>
      <year>2002</year>
      <high-points>[s]Do You Know Squarepusher[/s], [s]Love Will Tear Us Apart[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Do You Know Squarepusher</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>F-Train</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Kill Robok</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Anstromm-Feck 4</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Conc 2 Symmetriac</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Mutilation Colony</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Love Will Tear Us Apart</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Either Jenkinson really didn't know where to go next, or he was <em>seriously</em> willing to screw up with his listeners. Yes, he's had quite a few "dead end" EPs out there, but none of them sound quite like this one! See, the title track in this release was previously released as a single-sided vinyl single, and it is a truly brilliant track that stands up quite well against the best cuts from [a]Go Plastic[/a] &mdash; it's slower and less chaotic, but the rhythms and melodies he extracts out of his machines here are quite incredible and a wee bit exotic too. Also, the use of vocal samples as rhythmic elements is truly impressive, and not very common in the Pusher's catalogue. In short, this song is superb in every sense.</p>

<p>What comes next, then, is a hodgepodge of diversified <em>stuff</em>. Yeah, "stuff" is the best way I can refer to this: it's a completely inconsistent and loose set of tracks that aim at several different places at once. I have nothing against inconsistency in itself, as [a]Selection Sixteen[/a] used this to a good effect. But here, not only the tracks don't fit each other, but they barely stand up straight. You've got [s]F-Train[/s] and [s]Kill Robok[/s], which are purely rhythmic explorations with all sorts of sounds and samples smashing into each other and flying all around the place. The earlier track is at least remarkable because Jenkinson used his own voice as an element: he reads incomprehensible texts of questionable origin, which don't seem to mean nothing, and it's used mostly for the sonic effect, because there's no rhythm at all in his speech. No, folks, he isn't "rapping". It's quite cool, as he speaks in a hurried, frenzied monotone, but the track itself doesn't do much with it. [s]Kill Robok[/s] is more vicious, but it's far less exciting than anything in [a]Go Plastic[/a]. All that stuttering and pounding doesn't seem to be there to <em>entertain</em>, you know? I have to admit that I like the crazy-as-hell drum 'n' bass freak out of [s]Anstromm-Feck 4[/s], with Jenkinson delivering a bass solo fed through a fuzzy, dirty synth bass. In one hand, it almost sounds like the 'Pushah is desperate to prove he still got the chops to do something fast 'n' furious, but on the other hand, he <em>does</em> have the chops and he sure does deliver. Colour me impressed.</p>

<p>Then we flip the side and are faced with 12 minutes of ambient sonic explorations, in the form of the very very short [s]Conc 2 Symmetriac[/s] and the very very long [s]Mutilation Colony[/s]. The only way to tell them apart is that the latter starts with some haunting and very atmospheric organ-like drones, because otherwise, both of them are completely devoid of rhythm, melody, harmony and any discernible structure. Nothing <em>wrong</em> with that, but this is the kind of stuff that is better left for 20th century "classical" composers who wrote similiar pieces and got hundreds and hundreds of academic papers on how Ligeti's [s]Artikulation[/s] is a fantastic and terribly relevant piece of "electroacoustic" music while guitar rock is just horrible, unmusical noise (and notice that I <em>do enjoy</em> [s]Artikulation[/s], as well as some other similar pieces); I mean, you can at least be impressed with how those guys were shaking the very foundations of the extremely rigorous and conservative world of classical music, but in electronic music, a track like [s]Mutilation Colony[/s] doesn't do that! But of course, that doesn't mean that it can't be enjoyed, and enjoying or not those two tracks is heavily dependent on my mood. Problem is that they are terribly lacking in dynamics. There's a part near the end when the music really goes haywire, and the effect is pretty cool. It's just... unexciting overall. And, obviously, Jenkinson just <em>has</em> to throw another curveball and end this overall "brutal and digital" record with a [a]Budakhan Mindphone[/a]esque sped-up jazzy rendition of Joy Division's [s]Love Will Tear Us Apart[/s]! No, it's not a remix, it's a <em>cover</em>, and Jenkinson <em>sings in it</em>! And wanna know? <em>I love it!</em> It's a beautiful, sophisticated version, turning the dire and hollow sound of the original into a breezy, almost dreamy atmosphere, and Jenkinson's almost whispered vocals really work here. It's hard to imagine that a song so iconic and brilliant as that could be turned upside its head and yield something so good.</p>

<p>To make things even stranger, the CD issue of this record features a second disc with, get this, <em>a live recording</em> of Squarepusher in Japan. Okay, so the fans will definitely want this as it is his only official live recording (until [a]Solo Electric Bass 1[/a] came out, but that one is a jazz record!), but, frankly, it's pretty pointless. The songs (taken entirely from this record and [a]Go Plastic[/a], but also featuring a composition titled [s]Direct to Mental[/s] which is unique to this release) are virtually identical to their studio counterparts, with only a few, sporadic bits of manipulation and distortion; and given the absence of details about that performance, it's impossible to tell what was being done live on the spot and what was preprogrammed. Of course, it was probably a hoot and a half to <em>be there</em>, but listening to it is only interesting to hear Jenkinson so enthusiastically inviting the audience to participate and to "MAKE SOME FUCKING NOISE for the 'Pushah!" with him. The folks in the audience was sure doing it and diggin' it all.</p>

<p>I definitely don't want to dump crap on this record, because it doesn't deserve any bit of hatred. Face it: Jenkinson could have done a lot worse than this. And even if you think it's a lazy and uninspired record, it has its moments. Unfortunately it doesn't seem too easy to get the vinyl issue of the title track, but ehh, you'll hardly want to throw this CD on the wall if you do get it... at least if you listen to it expecting a lot less than a masterpiece. At best, you may be pleasantly surprised. I don't dismiss this album, really: I do enjoy it sometimes, and I like having it around. I mean, where else can I listen to Tom Jenkinson singing Joy Division? That's right: nowhere else.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Do You Know [l]Comments[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="ultravisitor">
      <title>Ultravisitor</title>
      <year>2004</year>
      <high-points>[s]Iambic 9 Poetry[/s], [s]Tetra-Sync[/s], [s]Circlewave[/s], [s]Ultravisitor[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Ultravisitor</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>I Fulcrum</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Iambic 9 Poetry</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Andrei</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>50 Cycles</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Menelec</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>C-Town Smash</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Steinbolt</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>An Arched Pathway</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Telluric Piece</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>District Line II</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Circlewave</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tetra-Sync</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tommib Help Buss</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Every Day I Love</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>For the first time ever, the cover of a Squarepusher features his face, undistorted and unmanipulated; in fact, it's just a plain ol' portrait. And why? I always assumed that this record was meant as a "musical self-portrait" of the artist, in the sense that it was supposed to show <em>all sides of Squarepusher</em>, at least the sides he displayed until then. So, is it possible to a single record showcasing <em>everything</em> the Pusher could do, and still make it cohesive and coherent? Judging by this album, what I can say is <em>like hell it is</em>!</p>

<p>This was the first Squarepusher record I've ever heard, and it is a mighty fine introduction to the man: it's a balanced and varied album, <em>and</em> it's excellent. Not just that, it's <em>perfect</em>: there are no loose ends, no missing bits, not a single dull moment. Jenkinson really pulled himself together to produce a masterpiece, and it is pretty obvious that this album had a special significance to him. But then again, maybe it's just me: I prefer albums that are multilayered and consisted of many different parts that match together, instead of an album that extracts as much as a possible from a single aspect. And Jenkinson really has a lot of different stuff to offer, from mellow classical guitar pieces to rapid-fire avant-garde bass guitar solos, from big one-man-ensemble compositions to stuttering drum 'n' bass, from melodic and carefully written electronic pieces to insanity-inducing breakcore from Hell.</p>

<p>One curious thing is that there are several live cuts in the album, that is, pieces and fragments culled from live recordings. In many of those instances, he deliberately let the audience noise in. In an interview from a link that is unfortunately dead (R.I.P.), he stated that he left the shouts and yelps of the audience as if to show that his fans "don't understand" what he's doing yet will cheer at anything he does; and indeed, the audience will scream and shout as he bashes away some really out-there avant-garde jazz influenced bass solos, getting damn close to being obnoxious. I wouldn't be surprised if he was using this technique to insult his audience, but that doesn't even make sense: all live recordings of him show that he constantly <em>encourages</em> audience participation, and you don't need much more than the live disc from [a]Do You Know Squarepusher[/a] to hear him going "LET'S MAKE SOME FUCKING NOISE!" to the audience. And even in <em>this</em> album: if you listen closely to [s]An Arched Pathway[/s] (that is, after all the horrible ear-destructive noise goes away), there's a short moment when he mutes the bass guitar and yells (off the mic, apparently) "Hello!" to the audience, which responds enthusiastically. So yeah, I seriously doubt he dislikes the yells.</p>

<p>But the inclusion of live bits isn't at all distracting: the musical content here remains consistent, so much that it's difficult to pull the pieces apart and decide where to start from. Say, what about the "purely electronic" pieces? The title track kicks off the album in a high note: even though it features a fast, drum 'n' bass-y rhythm, it's actually a quite complex, multipart composition featuring a wicked synth-bass solo, beautiful and haunting ambience, and a twisty synth melody that is, at the same time, sophisticated, abstract and evocative. For the, the best part is the second half, when the song locks in a chaotic, polyrhythmic percussion loop, bulding up until it dissolves into a beautiful atmospheric crescendo. It's a great way to start: you get a taste of the Pusher "tearing your fucking face off", but are gently reminded that you're not in for a predictable ride. Just as the electronic extravaganza ends, Jenkinson steps in with his bass guitar for the solo [s]I Fulcrum[/s], which is at times slow and meditative, at times fast and funky, at times completely uncompromised and free-form. Also, the bass (apparently a 6-string) is plugged into a wide array of effects, like an octave shifter (doubles every note, but one octave higher, creating a fat, round jazz sound) and what seems like a pedal-controlled ring generator, therefore allowing Jenkinson to twist the sound in all sorts of ways. The result is surprisingly entertaining and beautiful; and like that one, there is the fast 'n' groovy [s]C-Town Smash[/s], that almost sounds like a breakcore song played on solo bass (!), and the more avant-garde [s]An Arched Pathway[/s], which for the first minute or so has a stretch of horrible, uninterrupted noise over the soloing. Yikes! If you have heard [a]Mogwai Young Team[/a], this is almost an equivalent of [s]With Portfolio[/s] &mdash; yes, it is THAT painful. If you don't know that album, well, imagine having a pneumatic drill inside your ears and you've got a decent clue.</p>

<p>The jazz influence returns in a more full-fledged form in other tracks, and I should say that they're some of the strongest highlights on the album. You don't need to go further than [s]Iambic 9 Poetry[/s] to witness Jenkinson's grasp on melody, tension building and careful song construction. The whole thing starts off a deceitfully simple, yet gorgeous little melody, but it just doesn't stop progressing, moving from groove to groove in a neverending crescendo: when you think it's reaching the top, the rhythm breaks down to an exciting, chaotic, free-form improvisation, yet with the melody ruling above the chaos, and <em>then</em>, the rhythm goes into hyperspace mode and you'll know there's no coming back. It's an incredible performance, with some of Jenkinson's best drumming ever. Also, the song blurs completely the line between "spontaneous" performance and studio manipulation, as the free-form drumming is countered by hacked and slashes samples or tuned percussion, guitar and whatnot. In short, it's an incredible track and one of my favourites in the entire Squarepusher oeuvre. But it doesn't end there! Towards the end, the 'Pushah introduces us to [s]Circlewave[/s], that is similar in the sense that the whole song slowly builds off a simple melody. The melody is gorgeous, and almost dirge-like, and the layers of rhythm and harmony added by Jenkinson, instrument after instrument, is a marvel. The build is broken by some stage bantering ("Hello. ... ... <em>HELLOWW!</em>"), but then he cuts off into [s]Tetra-Sync[/s], the album's tour de force, majestic in every sense, a 9 minute masterpiece that could as well go on for <em>18</em> minutes without me noticing. Instead of a simple melody, the song is built on a beautifully tense, elaborate chord progression. If this is the natural culmination of his "jazz fusion" period, then everything is fully justified: [a]Music Is Rotted One Note[/a] could have been 60 minutes of studio dickery, but if it justifies [s]Tetra-Sync[/s], then it's all fair.</p>

<p>Fans of the electronic side of the 'Pushah won't be disappointed. Remember when I talked about [s]F-Train[/s], and how it featured Jenkinson rambling through the track with some uncomprehensible text? The trick is redone here, but the level of complexity and sonic construction is cranked up two 11. If I had to describe this in a short term, I'd say it's <em>hip hop from Hell</em>: the crazy and disoriented noise is all there, but oddly enough, it serves to create <em>a groove</em>; and of course, Jenkinson adds a funky layer of guitar and bass, making the whole thing even more surreal. And as the horribly timestretched "fiffffty cycclesssss" sample hits you, then everything goes to Hell once and for all, as if you're being engulfed by a sonic black hole. Crazy and amazing. The drum 'n' bass/breakcore/whatever side is very well represented, too, particularly in the atmospheric, windy [s]Menelec[/s], which starts off with some gamelan sounds, and maintains that air of mystery even as the drums are firing all their rounds against you. [s]District Line II[/s] is more unforgiving, with its chopped vocal samples and crazy, noisy bass guitar breaks. But the highlight here is [s]Steinbolt[/s], with its unbelievable barrage of metallic, distorted chords; it's almost like death metal meets breakcore or something!... Yeah, well, Venetian Snares has been doing similar stuff, but [s]Steinbolt[/s] is not going for the "horrifying" mood, but for the "pull apart your brain and put it back together inside out" mood. What's more awe-inspiring, though, are those haunting, coming-from-the-afterlife chords that appear near the end. Wow!</p>

<p>As has been said, the noise assaults and long jazz workouts are often interrupted by bass solos, but also by much more gentle and mellow songs, like the pseudo-classical piece [s]Andrei[/s] for classical guitar and bass, as well as the classical guitar solo [s]Every Day I Love[/s], that closes the album. But I can't help but give my full praise for [s]Tommib Help Buss[/s] &mdash; the link to the track from [a]Go Plastic[/a] is justified, as it is also based on a lovely electric piano melody. Here, though, it's oddly uplifting and sweet (in the good way!), and the instrumentation is slowly and gently made more complex as it progresses. Wonderful song. Perhaps [s]An Arched Pathway[/s] is <em>way</em> too overreaching, but hey, if this is a portrait of Tom Jenkinson, then I guess it's necessary, right? What's important to explain, though, is why this album feels like such a solid introduction to Squarepusher: even though pretty much every side of this talent is displayed here, it's not a matter of "there's something for everyone here!", as if you can just come and get the tracks you like. No: you have to embrace <em>the whole of it</em> in order to completely appreciate the album. Jenkinson is not breaking his musical self into easily swallowable little bits; instead, he's gluing them together into a cohesive whole. This album is meant to challenge you, and in a way <em>this</em> is the definite musical representation of the question <em>Do You Know Squarepusher</em>: if you don't listen to this record, then you can't even hope to try to know him, that's fact; if you do listen, well... I frankly don't know. But do yourself a favour and get this record.</p>

<p>Also, it's a goddamn long album: it's 79 minutes and 58 seconds long, pretty much filling the very limit of a Red Book audio CD. And I <em>love every second of it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>15</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Every Day I [l]Comment[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="venus">
      <title>Venus No. 17</title>
      <year>2004</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="window">
      <title>Square Window</title>
      <year>2004</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="everything">
      <title>Hello Everything</title>
      <year>2006</year>
      <high-points>[s]The Modern Bass Guitar[/s], [s]Planetarium[/s], [s]Rotate Electrolyte[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Hello Meow</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Theme from Sprite</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Bubble Life</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Planetarium</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Vacuum Garden</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Circlewave 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Cronecker King</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rotate Electrolyte</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Welcome to Europe</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Plotinus</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Modern Bass Guitar</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Orient Orange</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>If [a]Ultravisitor[/s] unified all the aspects of Squarepusher's talents instead of separating them, then this album is the opposite. Indeed, if you want a "careful" introduction to the 'Pushah, then this album is more recommended. Careful because, in one side, you get a bit of everything, and there's no attempt at making the album a cohesive whole (the vinyl issue of the album is a <em>TRIPLE</em> LP &mdash; an average of 10 minutes per side); and on the other side, the noisiest, most brutal side of the man is not present here. In fact, the album is so clean and so friendly that it's almost scary. Even the album cover is friendly: a colourful, beautiful montage of Jenkinson using all sorts of musical tools and instruments. But having just released his masterpiece, I think we can all agree that he's not committing any crime.</p>

<p>Besides, the cleanliness and friendliness are a conscious decision, not a "flaw", not an "accident". Of course, you may just plainly dislike that, which is different from condemning Jenkinson for falling in that trap. And it helps the songs: they were <em>made</em> to sound like that, and any attempt at making them more "hardcore" would ruin them to the core (ha!). Take the opening [s]Hello Meow[/s]: it's got all the elements of a fine drum 'n' bass song, but it is poppy and catchy; and when I say <em>catchy</em>, I say it will stick to your brain like a parasite. Jenkinson plays some fine bass and delivers some memorable melodies in it, and there <em>are</em> breakbeats and whatnot to keep your shoulders jiggling. It's not a masterpiece, but it's not <em>supposed</em> to be: this is not [s]My Red Hot Car[/s], you know! It's a great tune. Likewise there's [s]Welcome to Europe[/s], which is a little more sophisticated in terms of songwriting, and the melody is not as immediately catchy, but it's an engaging and fun song without any pretentions. The electronic workouts are not limited to those "poppy" excursions, though, as you have the gorgeous, evocative, harmonically complex [s]Planetarium[/s] (one of my favourites here), the [a]Ultravisitor[/a]-inspired [s]Plotinus[/s] and the beautiful [s]Rotate Electrolyte[/s], which grows from a purely percussion-oriented groove to a electronica-jazz fusion and ends with some beautiful, complex, gradually building synth chords. I definitely have a preference for these more complex tracks over the more poppy oriented, but that doesn't mean they overshadow the others.</p>

<p>The more purely jazzy side is actually sort of underrepresented here, as there is not big opus dedicated to it. It does, though, have a wonderful little pair of songs: [s]Theme from Sprite[/s] is slow and gentle, as well as very beautiful and tuneful, while [s]Bubble Life[/s] is just insanely catchy, with bubbly synth effects and a great interplay of tuned percussion, acoustic guitar and a fast, but soft electronic rhythm. They're very short, though, which is actually a shame. I like those songs! The other acoustic-oriented song is [s]Circlewave 2[/s], which couldn't even hope to reach the heels of its predecessor: it <em>is</em> beautiful and circular as well, but instead of jaw-droppingly gorgeous, it's "just" beautiful, and the instrumentation is <em>far</em> less elaborate. On the other hand, Jenkinson reserves an entire side for the 12-minute-long [s]Orient Orange[/s], a percussion-based, pseudo-ambient piece. I have having to use the term "ambient" to describe this, but in more recent terms, that's pretty much what it is: lengthy, static and based in texture and atmosphere rather than rhythm or melody. It's an odd offering, but a good track, and much better than the uneventful, uninteresting [s]Vacuum Garden[/s], which is just a choir of synths <em>slowwwwly</em> going up and down for six minutes. The effect is cool, but to justify a whole track? I don't buy it.</p>

<p>Fans of the 'Pushah's breakneck drum 'n' bass will probably want to check out [s]The Modern Bass Guitar[/s], which has Jenkinson with his bass guitar plugged into his MIDI devices and delivering his devilish, manipul-a-plenty solos over a fast, stuttering rhythm. I love this track, as it combines the more "show-offy" aspect of [s]Anstromm-Feck 4[/s] with the sheer grooviness of [s]Come On My Selector[/s], and adds some interesting, inspiring "ambient" touches. And the main riff is far catchier than that of [s]Anstromm-Feck 4[/s]. This song rocks, and definitely owns the title of best track here. Don't think you'll have to grab the record <em>only</em> for that track: this is a solid album, and will only displease those who, for some reason, seriously dislike the most accessible and least aggressive side of Jenkinson's music. I don't see why one would dislike it, though; it's not a record to be loved to death, but Jenkinson's sharp musicianship and intelligence is obvious all over the album. Do check it out eventually, and if you're a "cautious" newcomer to Squarepusher, get it first.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Now cautiously [l]send your comments[/l].</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="souvenir">
      <title>Just a Souvenir</title>
      <year>2008</year>
      <high-points>[s]Planet Gear[/s], [s]A Real Woman[/s], [s]The Glass Road[/s], [s]Delta-V[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Star Time 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Coathanger</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Open Society</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>A Real Woman</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Delta-V</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Aqueduct</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Potential Govaner</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Planet Gear</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Tensor in Green</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Glass Road</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Fluxgate</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Duotone Moonbeam</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Quadrature</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Yes Sequitur</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>One fine day, Squarepusher had a daydream. Or, at least, that's what he wants you to believe, according to the liner notes. But we all know how much Jenkinson likes to screw around with people.</p>

<p>The liner notes talk about him dreaming with a "crazy, beautiful rock band playing an ultra-gig", and describing in detail the bizarre and freaky tricks the band would pull off, like playing a guitar that could distort time, making the drums instantaneously switch places in the drumset and using the whole building as an amplifier. He remarks, though, that this album is by no means what the band sounded like, and was recorded as "just a souvenir" of such a wonderful daydream. It's obvious, though, that most of those vivid and imaginative tricks all refer to common marks of the 'Pushah's sound, as well as sonic features he would use here: heavily manipulated guitar playing, complex breakbeats, huge and fuzzed-out bass sounds, and so on. In all, the text that comes with the record is an entertaining little piece, but it can't even hope to make justice to this album.</p>

<p>For starters: in case you didn't notice, reread the part where Jenkinson talks about <em>a rock band</em>. Rock band? Not a fusion jazz band, or an electronic musician? A ROCK band? Yep, that's right. So far, we haven't had any elements of rock in the Pusher's music. What he does in this album, though, is not mix up some rock pieces in his already well established style: instead of stitching different pieces together into an unifying whole ([a]Ultravisitor[/a]) or in a pleasant "collection" ([a]Hello Everything[/a]), he creates a unique blend of different styles and genres, a big mix of things, a <em>single</em> personal style that he develops through these 14 tracks: punk rock energy is crossed over with funk soloing and complex harmonies, run through fuzzboxes and distortion, and laid over rapid-fire rhythms and grooves, and it's probably the most amazing thing Tom Jenkinson has ever done... next to [a]Ultravisitor[/a], at least.</p>

<p>That's not to say that all tracks sound like that. The formula described above can be truthfully applied to only a select few songs, as most of them reach out in different directions; for example, [s]Star Time 2[/s] is an almost purely electronic disco groove, that doesn't yet bring in the fuzzy guitars and drum 'n' bass grooves, but bops along nicely with gorgeous synth melodies, untrivial chord changes and head-spinning syncopated rhythms. [s]The Coathanger[/s] is also disco-ish, but the instrumentation is far more sparse and more based on Jenkinson's choppy, bumpy bass soloing. And it has <em>vocals</em>! Granted, the vocals are all ran through a Vocoder, and he's singing about the almighty Coathanger, which was the scenery of the "ultra gig" in Tom's daydream, but yeah, this is one of the songs with vocals in the album. [s]Open Society[/s] is a piece of solo classical guitar, but not only is it entirely atonal, but it's peppered with some of the most bizarre and unexplainable sound effects that Squarepusher has ever employed. I'm pretty sure this is what he was referring with the guitar that could manipulate time, because at times sounds like that guitar is whipping back and forth along some unknown dimension. There are two other tracks like that: the effect is interesting, but Jenkinson is smart enough to keep the tracks short, so they don't really get in the way of the rest. They serve as interesting, curious breaks along the way.</p>

<p>The serious fun starts with [s]A Real Woman[/s], a song that is part [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a], part [a]Budakhan Mindphone[/a] and part Ramones. The rhythm seamlessly switches between punkish straightforward 4/4 and frenzied drum 'n' bassin', the guitar switches from [a]Blitzkrieg Bop[/a] to complicated as hell jazzy riffs, and Vocoder Jenkinson sings about an allegedly <em>real</em> woman. Not only is it hard to imagine a song like this being made, but it's just impossible to imagine <em>Squarepusher</em> making a song like this, but he did it. The result is nothing short of brilliant <em>and</em> fun as the whole world. The instrumental pieces don't come up short, though: [s]Delta-V[/s] takes the formula and launches it into hyperspace, with a fuzzy bass delivering non-stop, furious riffs over complicated rhythms, and [s]Tensor in Green[/s] swings along slow-fast switches and left turns along the way. [s]The Glass Road[/s], the album's tour de force, boasts a gorgeous arrangement to a jazzy melody, all set to the usual rapid-fire rhythms, and alternating with heavy and rocking passages and other more complex breaks, eventually being swallowed by a lengthy, spooky "ambient" coda. My favourite here is definitely [s]Planet Gear[/s]: it simply <em>kicks ass</em>, and there's no other way to say it. The riffs are some of the best Jenkinson has ever written, and the contrast between the distorted, dark-ish verses and the more upbeat, lighter chorus is out of this world.</p>

<p>Sure enough, the recipe just wouldn't be ready without some more sophisticated touches. [s]Potential Govaner[/s] and [s]Duotone Moonbeam[/s] are almost totally jazz-based, the former very fast and quirky, and the latter more in the slow, [a]Budakhan Mindphone[/a]-ish vibe. The album closes on the very light note: [a]Quadrature[/a] is gorgeous, based heavily on acoustic guitar, with a delicate melody laid over tricky chord changes, and [a]Yes Sequitur[/a] has some of the most beautiful and evocative classical guitar playing in Jenkinson's catalog, even being just 1:30 long. The whole thing comes together in a package that stands absolutely tall and strong in the Pusher's discography. I tell you, if it weren't for [a]Ultravisitor[/a], I'd give this record a 15 with all the ease and confidence in the world. I still firmly believe [a]Ultravisitor[/a] is Jenkinson's masterpiece, but if you think that one is way too bloated or something, then you <em>just can't miss</em> this one. Those who only like his electronic work probably won't get into this, but hell, why should I care about <em>those</em> folks anyway? If you can't dig music as exciting and smart as [a]Just a Souvenir[/a], then it's your problem, not mine. If that's not your case, get this record, crank it up and enjoy.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>14</rating>
      <comment-phrase>"You're impressive / You're important / [l]You send comments[/l] / Because you're real"</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="lucent">
      <title>Numbers Lucent</title>
      <year>2009</year>
      <high-points>[s]Zounds Perspex[/s], [s]Illegal Dustbin[/s], [s]Star Time 1[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Zounds Perspex</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Paradise Garage</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Heliacal Torch</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Star Time 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Arterial Fantasy</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Illegal Dustbin</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>So what's with these "companion EPs" and such? So many electronic artists have to do them, it seems. At least this EP <em>is</em> compatible with an EP in terms of number of tracks and total length, which means Squarepusher doesn't want to be "unconventional" like Autechre, who released a "companion EP" that is <em>over two hours long</em>. What's up with that, anyway? Why can't our artists be conventional and do as the music business says? If the industry says that all you're allowed to buy are expensive CDs that you can't even rip to your own computer, that's what you have to do! But no, those artists release music online, on USB flash drives and on <em>vinyl</em>!! Don't they know vinyl is <em>obsolete</em>???</p>

<p>That was a JOKE, by the way. For one, I love vinyl, as much as the guy next door. Even though I don't even know the guy next door's name (TRU FAX).</p>

<p>This EP is such a "companion" to [a]Just a Souvenir[/a] that the cover art is almost identical to a passing glance. So you take this release, scan the track titles and read [s]Star Time 1[/s], so you pop it in your player expecting a fuzzy jazzy rock 'n' roll work-out with drum 'n' bass rhythms and crazy guitar riffs and you get... a <em>disco track</em>? Well, you see, this release is only a companion in, um, "philosophical" terms, because in musical terms, it's merrily going back to [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a]! Yes, the first track is a disco dance groove (disco in modern terms, of course, synths and drum machines aplenty, and not with sliding strings riffs and a drummer going "bump tssss-tat tssss-bump ta-tssss-tat"), but the tracks are overall quite varied and mostly dance oriented, but filled to the brim with Jenkinson's unusual harmonies, chord progressions, bass solos and off-kilter rhythms. Cynics could say that he's stepping back to "please the crowds" or something, but I say that this is actually pulling [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a] forwards, adapting it to his recent developments. You see, a less ambitious artist could have built <em>an entire career</em> on top of [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a], and why not? Many electronic artists build their careers on a single genre and maybe a few subgenres as well and are actually quite great. Squarepusher, however, started to branch out into everything he wanted, and going back to a dance release is, in fact, a very refreshing move.</p>

<p>These tracks here all boast <em>excellent</em> dance rhythms &mdash; <em>I</em> could dance to this stuff! Either alone or with my wife, though, because I'm a lousy dancer. And naked. No, I actually didn't write that. Did I? What the hell do you think I am, some "look at me I'm so LOL-worthy funny" attention whore? Or some Mark Prindle wannabe who ends his paragraph mid-word for comedic ef</p>

<p>These tracks here all boast <em>excellent</em> dance rhythms, but they're not at all conventional. See, the aforementioned [s]Zounds Perspex[/s] opens up with a <em>crazy</em>, syncopated and whacked-out chord progression. In harmonic terms, this is the most complex track, but the others don't come too far behind. In a way, this is an almost <em>snobbishly</em> intellectual album, but what do you want? This is Squarepusher we're talking about, the guy IS smart, he knows what he's doing: he's doing intelligent music that never fails to entertain. All tracks here are interesting, beautifully written and exciting. By the way, if you're wondering about [s]Star Time 1[/s], it's not very similar to its counterpart in [a]Just a Souvenir[/a]. This one is way faster, and featured another of those quirky, interesting chord progressions; it <em>does</em>, however, share some sounds with [s]Star Time 2[/s], and it's actually based on a figure for a tinkly celesta-like sound that appears at the very end of its companion song. It's one of my favourite songs, here, and I'm also fond of the beautiful [s]Heliacal Torch[/s], with melodic touches that make me think of [s]Tomorrow World[/s]. [s]Arterial Fantasy[/s], on the other hand, is more chaotic and features a breakneck breakcore rhythm and agressive synth sounds.</p>

<p>If you listen closely, you'll actually realise that the album builds a rhythmic crescendo through these six tracks: the first two are very groovy and disco-ish, the two in the middle enter drum 'n' bass territory, while [s]Arterial Fantasy[/s] is more [s]Rustic Raver[/s] than [s]Coopers World[/s]. This leaves us with [s]Illegal Dustbin[/s], and it's quite possibly one of the most aggressive and violent tracks in the Pusher's whole repertoire. Forget about the noisefests in [a]Go Plastic[/a]: this actually invades Venetian Snares territory, with ear-destructive synths, rushing drums and gabber-like overdriven-to-hell-and-back percussion and distorted vocal samples. The song actually starts like nothing much is going to happen, but by the end, you'll probably be shocked that Jenkinson is doing that unstoppable "BOOOM-BOOOM-BOOOM-BOOOM-BOOOM-BOOOM-BOBOBOBOBOBOBOBOOOM-BOOOM" rhythm, but the amazing thing is that he does it <em>so well</em>! Is there anything this man <em>can't</em> do? He could easily out-perform all those "dubstep" artists out there if he wanted to, I am sure. Of course he didn't want to, but that's for later. For now, I can't say that this is an excellent EP, and one of the very best in the 'Pushah's catalogue. Just don't expect [a]Just a Souvenir II[/a], and you'll enjoy it lots.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s][l]Comment Time[/l] 1[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="bass1">
      <title>Solo Electric Bass 1</title>
      <year>2009</year>
      <high-points>There's nothing for me to pick here</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.01</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.09</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.10</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.04</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.06</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.02</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.03</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.05</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.07</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.08</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.11</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>seb-1.12</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>This album is <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ExactlyWhatItSaysOnTheTin">exactly what it says on the tin</a>! If you don't like jazz, this is gonna be <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/NightmareFuel">nightmare fuel</a>! And if you don't like solo instrument jazz, this will be <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/HighOctaneNightmareFuel">high octane nightmare fuel</a>! Otherwise, it's a <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/CrowningMomentOfAwesome">crowning moment of awesome</a>! So much, in fact, that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/YourHeadAsplode">your head may explode</a>!</p>

<p>Yes, this is a 40 minute solo performance recorded at the Jazz à la Villette 2007 festival by our friend "Hello, my name is" Thomas Jenkinson and his 6-string electric bass guitar, with no effects applied: it's a "pure" jazz performance. As you can see by the crazy track listing, Jenkinson reordered pieces of the performance to his own liking, but it seems the whole thing is here. But those are just technical quibbles, you know? Main thing is, if you enjoy Jenkinson's skills at the bass guitar, you'll have to have it. Of course, others enjoy his playing but only in the context of a proper composition, and displays of his technical skill and intimate knowledge of his bass can be found everywhere in his discography. But nowhere else can we hear him focusing all his attention to the bass guitar, without ring modulators and other wacky pedal effects, for almost 40 minutes. At the very least, it's an interesting listen.</p>

<p>His playing is, though, definitely entertaining. He's just not noodling and showing how fast he can flash his fingers, but he is trying to pull off nice textures, melodic passages and groovy-as-heck freak-outs. The performance is very dynamic and holds interest very well. Of course, it helps to have at least some familiarity to this kind of music, and if jazz just isn't your cup of tea, you'd better skip it. Take it as this: if Keith Jarrett's [a]Köln Concert[/a] bores you to tears, keep away from this (and now that I've made my purposefully snobbish display of jazz knowledge, you can make fun of me in the comments as much as you want. Go ahead, I won't get mad). As for me, I like this, but this isn't a record I'd listen to every day, or every other day, like, say, [a]Just a Souvenir[/a] or [a]Hard Normal Daddy[/a]: this would be an absolutely great performance to watch, you know, to witness first-hand, being there in front of the guy. That would be cool. But it is interesting, and a welcome addition to Squarepusher's catalogue. Of course, the title indicates that there might be a sequel, and I won't hold my breath until it happens... but I'll want to check it out, that is for sure.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[a]Solo Electric [l]Comments[/l][/a]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <related-artist ref="shobaleader">
      <name>Shobaleader One</name>
      <album ref="demonstrator">
        <title>d'Demonstrator</title>
        <year>2010</year>
        <high-points>[s]Plug Me In[/s], [s]Into the Blue[/s]</high-points>
        <tracks>
          <disc>
            <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Plug Me In</title></track>
            <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Laser Rock</title></track>
            <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Into the Blue</title></track>
            <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Frisco Wave</title></track>
            <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Megazine</title></track>
            <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Abstract Lover</title></track>
            <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Endless Night</title></track>
            <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Cryptic Motion</title></track>
            <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Maximum Planck</title></track>
          </disc>
        </tracks>
        <review><![CDATA[
<p>One thing is for sure: if you want a certain, definitive way to assure your position as the ultimate Squarepusher fanboy, this album is your best opportunity.</p>

<p>Okay, some context first: Jenkinson alleged that a group of musicians approached him to form a band (inspired by the "ultra-gig" story in [a]Just a Souvenir[/a]), and after initially dismissing the idea, he decided to give it a go and recorded this album. In fact, the promotional material depicts five people wearing eerie black cloaks and "LED display" masks, and they identities are all maintained anonymous. So, nothing guarantees that this isn't just another put-on by Mr. Jenkinson, and listening to the album gives no conclusive responses about whether this story is true or not. But it's easy to see that this "band" is an effective way for him to signal to his fans "Beware! This is not [a]Go Plastic[/a]!", because the album has as much to do with Squarepusher as it has to do with Julio Iglesias.</p>

<p>Basically, the album consists of CHEAP POP! COMMERCIAL SELL-OUT RADIO-FRIENDLY PAP! HIP-HOP WANNA-BE GARBAGE THAT COULD VERY WELL HAVE RIHANNA PROVIDING VOCALS!... or, at least, those are the things you must proclaim if you want to show off as a "true" fan of "real" Squarepusher, and not this "travesty". But if you're a fanboy, you can proclaim this as yet another masterpiece, as every other piece of vinyl or plastic that he has put out as any of his aliases. But if you're <em>me</em> (and you most probably aren't, unless I am reading this review myself, and I do that often because I love myself!), you'll listen to this once, twice, three, four, five times, etc., and come to your own conclusions. And I concluded that this is great music.</p>

<p>But then again, I'm not the guy who pukes his guts out when he listens to Rihanna. I don't really like her stuff, but I think it's pretty valid. There is, in fact, VERY little stuff that truly offends me, and I'm not offended by inoffensive pop music. And as far as pop music goes, this is pretty inoffensive. Not <em>entirely</em> inoffensive, but you could have about five of these tracks running on the background of your workplace and hardly anyone would notice &mdash; except, perhaps, for the heavily Vocoder-ed vocals. And as far as Squarepusher goes, this is nearly unrecognisable. There are no fiendishly harsh bass solos, piercing drum rushes or anything like that. What you get is a bunch of friendly, romantic ballads and a couple of harsher electro-rock tunes. And you also get the intelligent songwriting, sophisticated melodies, eyebrow-raising chord changes and tasteful textures. In short, "commercial sell-out" my ass.</p>

<p>So, the only thing that <em>really</em> keeps these songs away from being 100% radio friendly are the vocals, which are <em>all</em> run through a Vocoder &mdash; but then again, if the "extreme Auto-Tune" effect has become completely acceptable for radio play, I wonder why the Vocoder shouldn't be? Sometimes the lyrics are pretty hard to understand, but why should that be such a great problem? Anyway, [s]Plug Me In[/s] and [s]Into the Blue[/s] are extremely catchy and enjoyable romantic tunes... well, "romantic" only as far as I can guess, because the lyrics [s]Plug Me In[/s] consist entirely of purposefully dorky puns on studio jargon ("Do you wanna sync up with me? / Twenty-four bits a night / Is all I need to do it right"), so it could as well be a love letter to a sampler or something. But both songs are <em>great</em>, with enough melodic hooks to make them catchy and enough harmonic twists to keep them interesting, without falling in obviousness <em>or</em> snobbishness. To me, they are the best of the slowest tracks, with the instrumental [s]Frisco Wave[/s] as an excellent, beautiful complement for the set. The other ballads are good but not as remarkable.</p>

<p>In the more rock-oriented vein, we have the <em>very</em> straightforward-no-nonsense instrumental [s]Megazine[/s], which is fun but not much else. The riffs used are not really that great, but they work well with each other, and for a 3-minute-long chunk of fun, it works well. I'm a bigger fan of the twisty [s]Laser Rock[/s], with a great drum work that makes it sound like the song is about to launch from its dubstep-ish groove into frenzied hyperspace at any moment, and the Vocoder tricks add at lot to the song's feel of unpredictability and wildness. Closing the set, we have the <em>very</em> ominous and harsh [s]Maximum Planck[/s], which also betrays quite a bit of dubstep influence, but with an edge of hard rock. It's pretty surprising that Squarepusher's mellow songs should entertain more than the harder ones, but well, <em>this whole album</em> is surprising. Sort of: after so many twists and turns, could you really be surprised by <em>anything</em> he does? And if you think about the things he could have done (say, an album consisting solely of Carlos Gardel compositions), this ain't really that surprising, is it?</p>
]]></review>
        <rating>12</rating>
        <comment-phrase>[a]Cryptic [l]Comment[/l][/a]</comment-phrase>
      </album>
    </related-artist>
  </artist>
</update-list>