<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<updateList>
  <updateTitle>STEREOLAB'D!!!</updateTitle>
  <updateLink>http://sirmustapha.0sites.org/reviews.php?a=stereolab</updateLink>
  <updateText>So, after a very, very long hiatus, it turns out that the first reviews to be posted -- or, better yet, REPOSTED -- in here are Stereolab reviews! I hope you enjoy 'em, they were written with a lot of love and care.</updateText>
  <artist ref="stereolab">
    <name>Stereolab</name>
    <text><![CDATA[
<p>Where does one start if he wants to define or describe Stereolab? Maybe let's start with the labels put in 'em. Wikipedia tells us that they were one of the first bands to be labelled as "post rock". That may have made sense back in the 90's, but if you hear the stuff that's most commonly called "post rock" today (Mogwai, Explosions in the Sky, 65daysofstatic and such), well, <em>forget it</em>. They are NOT like those bands who make vast, huge, sprawling instrumental compositions with not many instruments other than VERY overdriven electric guitars, drums and bass, usually based on very simple motifs and riffs. That's not Stereolab at all. What Stereolab IS is a band that blurs the line between "pop" and "experimental" like very few bands can. Imagine a song that is boiling with unusual sounds and arrangements, yet features a sweet and delicate female voice singing melodies that you cam hum or whistle on the way to the convenience store. Stereolab did exactly that.</p>

<p>The man responsible for those "unusual sounds and arrangements" goes by the name of Tim Gane, and he's obsessed with everything that's old and foreign. Sort of. He digs analogue synths &mdash; the REAL stuff, like Minimoogs &mdash;, electric organs like the Vox and the Farfisa, 70's German rock bands (or Krautrock, if you will), 60's pop, Brazilian pop and bossa nova and so on and on. It's rather safe to say that Gane is the man behind those things, because the band's line up rarely was the same in different albums &mdash; drummers, bassists, guitarists and keyboardists were all changing, and Tim Gane remained at the head of it all; he and his counterpart, the French born L&aelig;titia Sadier, who is the one responsible for the "sweet and delicate female voice". She doesn't only sing, but also provides the lyrics, which are... well, "unique" doesn't even begin to define them. If you thought Liz Fraser's incomprehensible ramblings in Cocteau Twins was weird enough, wait until you hear THESE lyrics &mdash; at least the ones in English, because she writes and sings in her native French as well. L&aelig;titia doesn't bother with breaking sentences and words across the different verses, she doesn't bother matching the stressed syllables with the downbeats, and it seems the ONLY thing she bothers with is with the content of the lyrics; she often sings about political affairs, social themes, philosophical themes, all with a very leftist point-of-view. The most superficial listeners call this stuff "Marxist", but that label makes as much sense applied to her as it does applied to Bob Marley.</p>

<p>I hope you don't mind if I don't mention the lyrics in my reviews, because there rarely is anything to write about them. Thing is, I LIKE the effect that L&aelig;titia's lyrics have in the songs, as they are detached enough not to be detracting. Sometimes they are noteworthy, but only sometimes. Usually pulling up the lyrics sheet on the Internet is the best alternativa if you want to know anything about them; "but Fernie," I hear you say (because I have magical ears and can hear your thoughts across the Internet), "isn't that the same thing as not talking about the music and pointing to YouTube instead?" That's a good (i.e. dumb) question. The thing is, the music has a LOT of layers and interesting things to talk about, while the lyrics are as direct and unsubtle as they can be; and I'm here to review music, not political stances, okay?</p>

<p>Anyway, L&aelig;titia's lyrics may not be worth talking about, but that voice! That voice is just magnificent. It's not a "gorgeous" female voice like that of aforementioned Liz Fraser, neither is it unique and gripping as that of Bj&ouml;rk, but it just matches the music like no other voice could. Actually, there is a lie, because there is a SECOND voice that fits this music, and that is the voice of Mary Hansen, who during many years was the second vocalist and did INCREDIBLE duos with L&aelig;titia. Sometimes one would be singing words and the other would be just chanting wordless syllables ("Ba-da-ba-da" and "dum-dee-dum" are good examples), sometimes they'd both be exchanging words, but the combinations are always amazing. They both also handle some instruments (keyboards, guitars, percussion), but it's sort of pointless to mention who plays what in each song &mdash; I'm just hiding the fact that I have NO IDEA of who plays what in each song, but that goes without saying.</p>

<p>Stereolab started out playing a style of "experimental rock" that combined the rigorous and mechanic rhythms of Krautrock, overdriven electric organs and walls of disorted guitar into a very distinguished sound. That sound, however, ranged from agressive to downright gorgeous, depending on the song. Later on, Gane started to incorporate many different influences, which resulted into the brilliant melting pot that is [s]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/s], and then they moved on to jazzier, more sophisticated music that some call "loungey". But the main thing is that they changed a lot between the albums. Also they released TONS AND TONS of singles, EP's and other assorted non-album tracks, and they are usually gathered into compilations that will be reviewed here too. I will not review the individual singles and EP's, as that would be too burdensome and inconvenient. Anyway, enjoy the reviews, and if they convince you to pick up their albums, enjoy these as well; and I seriously hope you enjoy them as much as I do, but not <em>more</em>, as that would probably turn you into a brainless fanatic, and that's no good.</p>]]></text>
    <album ref="switchedon">
      <title>Switched On</title>
      <year>1992</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Super-Electric[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Super-Electric</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Doubt</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Au Grand Jour'</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Way Will Be Opening</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Brittle</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Contact</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Au Grand Jour</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>High Expectations</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Light That Will Cease to Fail</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Changer</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The band started their career releasing singles, EP's and stuff like that, before putting out their first proper LP album (titled as a homage to Wendy Carlos's pioneering electronic album [a]Switched On Bach[/a]). This compilation gathers all the tracks from the band's first releases: [a]Stunning Debut Album[/a], [a]Super 45[/a] and [a]Super-Electric[/a]. Suffice to say, it is excellent, and it's extremely advisable to the dear reader not to twirl his nose at the word "compilation" because, unless he really loves hunting for difficult-to-find vinyl releases and has enough availability to do so, the best way to check out those tracks is in this record; and for <em>anyone</em> willing to get initiated in Stereolab, these tracks are an absolute necessity.</p>

<p>These songs feature the band in a stage when their music had a certain na&iuml;ve charm, a joviality, and would later on be replaced by other qualities. Right from the start some of the most distinctive marks of the band are already firmly in place: the tight production with walls of distorted guitar, the influence of krautrock bands (most notably NEU!) in the rhythm section, the obsession with electric organs and vintage analog synthesizers, and the combination of those things with the delicate, multilayered, melodic vocal work by lead singer L&aelig;titia Sadier. Those elements define the very genesis of the band, and this is the true source of all that.</p>

<p>For starters, the very first track, [s]Super-Electric[/s], is the very summation of all things Stereolab, and is one of their best songs ever &mdash; or, at least, one of their best songs of this decade. The rhythm is fast and pulsating, in the best tradition of NEU!'s [s]Hallogallo[/s], complemented by a buzzy yet smooth combination of organ and guitar making this strangely dreamy, floaty pillow of B major chords, here and there disturbed by other chords. On top of that, L&aelig;titia lays her wonderfully sing-alongable melody and secondary la-la-las. Clocking at five minutes and a half, the length is absolutely necessary to allow the sound to develop fully and gracefully, and it never, ever overstays its welcome. Early Stereolab could hardly ever get better than this.</p>

<p>The rest of the album, though, doesn't disappoint at all. The sound of the songs hardly changes much, and most of the "variety" here comes in the shape of slower ballads, namely the gorgeous [s]The Way Will Be Opening[/s], the relatively forgettable yet catchy romantic (!!!) [s]High Expectations[/s] and the extremely beautiful, uplifting [s]Changer[/s] (which is actually French for "to change"), which starts gentle and delicate and grows bigger towards the end. Along the way, you get the meatier songs like [s]Au Grand Jour[/s] (which comes with a secondary, lighter version titled [s]Au Grand Jour'[/s]), the bouncy [s]Brittle[/s] (with an insanely catchy melody and twinkly, bubbly synthesizer effects strategically added), the speedy, boppy [s]Doubt[/s] and the delicate, almost slight [s]The Light Will Cease to Fail[/s]. The uniformity of sound, instrumentation and arrangement is well compensated by the variety of moods; yeah, the mostly all fall into the same "overall" mood, but there are enough twists and disturbances to keep the whole listening experience interesting.</p>

<p>The only moment of "experimentation" the album offers is the 8-minute-long [s]Contact[/s]. It's slow, droney and very repetitive, but it sure as hell is hypnotic. But let's face it: even if you don't find anything worthwhile in the song, you cannot dismiss it as a work of endless dicking around by some talentless hacks because, well, just look at the 9 songs around it! [s]Contact[/s] is not an obnoxiously self-aware work of "experimentation", but just a moment of letting it loose and trying something new. So, I give kudos for these guys. Keeping in mind that this record is a compilation, it's surprisingly cohesive, and truly essential. Unless you're willing to go out and get the original vinyl singles and are REALLY turned off by compilations, do get this record.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]Contact[/s] me and [l]drop your comments[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="peng">
      <title>Peng!</title>
      <year>1992</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Perversion[/s], [s]Surrealchemist[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Super Falling Star</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Orgiastic</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Peng! 33</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>K-Stars</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Perversion</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>You Little Shits</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Seeming and the Meaning</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Mellotron</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Enivrez-Vous</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Stomach Worm</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Surrealchemist</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>This being the band's very first full length LP album, it's pretty much impossible not to compare these tracks to the triumphant success of the tracks from [a]Switched On[/a]. I'm not going to play the pessimist here, but there is definitely <em>something</em> lacking from these songs; I'd say it's the joviality, the <em>shine</em>, the <em>sparkle</em> that made the previous songs truly stand out. It's not only the production, that's far flatter, more muffled and more constrained, but the songs as well. Let's take [s]Orgiastic[/s] as an example: yes, it follows pretty much the same "framework" of songs like [s]Super-Electric[/s], but the melody isn't quite as catchy, and the sound is just not as entrancing. But well, I'm not going to say that the WHOLE album is like this, no sir! This is just an example to state why this album is, overall, weaker than the classic [a]Switched On[/a].</p>

<p>But no! I won't act like the whole album is like that! The album <em>does</em> deliver some sweet songs in the "fast" department, with the jolly, understated [s]Peng! 33[/s] and the poppy [s]The Seeming and the Meaning[/s]; true, they never reach the height of [s]Super-Electric[/s] or [s]Brittle[/s], but are fine in their own right. [s]Stomach Worm[/s] stands out particularly, though, because it's faster than everything, featuring an absolutely poppy melody, but breaks loose in a very energetic and exciting extended instrumental outro. This is something we haven't had much from Stereolab yet; yes, there was [s]Contact[/s], but that wasn't a poppy song anyway! [s]Stomach Work[/s], on the other hand, is catchy and sweet for the first few minutes, and then breaks loose with all might and power. I like that!</p>

<p>And while we're talking about the poppy songs, let me namedrop my favourite song here, [s]Perversion[/s]. It's also lengthy, with a slightly extended instrumental coda, and it has a far groovier, funkier rhythm. What truly grabs me in this song is the lyrics: this is a <em>speech</em>, not a set of lyrics! And L&aelig;titia Sadier bends and breaks the words to make them fit the melody, and... and... it <em>works</em>. The result is bizarrely enticing. Maybe it's just that voice she has? I dunno, but it's not <em>any</em> singer that can combine so masterfully melody and lyrics and just don't seem to fit. I really like this one, in short.</p>

<p>Another new thing this album brings are the slow, moody songs. Yes, we had ballads on the previous record, but not the moody, sometimes almost brooding songs such as [s]Super Falling Star[/s] that opens this record. It doesn't even have drums in it! It's a great song, very captivating, with a cloud of jangly guitar and organs supporting Sadier's multilayered vocals. [s]K-Stars[/s] also has a very lovely vocal work and adventurous synth effects, while [s]You Little Shits[/s] is more understated and mysterious. But for me, the highlight among these songs is the closer [s]Surrealchemist[/s], which again features no drums. In fact, if you consider [s]Super Falling Star[/s] to be the "dark" side of Stereolab's slow songs, [s]Surrealchemist[/s] is <em>definitely</em> the "light" side, and with honours. It's the longest song here, and for me, that gentle ending with the melodic bass jangling and floating organ could go on forever.</p>

<p>I'm not particularly interested in [s]Enivrez-Vous[/s], which has L&aelig;titia reciting a Baudelaire text over a very standard Stereolab backing, and [s]Mellotron[/s], which is an, um... "homage" to the Silver Apples. Basically it's a carbon copy of their song [s]Ruby[/s], which just the vocal melody and lyrics changed. I have no idea why Tim Gane would decide to pay homage to such an obscure song of such an obscure band, but... I guess that's the point? Yeah, I guess that's it. And by the way, paying homages would become VERY common place for the band, and here's pretty much the starting point. And songs titled after musical instruments too &mdash; come to think of it, I don't think they even played a Mellotron in this record at all. But so what? You wouldn't expect Stereolab to act like a NORMAL band, would ya?</p>

<p>I'm gonna be frank: I'm not very comfortable giving this album a 10/15; in my heart, it feels too low. But what the heck, this is a great band and they have LOTS of great releases ahead, and I'm not going to fry my brains over this record. A 10 it is, pushing a little towards an 11 by the strength of [s]Super Falling Star[/s], [s]Perversion[/s], [s]Stomach Worm[/a] and [s]Surrealchemist[/s]. Yeah, that seems fine.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]Enivrez-Vous[/s] avec [l]commentaires[/l]!</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="lowfi">
      <title>Low Fi</title>
      <year>1993</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Laisser-Faire[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Low Fi</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>(Varoom!)</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Laisser-Faire</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Elektro (He Helt the World in His Iron Grip)</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Of all the inumerable line up changes this band went through, this is probably the first truly memorable change: the band was joined by Australian guitarist, percussionist and second vocalist Mary Hansen, whose gentle, slightly nasal vocals and smart interplay with L&aelig;titia's lead vocals would become a trademark of the band's poppier tendencies. It's hard to say that these songs here are "poppier" than the ones that came before, but the smooth, playful vocal interplay is already sticking its head out.</p>

<p>This EP, for some reason, would not be represented in any of the band's singles and EP's compilations. It's odd, because these songs are perfectly good &mdash; though, in my opinion, they don't reach the height of most of their early songs. The record is quite a lot less, um, "compromised" and sounds a little more experimental than before. I dunno if "experimental" is the right term; "loose", perhaps. Yes, there is a lot of tight, melodic poppiness to be found here, like in the fast, almost sickeningly catchy [s]Laisser-Faire[/s], which L&aelig;titia ranting about the increasing right-wingedness of the world over a quite sweet, rocking background. It's a little like [s]Super-Electric[/s], only faster and more "shiny". [s]Low Fi[/s], on the other hand, sets the usual combination of rhythmic guitars and buzzing organs to a surprisingly slow tempo. The result has all the charm and gentleness that the band would perfect in later releases. It's also the best track to look for L&aelig;titia and Mary's fun vocal interplay.</p>

<p>[s](Varoom!)[/s] is a less catchy and accessible tune, with the well known fast and tight rhythm and a strangely buzzy, saturated sound. This track seems less about vocal melody and more about the overall sound and the fiddling around with synthesizers, and it ends with more than five minutes of a really distorted drone featuring a Farfisa organ beatbox and guitar chords. [s]Elektro[/s], then, brings back the chords from [s](Varoom!)[/s] and spends three minutes playing around with synthesizers. It sounds really dumb in theory, but actually, it's sort of fun. The last few minutes close with a ballad, with acoustic guitars and L&aelig;titia singing over a pretty complex chord progression. Consider this: for short four song EP, it is pretty full of surprises. It's not easily recommendable for casual fans, and honestly, I don't listen to it very often; but those two highlight songs definitely deserve a listen if you're growing interested in the band. Don't neglect it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>"I can feel it more and more / Within ten years we'll have a [l]comment[/l]"</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="music">
      <title>Space Age Batchelor Pad Music</title>
      <year>1993</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Avant-Garde M.O.R.[/s], [s]Ronco Symphony[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Avant-Garde M.O.R.</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Space Age Batchelor Pad Music (Mellow)</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Groop Played Chord X</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Space Age Batchelor Pad Music (Foamy)</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ronco Symphony</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>We're Not Adult Orientated</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>U.H.F. - MFP</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>We're Not Adult Orientated (Neu Wave Live)</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>This EP saw the arrival of keyboardist Sean O'Hagan, who would later leave the band to form the High Llamas. This means that, at this stage, the band was a SIX piece group &mdash; or Groop, if you will. This here EP is said to have been quite a hit and let the way to a major label deal, but I wonder exactly <em>why</em>. Honestly, I don't see anything in this record that puts it on par with [a]Switched On[/a]; heck, in my book, it's pretty much side to side with [a]Peng![/a]. One thing that makes it stand out, though, is that it is a LOT less worried with producing catchy tunes and more concerned with being experimental and "out there". The artwork is an obvious throwback to those "Space Age" 60's albums. I just don't know where the "Batchelor (sic) Pad Music" comes from, but I guess that's the joke.</p>

<p>Side A of the EP is titled "Easy listening", and side B is "New wave", but that means nothing. Yeah, you <em>could</em> call side A lighter and easier on the ears, but not when it has something like the first title track, the "Mellow" thing, which is Sean O'Hagan playing a little tune on a Farfisa organ, which consists mostly of nagging chords and a sparse bass line. Okay, so it isn't just random dicking around and it IS an actual composition, but if you're not so anal about it, it will just be an endless series of "FWAA! FWAA! FWAA! mm-FWAA! mm-FWAA! FWAA! FWAA! mm-FWAA! mm-FWAA!" going on for almost two minutes. "Mellow" my ass. "Foamy" is a far more apt title, and it's far more mellow also: it's just a bit of playing around with bubbly synthesizer sounds. It's kinda cute. [s]The Groop Played Chord X[/s] sounds like an embryo for Stereolab's more "longey" ballads, being just under two minutes and having just wordless vocals as its "main attraction". The whole thing is bookeded, thankfully, by two wonderful little ballads; [s]Ronco Symphony[/s] is more laid back and lazy than the opener [s]Avant-Garde M.O.R.[/s], but they're both great.</p>

<p>Side B opens with the 6 minute long [s]Hallogallo[/s] exercise (and hilariously titled) [s]We're Not Adult Orientated[/s]. In terms of vocal melody, it's so simplistic it's almost banal, but the whole thing is sort of entertaining... though it does overstay its welcome a little bit. Its "reprise" is a live, and mercifully short, rendition, which shows the band's cranked-up live setup quite extraordinarily well &mdash; L&aelig;titia's vocals become almost buried under the guitar and organ noise! [s]U.H.F. - MFP[/s], then, is not a rocker, but it's not quite a <em>ballad</em>... it does have a nifty melody and Mary Hansen does some really, really neat vocal harmonies. I really can't speak much in behalf of this album &mdash; it doesn't interest me much, but it's definitely worth hearing at least once.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]We're Not Adult Orientated[/s], [l]but try to act like a grown up when you send your commentations[/l].</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="announcements">
      <title>Transient Random-Noise Bursts with Announcements</title>
      <year>1993</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Jenny Ondioline[/s], [s]Tone Burst[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tone Burst</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Our Trinitone Blast</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Pack Yr Romantic Mind</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>I'm Going Out of My Way</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Golden Ball</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Pause</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Jenny Ondioline</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Analogue Rock</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Crest</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Lock Groove Lullaby</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>So, the Groop gets signed to Elektra Records &mdash; the same label that, for some unknown reason, signed the ultra-hip and mainstream band Ween a few years before. Wonder who was more "underground" back then &mdash; Ween or Stereolab? Hm, it matters not; it matters that, now, the band has a pretty big budget available to them! But the change doesn't become too clear yet; the sound here is still very much in line with the previous releases. But the budget is not the only great big about this record, no sir. The <em>second</em> big thing is, of course, the title. The strange and almost meaningless title is fully explainable, though; it's just one of the several references to <a href="http://www.discogs.com/Artistless-Release-Hi-Fi-Sound-Test-Record/release/1358752">Stereo Test Record HFS69</a> &mdash; references which include the very cover of the album and a sample of the record included on [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s]. This is a fine display of Tim Gane's obsession with music technology and the "hi-fi" era of the 60's, as it wouldn't only manifest itself through the Moog synthesizers and Vox organs.</p>

<p>But the <em>third</em> big thing in this record is the music! Yes, laddies and Changleman, THIS is the band's first classic. Not only the production and songwriting are tons better here than in [a]Peng![/a], but the band pulled all stops regarding their will to experiment and try new things, and the result is a bold, daring, confrontational, almost <em>menacing</em> record. Some music here is so upfront and angry that it's almost scary! Look at the aggressive distortion-fest of [s]Our Trinitone Blast[/s], the terrifyingly heavy, plodding [s]Golden Ball[/s] and the epic [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s] to see if I'm telling the truth or not. The band is unstoppable in this double LP, and it makes [a]Switched On[/a] sound like a very humble beginning and [a]Peng![/a] like the band was merely cleaning their throats before they started screaming for good here.</p>

<p>For starters, let's single out the sidelong epic [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s] here. It's 18 minutes long, and brings to the forefront the influences of NEU!'s so called "Apache beat" that was such a memorable trademark of songs like [s]Hallogallo[/s] and [s]F&uml;r Immer[/s], and puts it to work here, enriched by the big distorted guitars and the grinding, overdriven organ chords we've become used to, except they sound very upfront and powerful here. Also, there is a powerful drive to the song, complemented by some beautiful vocal harmonies by the two vocalists. Sadier's vocals are sing-songey as usual, and the whole brew just keeps boiling for about seven minutes or so. Then, everything stops, only to come back transformed into pretty much a completely different song: a slower, minor key rocker with a sparser, more menacing sound that is definitely VERY reminiscent of [s]Hallogallo[/s]. The vocal melody becomes a sort of mantra ("We've got to keep the lift, hope and struggle / We've got to keep the lift, hope and struggle / Give me the strength, the lift, hope and struggle / Where is the lift, the hope and the struggle?" and so on), and the thing just keeps marching on and on until suddenly the song goes haywire with a hyperspeed tempo and some very twisted noises sampled from the aforementioned test record, only to fade away with the slower tempo and backwards bass guitars. Makes sense to you? Well, this habit of jumping into completely different "songs" during the course of a track shall become VERY common for the band from now on, but the main idea here is that [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s] is possibly the composition that best sums up early Stereolab &mdash; or at least its "darker" side, if you consider [s]Super-Electric[/s] as their "brighter" side. Either way, it's brilliant and I love it.</p>

<p>The rest of the record, though, not only stands up well against the heat of [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s], but exceeds the expectations. The band is breaking barriers and bursting at the seams in <em>every</em> aspect! The opener, [s]Tone Burst[/s], starts the whole thing with an upbeat, jerky rhythm and major key chords and the beautiful brew of guitars and organs as usual. The focus on the instruments is very sharp; in fact, the instrumentation is so in focus that, when L&aelig;titia's vocals come in at last, the whole band is faded out from the mix as if to highlight just how out of place the vocals are in the song. When she goes away, Gane kicks in with a catchy little guitar thingamajik, but then the organs and rhythm guitars go completely haywire with chaotic twanging and grinding, like a machine overheating and bursting steam in all directions and falling apart in a spectacular performance of distruction. It's, in short, fantastic.</p>

<p>[s]Our Trinitone Blast[/s] doesn't push so heavily in the chaotic aspect, but the vocals are far angrier than usual, and masked under a <em>very</em> unusual distortion effect. There are brief breaks with nicer vocal harmonies and quiet instrumentation, but then it kicks back with the fast tempo and wall of chords. It's another great song here, and along with [s]Tone Burst[/s], opens the album exceptionally well. The album again delivers some other heavy rockers with [s]Analogue Rock[/s], which isn't very interesting overall, except for that coda with a very peculiar voice effect, and [s]Crest[/s], with a <em>very</em> repetitive "block chord" guitar figure and an equally repetitive vocal phrase. They fit in well within the album, but as individual songs, they don't really stand out.</p>

<p>What <em>do</em> stand out are some of the creepier songs here. I don't really know why they sound creepy to me, but they just do! [s]Pause[/s], for example. I mean, for fuck's sake, it has a recording from a Numbers Station running beneath the whole song! Is there anything creepier than that? It's so creepy that Boards of Canada used the same trick in [s]Gyroscope[/s], from [a]Geogaddi[/a], and Wilco incorporated it in [a]Yankee Hotel Foxtrot[/a]! The song itself somehow has the sound that most perfectly fits the adjective "ghostly": the organ chords just float around, without drums, guitars or anything, and just with the two vocalists singing gently lyrics that go "Retrieve the past / Like a prayer". Well, that's sort of like a motto for the band, isn't it? Afterwards a jangly guitar enters the song, and it goes sing-songey as well, but it's just really ghost-like and neat. And yeah, it breaks off into something completely different afterwards &mdash; which is just a snippet of the last track in the album, [s]Lock Groove Lullaby[/s], which is just strange and twisted. Remember what I said about the brooding moody songs in [a]Peng![/a], such as [s]Super Falling Star[/s]? Crank the broodiness up to 11 and you've got [s]Lock Groove Lullaby[/s]. As for [s]Golden Ball[/s], well... it starts low, menacing, slow, building on guitars and distorted vocals, and then it just keeps growing and growing on the same chord, and when you're already engulfed by it, you jump off your seat because of a "stylus dragged through the record" sound that suddenly, unexpectedly advances the crescendo. Imagine how many people freaked our hearing that on vinyl! Poor sods must have gotten desperate for their needles. But no, it's part of the song, it's there on the CD as well, and it's the ultimate proof that Tim Gane is a bastard.</p>

<p>But still, the band doesn't disappoint in the poppy department either! [s]I'm Going Out of My Way[/s] is a gorgeous little tune, with a playful little organ figure and an equally playful vocal melody, and [s]Pack Yr Romantic Minds[/s] has an unusually sparse, sensuous groove and a magnificent vocal delivery as well, only occasionally interrputed by heavy guitar laden breaks. Two beautiful pop tunes add a delightful, necessary flavour to this record. This album is an easy 13/15... well, not exactly "easy", as those two songs near the end bog down the pacing a little and, well, as much as the album is a classic, it's not a <em>masterpiece</em> or anything. But who cares? The most exciting thing about this record is exactly the fact that it is imperfect; <em>purposefully</em> imperfect, at times saturated, at times distorted and all twisted up. It's a great release, and the ONE album you must own to represent Stereolab's early stage. Yeah, there's [a]Switched On[/a], but that one is a compilation, isn't it?</p>]]></review>
      <rating>13</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]Pack Yr Romantic[/s] [l]Comments[/l]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="quintet">
      <title>Mars Audiac Quintet</title>
      <year>1994</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Wow and Flutter[/s], [s]Ping Pong[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Three Dee Melody</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Wow and Flutter</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Transona Five</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Des Étoiles Électroniques</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Ping Pong</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Anamorphose</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Five Longers Later</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Nihilist Assault Group</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>International Colouring Contest</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Stars Our Destination</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Transporté Sans Bouger</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>L'Enfer des Formes</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Outer Accelerator</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>New Ortophony</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Fiery Yellow</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Only a few great bands could follow up a classic with yet another classic. Unfortunately, that's not the case with Stereolab here. It seems like, suddenly, the band decided to become <em>boring</em>; and if you're not aware, as you should be, I have an intense aversion for the word "boring" &mdash; I mean, I can't think of a word as irritating, vague, subjective and pointless as the word "boring". But that's the case here! Somehow!</p>

<p>Okay, let me calm myself down and say that <em>the band as a whole</em> has not become boring, and a significant portion of this record is not boring at all. The thing is, they took their famous formula of NEU! drum beat + Vox/Farfisa organs + Big guitar chords + Poppy melody and took it to ridiculous extremes of repetitiveness and sameyness here. [s]Three Dee Melody[/s], [s]Wow and Flutter[/s], [s]Transona Five[/s], [s]Anamorphose[/s], [s]Nihilist Assault Group[/s], [s]L'Enfer des Formes[/s] and [s]Outer Accelerator[/s] are all small variations of that formula: some are fast and some are slow, some have a different rhythm, but overall it's always the same. I don't know about you, but SEVEN songs following the same basic pattern seems a little too much to me. Not only that, but there are just way too many songs here and not enough variation; and when there IS variation, it doesn't always work.</p>

<p>But let's be fair: those "standard pattern" songs aren't bad at all. [s]Wow and Flutter[/s], in particular, is beautiful and catchy in the fine Stereolab tradition. There's also the gorgeous [s]Outer Accelerator[/s], led by a very simple and very beautiful guitar line and a short vocal moment by L&aelig;titia &mdash; that is, until it fades into a COMPLETELY different song (that is actually [s]Klang Tone[/s], available on a bonus single CD included in some issues of the album, as well as the [a]Aluminum Tunes[/a] compilation years later). As for [s]Nihilist Assault Group[/s], the first half of the song is almost ridiculous in its blatant similarity to the second part of [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s]. That song, though, is actually made of several different "parts", and they put only two parts of it in this album; but the second one isn't all that different, really. Others are somewhat different: [s]Three Dee Melody[/s] is much slower, but very unlike the slow and creepy songs of the previous album, and aside from the nifty vocal interplay between the two singing ladies, it's just sort of passable. [s]Transona Five[/s] has a bluesy 12/8 rhythm and a set of 6 lines L&aelig;titia keeps singing over and over again. And it goes for five minutes. Yeah. There's also [s]Anamorphose[/s], which if I were a completely uneducated dunce (as I indeed am) I'd call "minimalist", as it features a slow rhythm and a series of entwined small vocal phrases that keep fading in and out of the mix, as if forming a tricky little tapestry. It also has an organ playing a pair of chords, but each time the chords are dragged out for longer. And the song ends with an interesting brass line, and it lasts for seven minutes. Yeah.</p>

<p>There is one thing I haven't mentioned, and which helps to make this album, I believe, less interesting and gripping that it could have been: the production is much cleaner and much crisper, no doubt the result of a bigger budget due to the band having being signed to Elektra Records. I suppose I could use that as a cheap justification for saying "this is why big labels suck! Long live the indie labels!" or something, but I wouldn't go that low! I have a dignity to preserve, dammit! Who am I? A redator for Pitchfork Music? Meh. Either way, this production surely sparkles and shines, and I'm grateful that this wasn't the production employed on the previous album! After all, it was exactly that gritty, almost dirty sound that made [a]Transient Random-Noise Bursts with Announcements[/a] so interesting! But well, the production actually works in some cases, like in the gorgeously catchy [s]Ping Pong[/s], which breaks into a snappy rhythm and playful brass arrangements and the wonderful [s]Transport&eacute; Sans Bouger[/s], with some more great singing by the ladies. One thing I don't understand is why they butchered [s]New Ortophony[/s]; the full version of the song, present in the aforementioned [a]Aluminum Tunes[/a], is six minutes long and has an initial portion with a really nifty vocal melody. For some reason they chopped off that part and left only the lengthy instrumental break and the final, slow coda. Who can guess! I know this band likes doing those crazy tricks, but why cut off such a nice part of the song?</p>

<p>Among the other songs you've got weird little ballads carried by organ beatboxes, such as the bossa nova inspired [s]Des &Eacute;toiles &Eacute;ectroniques[/s] &mdash; with some very beautiful vocal harmonies! &mdash; and the not so interesting [s]The Stars Our Destination[/s]. [s]Five Longers Later[/s] is an interesting case: for its first part, it's a lullabyesque tune with Mary and L&aelig;titia singing over some lonely organ chords, and then kicks off into a really heavy rocker! It's pretty great! As for [s]International Colouring Contest[/s], it's a surprisingly silly pop song, but not really unenjoyable. And for a really strange finale, [s]Fiery Yellow[/s] &mdash; written by Sean O'Hagan, who left the band during the recording of this album &mdash; is played entirely by marimbas, xylophones and other percussion instruments. It's minimal and repetitive, but I like it lots.</p>

<p>I don't know whether many other people had the same complaints as me, but it seems that, if you agree with me that the extreme repetitiveness of this album is a mistake, then the band learnt the lesson well, as we shall see shortly. Overall, this record is not essential, but you shouldn't throw it in the trash bin either. Get it only after you're familiar with the band, but once you are familiar, do get it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s][l]Commenté Sans Bouger[/l][/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="ectoplasm">
      <title>Refried Ectoplasm: Switched On, vol. 2</title>
      <year>1995</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Lo Boob Oscillator[/s], [s]Harmonium[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Harmonium</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Lo Boob Oscilator</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Mountain</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Revox</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>French Disko</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Exploding Head Movie</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Eloge d'Eros</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Tone Burst (Country)</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Animal or Vegetable (A Wonderful Wooden Reason)</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>John Cage Bubblegum</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Sadistic</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Farfisa</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tempter</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>As indicated by the title, this record is another compilation of non-album tracks. These songs, however, come from slightly more varied sources, not merely a couple of singles and EP's. Some tracks were previously unreleased, some released on obscure split singles, and two of them come with a colaboration with Steven Stapleton (infamous leader of Nurse With Wound). This makes the record even more necessary for Stereolab fans, because without it, some of the track simply can't be found.</p>

<p>I can argue that this record is even better than the first installment of [a]Switched On[/a] &mdash; not MUCH better, but there are three more tracks, and they're all good. Okay, not <em>all</em> good, but most of the tracks range from good to outstanding. Shall we begin with the outstanding ones first? Well, look no further than [s]Lo Boob Oscillator[/s], a fantastic pop song with a gorgeous rhythm with jangly guitars, snappy drums and delicious vocal harmonies, with L&aelig;titia Sadier putting her French for good use. When it has already done all of its pop goodness, it launches into the band's well known NEU! pastiche for a good two minutes or so, prolonging even further the song's greatness. Wait, but hadn't I complained about sameyness and repetition on [a]Mars Audiac Quintet[/a]? Well, this is where the killer thing comes in: the band sounds INCREDIBLE in this outro, and I definitely think it's all due to the production. It's not that slick, oiled sound of the previous album, but a crisp, upfront, crunchy, beaty sound that leaves me <em>truly</em> floored and asking for more. I love, love this track to bits.</p>

<p>You want another shocker? I'll give you another shocker: there are SEVERAL tracks here featuring the NEU! beat/guitar/organ framework and they ALL ROCK. [s]Harmonium[/s], for example, is one of them. The rhythm is much sparser, though, giving the song a "floating" feel, and there is a beautiful sound of a Moog synth in the background. In a way, this track (along with a few others) is a "spiritual successor" to [s]Mellotron[/s] from [a]Peng![/a]; the tempo is much slower and the instrumentation is all different, but the songwriting is similar: it's mostly a one chord drone (D major), but broken by a loud break a few bars long on the superdominant (E major). [s]Ruby[/s] by the Silver Apples was the same thing, and so was [s]Mellotron[/s]. And [s]Harmonium[/s] follows the pattern, and it's gorgeous, and has wonderful vocals as well (as usual!). [s]Farfisa[/s], on the other hand, maintains the same rhythm of [s]Mellotron[/s], but the chords and melody are all different. It's a nice tune as well. [s]Revox[/s] is more on the vein of [s]Nihilist Assault Group[/s], but the sound is kind of overbearing and annoying, so the repetition sort of loses its power. And the vocals are less pretty. To be frank, this song sounds like a lazy throwaway. [s]French Disko[/s], now, sounds NOTHING like a throwaway, and so far in their career, this is the song that best approaches what could be their "smash single": it's rocking and catchy as hell, and has the ladies singing "La R&eacute;sistance!" on the chorus. It's perfect.</p>

<p>Other poppy, accessible, catchy tunes here include the fast, gentle [s]Eloge d'Eros[/s] and the slightly more rocking and repetitive [s]John Cage Bubblegum[/s], both sung in French. [s]Mountain[/s] ain't exactly "poppy", and for some reason the production is different than in the other songs &mdash; kind of muffled, subdued somehow &mdash; but it's also melodic and catchy. [s]Sadistic[/s], on the other hand, is possibly the most frantic and, um, "schizophrenic" songs they recorded so far, with Sadier singing over some rather paranoid chords and doing short hilarious "rap" breaks between each of the sung lines. As for the closing song, [s]Tempter[/s], it's one of my favourites here; it's more in line with the slow and moody Stereolab songs, but it has a <em>very</em> insistent bass drum pulse giving motion to the song, and the singerines engage in some very beautiful vocal interplay, with L&aelig;titia singing her usual charming melodies and Mary backing up with some magical "dum dum-dee-dum dum-dee-dum". It's beautiful, I love it.</p>

<p>We're left with the biggest oddities in the record. The first one is a <em>COUNTRY</em> version of [s]Tone Burst[/s]. Of course, by "country", the band is referring to a single acoustic guitar rhythm, a gorgeous guitar line played with tremolo and some very light, galloping percussion. Add L&aelig;titia's vocals over there and you got a completely weird, but wonderful, version of the melody. It was previously unreleased, and I can only wonder what they recorded it for. Who knows? The next two tracks were released on the collaboration with Steven Stapleton of Nurse with Wound, [a]Crumb Duck[/a]. [s]Exploding Head Movie[/s] is merely a reworking of the second part of [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s], and the main differences is that it's slightly faster, the guitars are run through resonance filters going up and down to give it that "vomiting" effect, and L&aelig;titia's vocals are mixed in some bizarre way that they sound completely detached from the music. In my opinion, it's not worth very much, really. [s]Animal or Vegetable[/s], though, IS worth a lot; the subtitle from the song was taken from [s]Meadow Meal[/s] by Faust, and the song was written as a "homage" (if you know the Stereolabic meaning of "homage", of course) to Faust's [s]It's a Rainy Day (Sunshine Girl)[/s]. It actually starts out with some vague vocal mantras over a sparse organ accompaniment, but soon the thump-thump-thump-thump rhythm kicks in and the slow, exciting crescendo starts, leading to heavy guitar chords, schreeching guitars and heavy drum bashing. I <em>LOVE</em> this! In the final few minutes, Stapleton creates an ear-piercing tape collage with odd noises and assorted band recordings. It's weird, and I like it.</p>

<p>Be sure to grab this record eventually &mdash; if only for the absolute necessary songs such as [s]Harmonium[/s], [s]Lo Boob Oscillator[/s], [s]French Disko[/s] abd a few others. The ultra-rare or unavailable songs may not be absolutely essential for the casual fans, but they are definitely nice to have. In short, it's a great compilation and you'll be glad to have it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]Comments requested! Do your part![/l]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="ketchup">
      <title>Emperor Tomato Ketchup</title>
      <year>1996</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Tomorrow Is Already Here[/s], [s]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/s], [s]Cybele's Reverie[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Metronomic Underground</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Cybele's Reverie</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Percolator</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Les Yper-Sound</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Spark Plug</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>OLV 26</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Noise of Carpet</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Tomorrow Is Already Here</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Emperor Tomato Ketchup</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Monstre Sacre</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Motoroller Scalatron</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Slow Fast Hazel</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Anonymous Collective</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>If you ever heard of people talking &mdash; or read people discussing on the Internet &mdash; about Stereolab, the chances are very high that they were talking about, or at any point mentioned, this album. [a]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/a] has become almost synonymous with Stereolab, and it's very easy to see why: it's a <em>GODDAMN AMAZING</em> album. But not only that: it sums up excellently well the good things the band has been doing so far, but it also showcases much of what the band would become later on. In a way, it's a transitional album, but instead of showing an embryonic form of a Stereolab that would soon be, it displays a full-fledged, adventurous, creative and fearless band. Stereolab at this point is willing to do ANYTHING.</p>

<p>I'm not saying that this album shows every facet and every style the band ever tackled, no sir: but the boldness, the relentless curiosity and willing to experiment is already in full flight, and already in the first track! [s]Metronomic Underground[/s] kicks off with a funky groove, and develops into a rock steady, mesmerising funk with electric pianos, a sticky bass riff, Stereolab's trademark Vox organs, wordless vocals and Mary Hansen repeating "craZY / stuDY / a TOR- / -peDO" &mdash; most interesting words to start an album, I say! L&aelig;titia's lead vocals are pretty sparse, and the point is that the song is made of all these small pieces of sound weaved into a rich and groovy tune, sort of like some experiments from [a]Mars Audiac Quintet[/a], but actually danceable and boasting excellent production! And the song grows and grows, heavier and heavier, until the whole this is coming down at you. It goes on for 8 minutes but, unlike [s]Anamorphose[/s], you don't feel it at all.</p>

<p>What comes next is a catchy pop tune, but not the catchy pop tune that we're used to hearing, no sir! [s]Cybele's Reverie[/s] features a string quartet and one of the band's most dynamic, gripping and strong performances ever to this point. The main vocal melodies and the crescendo breaks with several instruments weaved int othe mix combine perfecly, and the result is one of the band's best songs so far. But as you can see, it's sort of improductive to go on at length about each and every song here, because they are ALL great. The only point in which the album sort of loses steam is on side four, but standing against such amazing songs, it's easy for one to lose steam! For the other three sides, the band is at an all time high, and they never let go.</p>

<p>So, shall we talk about the extremely jazzy [s]Percolator[/s], with a really cool riff for a really cool Moog tone and an awesome coda with some mean sax blowing? Or about the hard rocking, fast, sing-alongey [s]The Noise of Carpet[/s]? Or how about the fact that the obvious [s]Hallogallo[/s] copy-and-paste jobs are all but GONE here, and every song that borrows the famous "Motorik" beat adds an interesting twist to it? For example, [s]Les Yper-Sound[/s] has a really sparse electronic beat simulating the metronomic, insistent drumbeat of [s]Jenny Ondioline[/s] and the like, and the guitar is relegated to a mere muted "chunk-a-chunk chunk" rhythm. And the vocals are great, as usual, needless to say. [s]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/s], on the other hand, goes for an extremely bouncy rhythm with playful synthesizer work and a great vocal performance by Mary Hansen in French! You know, you might be annoyed at how I blasted the songs in [s]Mars Audiac Quintet[/s] for recycling the Motorik beat on and on and then praise this song that uses the exact same beat; but the thing is, the mood here is <em>extremely</em> playful and fun, and that long instrumental intro is sufficient to make the whole song &mdash; and then the vocals come in and deliver even more goodies. It's great.</p>

<p>I do have to say I'm pretty impressed by just how much the band CHANGED after the last record. But I guess the thing is Stereolab has always been this big mutating thing since day 0, but not until now has this fact been manifested so radically. I really don't think I can name any track here that is similar to any track in [a]Mars Audiac Quintet[/a], even though many of the "principles" remain. Take the repetitiveness and the weaving of many different lines present in [s]Anamorphose[/s]; a similar pattern reappears in [s]Tomorrow Is Already Here[/s], except here those ideas are framed within a more accessible song, and it's excellent. The alternating guitar chords along with the "block chords" from the organ, the stuttering drums and the vocal melody make a song that is plainly <em>hypnotic</em> and gorgeous. I know, it's cheesy to call a song "hypnotic", "mesmerising" and such, but that's the only proper way I can find to describe the effect this song causes in me; it just catches me and refuses to let go. As for "mesmerising", you can't go wrong with [s]OLV 26[/s], a slow song using an organ beatbox for rhythm and is carried forth by a buzzing, insistent bass riff. Ha! Ha! You think I didn't get it, do you? But I did! I'm just playing na&iuml;ve here, but I actually know that <em>THEY JUST MADE A NOTE-BY-NOTE COPY OF A RIFF FROM KRAFTWERK'S [s]AUTOBAHN[/s]!!</em> And this is no exaggeration, folks, the riff is <em>exactly the same</em>, only transposed to a different key. In case you don't know, the riff is that four note riff that comes after the very first "fahr'n fahr'n fahr'n" chorus. Instead of playing it in A, Stereolab played it in B, and wrote a heck of a great song around it. But how can I tolerate this kind of blatant plagiarism? I say, gimme a break, I doubt that Tim Gane thought he was fooling anyone. One thing is for Rod Stewart to take an incredible hook from an actually obscure artist (oscure in the States and in Europe, of course, because Jorge Ben has always been very big in Brazil) and using it on his song in order to score a hugely profitable smash single, and another is for Stereolab to quote a very recognisable riff from a very obvious landmark of electronic music to make an experimental song in a very non-commercial album. You may say I'm biased, but I say there are no absolute standards and when it comes to art, it's impossible to achieve an objective truth (with one exception: Coldplay's [s]Viva la Vida[/s] is NOT a Satriani rip-off and anyone who says otherwise is an obvious dumbass). Anyway, [s]OLV 26[/s] is beautiful, and it creates a pretty thick and dense atmosphere mostly with analogue synths and L&aelig;titia lambasting the religious idea of Paradise. The ending features a lengthy instrumental coda, and the playing here truly shines. As for the closing [s]Anonymous Collective[/s], it's a droning "ballad" featuring a nifty vocal melody and a very monotonous synth background. I'd be tempted to call it "medidative" if the mood wasn't so lighthearted.</p>

<p>[s]Monstre Sacre[/s], though, is definitely an oddity, not just in the record, but in the band's career so far. It is also a ballad, but it sounds genuinely SAD somehow; L&aelig;titia's lyrics are sort of hard to understand, but it sounds kind of personal and sombre. It's definitely beautiful, but, wow, weird. [s]Motoroller Scalatron[/s] and [s]Slow Fast Hazel[/s] are two songs that I never got too attached, for some reason. The former has a very fun organ riff and all the usual ingredients that make a good Stereolab song, but it's maybe a bit too... light? I dunno, it's objectively a good Stereolab song and I enjoy it while it's on, but it doesn't shine as the others. The latter is stranger: it alternates a slow and a fast rhythm (notice the title? Huh?) and the arrangement and melody are pretty extravagant. It's beautiful and all, but it just doesn't compare to the rest. Oh, hell, I guess this is the problem with albums with such amazing songs: I get all defensive with the weaker songs. But I tell you: put those two songs on [s]Mars Audiac Quintet[/s] and... heck, they wouldn't even FIT, but they'd be highlights.</p>

<p>If this review wasn't enough to convince you to grab this album, keep in mind that this is maybe one of the nicest records to hear the possibilities of analogue synths. They pull off <em>dozens</em> of tricks here, BUT!, the tricks are always in context and work towards the song. Notice the fat, upwards tone used in the opening riff of [s]Percolator[/s], or the fiddling around with the filters and the LFOs on the coda of [s]OLV 26[/s], or the chopping "helicopter" effects used in [s]The Noise of Carpet[/s] and the title track, or the swinging buzz in the intro of [s]Motoroller Scalatron[/s] &mdash; and that, funnily enough, closes the album. It's all great. This album <em>only</em> doesn't get a 15 because the band's masterpiece was yet to come, but please, do yourself a favour and don't miss this album. And if you have it, go put it on now. Do it for me! I'm a nice guy, am I not?</p>]]></review>
      <rating>14</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]Send your comments[/l]. [s]Anonymous Collective[/s] not allowed.</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="loops">
      <title>Dots and Loops</title>
      <year>1997</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Rainbo Conversation[/s], [s]A Flower Called Nowhere[/s], [s]Diagonals[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Brakhage</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Miss Modular</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>A Flower Called Nowhere</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Diagonals</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Prisoner of Mars</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Rainbo Conversation</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Refractions in the Plastic Pulse</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Parsec</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ticker-Tape of the Unconscious</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Contronatura</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>[a]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/a] may be their most essential, most immediately recommendable album ever, and it surely is a marvel in terms of the band's development and evolution and everyone, fan or not, must own it. But, for me, there is exactly one reason why it is not the band's ultimate masterpiece, and the reason is: this album exists.</p>

<p>I understand people who disagree with me, because [a]Dots and Loops[/a] is a lot less diverse, bold and adventurous than its predecessor, and much of the excitement of those jazzy, rocking, playful, bouncy and crazy songs all mixed together is lost here. However, this is smartly compensated by an amazing production and an <em>unbelievably high</em> songwriting quality. I'm absolutely serious when I say that, in terms of composition, the band reached an all time high here. Now, the production is an oddity. Tim Gane, with this record, started to experiment with some twisted ideas, and the title of the album partially reflects that. I don't know what the "dots" are, but the "loops" are pretty clear: much of what you hear in this record is not the band performing as, you know, a <em>band</em>, but is actually a bunch of loops of individual instruments playing. So, instead of recording a full take of drums, Gane would record drummer Andy Ramsay drumming away, select the best measures and use them as "blocks" for the recording. Same thing with bass, with vibraphone, with guitars and so on and on. Why he chose to do that, and why he chose to do that in THIS particular record isn't quite well explained &mdash; he just probably felt like it. But the thing is, if you didn't read about that, you probably wouldn't even realise how it was done! I listened to the album to a good ten times or so before I read about it, and I tell you, it is a LIE to say this album sounds "cold" or "mechanical" because of that. Maybe that's exactly what Gane was trying to prove? I don't doubt.</p>

<p>The songs do certainly allow themselves for this kind of treatment, because they are very rhythm and groove based. There are no extra-dynamic songs like [s]Cybele's Reverie[/s], for example; if you want to compare, [s]Metronomic Underground[/s] is a better example. But even still, the melodies, the arrangements, the textures and the moods in these songs are amazing. Take [s]Miss Modular[/s]; aside from having a wonderful danceable beat with snappy drums, groovy bass and shoulder-wagging acoustic guitars, L&aelig;titia and Mary's vocal performances have this "cool", as in "cool with sunglasses on" quality to them, but without sounding gimmicky &mdash; after all, they're singing about a trompe de l&oelig;il or something. But it's the vocal melody and the brass arrangement &mdash; yeah, the brass arrangement! &mdash; that make this song take off. [s]Diagonals[/s] is a similar affair, but is even better. The melody, replicated by the bass and the vocals, is wicked simple and wicked great, and that syncopated rhythm with the drums and electric guitar bouncing off each other in 5/4 is, for want of a better word, awesome. I was pretty excited when I realised just what is the trick of that pulsating, jerky organ sound in the organ: it's an organ plugged into a Vocoder being modulated by... the drums! It's one of those electronic gimmicks Tim Gane loves to play with, but it works wonders.</p>

<p>It's not quite true that this album lacks diversity and dynamics. No, it's not [a]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/a], but it is NOT this homogenous mass of loungey fluff that you may read around there. The album actually does swing around between different grooves and moods, and look! They even fiddle with <em>breakcore</em> in [s]Parsec[/s]! I know, it's not a Squarepusher song or anything, but it does have those rapid-fire, frantic drum outbursts all over it! And the tempo is fast, the rhythm is in 5/4 and that brilliant organ riff was stolen from somewhere I don't remember right now, and the singerines go "chee-pah chee-pa-chee pah pa-chee-pa-chee"! I love this tune, and bizarrely enough, it was used in a TV advert for the Wolksvagen Beetle (just the starting snippet). Immediately afterwards, [s]Ticker-Tape of the Unconscious[/s] (gotta love these titles) builds an infectious groove with more brass arrangements over a percussion sample from a Gal Costa record. Now, who on Earth would use a sample from an obscure Gal Costa record &mdash; that is, other than some obscure Brazilian band? I was shocked to discover that. Even though the song stays below the glorious ranks of [s]Miss Modular[/s] and [s]Diagonals[/s], it's great; similarly to [s]Brakhage[/s], that starts the record in a surprisingly understated note, with a hushed intro with brushy drums, a cute figure on vibraphone and a very gently swinging two chord pattern introducing a lovely vocal melody (isn't it just fun how L&aelig;titia opens the record singing "We need so daaaaaaamn... / many things..." Ahh, those twisted English lyrics!). Compared to the rest of the record, this song is surprisingly mellow and understated, and I guess that's why it opens the record so well.</p>

<p>There <em>are</em> ballads here, yes, like the even more understated [s]Prisoner of Mars[/s], which boasts an unbelievable bass riff against a quite sophisticated vocal melody. But trust me, that song pales next to [s]A Flower Called Nowhere[/s] and its 6/8 rhythm that's as urgent as it is melanchony, with high piched twangy chords, a simple and effective melody and beautiful harmonies and chord progressions. It's a wonderful composition, lovingly crafted and beautifully arranged. But then, [s]Rainbo Conversation[/s] comes in and almost makes the rest sound like shit. My goodness, what an amazing song! For starters, it's a bossa nova played in 5/4. It's not <em>quite</em> bossa, because it is a little faster and more urgent than that, but still, a rhythm that is already syncopated and groove by nature is twisted even further by a minus-one-beat-per-measure time. On top of that, there is this gorgeous texture of strings, marimba, acoustic guitar, percussion aplenty and the vocal melody. And instead of just hovering around with that pleasant sound, the song has a wonderful tension-and-release dynamic running through it, as it is going through a gentle crescendo that culminates in a quiet break with just percussion and vocal harmonies. This song rocks, and I don't care if people come here and say that Stereolab's "lounge crap" is much worse than what they did before, [s]Rainbo Conversation[/s] is still a masterpiece in my book.</p>

<p>One of the things that didn't change, in terms of musical style, in this here record is the trick of switching to a COMPLETELY DIFFERENT THING along the course of a song. [s]Refractions in the Plastic Pulse[/s] is sort of like that. It's not exactly because these four different parts are linked together by a single melodic motif. Well, three parts are linked, while the third part is hanging there, perhaps as an interlude. This track occupies the entire third side of the album, and it's pretty much like four different songs: the first is a gentle jazzy ballad in slow double waltz time that introduces the melody and the lyrics that make the basis of the entire track. A pulsating analog synth tone links it into the speedy second part that has a smart little organ figure. The third part is a very slow and quiet ballad thing that, as has been mentioned, has an entirely different melody and an entirely different set of lyrics, and the fourth part has a constantly ascending vocal melody and a string quartet adding all sorts of beautiful things. All those parts are linked by analog synth tones, and they really don't have much to do with each other, but they are all good. Likewise there's [s]Contronatura[/s], which is amazing, though: it starts with a quiet shuffle with a bass riff constantly carrying it forwards and the singerines doing thier usual magic. When I first heard this album, I assumed it would go on like that for all its 9 minutes, and I thought it was going to be wonderful. But then, the instruments go away, leaving just some sparse percussive noises, and the band breaks back in with a jaw-droppingly great disco-ish groove to close the album in a very high note.</p>

<p>I have absolutely no reservations in calling this my favourite Stereolab album ever &mdash; it's every bit as natural as calling [a]Dark Side of the Moon[/a] my favourite Pink Floyd album ever. [a]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/a] it's an essential album indeed, but this one is supreme, and it's impossible to get tired of it. Keep in mind the difference in tastes before you go headfirst into this album, but also remember that if THIS album doesn't do the trick to you, then you'd better stop with [a]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/a] and forget about the rest. Late period Stereolab does not get better than this.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>15</rating>
      <commentPhrase>"We need so daaaaaamnnn / many [l]comments[/l] / to keep our stupiiiiiid / sites running..."</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="tunes">
      <title>Aluminum Tunes: Switched On, vol. 3</title>
      <year>1998</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="night">
      <title>Cobra and Phases Group Play Voltage in the Milky Night</title>
      <year>1999</year>
      <highPoints>[s]The Free Design[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Fuses</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>People Do It All the Time</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Free Design</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Blips, Drips and Strips</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Italian Shoes Continuum</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Infinity Girl</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Spiracles</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Puncture in the Radax Permutation</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Velvet Water</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Blue Milk</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Caleidoscopic Gaze</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Strobo Acceleration</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Emergency Kisses</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Come Play in the Milky Night</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Something happened: Stereolab turned <em>serious</em>. I know that sounds weird, as [a]Dots and Loops[/a] is already very "serious" compared to [a]Emperor Tomato Ketchup[/a], but in terms of Stereolab as a whole, it is much more "laidback" than it is "serious". With this album, the band decided to go really big with thick and huge arrangements, syncopated rhythms, sophisticated song structures, experimentation with other styles and other things and so on. In short, it's a very ambitious record, and I'd say it's the most ambitious record Stereolab has put out so far, or even the most in their whole career. There's nothing wrong with ambition per se, and ambition is not the problem with this album. The problem is that this album is not as fun, not as catchy and not as pretty. And as you should know, fun, catchy and pretty are exactly what the band does best.</p>

<p>But don't turn away thinking that I'm jumping on the bandwagon of bashing this album. The relative lack of those three elements only mean this release is weaker than the releases that preceeded it. It's not a disappointment, it's not weak and it's not bad, but I will admit: it took me quite a lot of effort to try to get into the record. But it did pay off, and overall this album is still very enjoyable and a quite solid offering from the band. In parts, at least. Say, why don't we compare this with [a]Mars Audiac Quintet[/a] in terms of quality? So, the problems with that one were mostly the monotony, the endless recycling of formulas, and the fact that the most adventurous songs didn't satisfy much. These problems definitely don't appear here, as the songs are quite varied, but there is a severe lack of truly stand-out songs, and a few tracks <em>really</em> get a little tiresome. But on the whole, it's an enjoyable, if a little forgettable, record.</p>

<p>The saddest thing is that the album kicks off on an incredibly high note with [s]Fuses[/s], boasting a fast, polyrhythmic groove with dissonant entwined lines, weird melodies played on vibes and cute little wordless vocals. Hearing this song leaves one in complete disbelief that any song here could be dull; but it's followed by [s]People Do It All the Time[/s], a pretty lacklustre and unmemorable ballad. But then there is the amazing [s]The Free Design[/s], an amazing groove with a complex, fast rhythm and a relentless bass riff carrying it towards the latin-line brass arrangements and L&aelig;titia's smooth-as-heck vocals. This song is brilliant, and as it reaches the coda, the brasses suddenly play the main hook from ABBA's [s]Dancing Queen[/s]! I swear that, in my whole collection, there is no musical joke as unexpected and bold as this &mdash; and if you say you always expected Stereolab to quote ABBA in their music sometime, I'll call you a liar.</p>

<p>To focus of the record is not musical jokes, though. You can sum up most of the record's focus in one word: rhythm. The syncopated polyrhythms and twists on time signatures here are completely unique to this record in Stereolab's catalogue. Just check out the fragmented rhythm of [s]Blips, Drips and Strips[/s], featuring Mary Hansen's wordless singing matching perfectly the stuttering drum pattern &mdash; it's an incredible effect. But then, even when the band's weaving a brilliant tapestry of sounds and rhythms, the stuff going on top of it may not be all that interesting. You got exceptions like the catchy [s]Infinity Girl[/s], but then there are experiments with slow soundscapes like the first part of [s]Italian Shoes Continuum[/s] &mdash; it's far less interesting than the title suggests, and even when the song suddely switches into a fast groove, the only ear-catching thing is the "poing-poingy" filter effect applied to L&aelig;titia's singing. [s]The Spiracles[/s] is based on a simple piano groove, and it's pleasant and rather pretty, but not much more than that. [s]Puncture in the Radax Permutation[/s] is a little better, with a mysterious, ominous slow part bookending the song, and boasts a really beautiful, tense, nervous middle portion with Mary on lead vocals and a marimba arpeggio. A bizarre exception is [s]Caleidoscopic Gaze[/s], which has an incredible slow part bookending the song. I admit, though, that what's really so good about it is the melody played on a singing saw. You know what that is, don't you? It's a saw played with a violin bow, and the playing here is gorgeous. The faster middle portion isn't really very good, though, and the song is a tad too long at 8 minutes. Another exception is the gorgeous, dreamy ballad [s]Come Play in the Milky Night[/s]. Beautiful tune.</p>

<p>The most interesting and controversial song here is the 11 minute long [s]Blue Milk[/s], a song people are generally very tempted to call "minimalist", as it consists of a little mechanical thingamajik &mdash; two notes alternating on several high-pitched instruments &mdash; going on and on and on for about 9 minutes or so. Of course, it's not static repetition all the way through, as different layers and instruments come in and out of the mix, and the brew slowly gets denser and denser; the band isn't dumb enough not to put dynamics in this thing, right? At the tail end, the thing transforms into a mock-up of the NEU! pastiches of old, with the same thing played over a fast drum beat. Talk about NEU! pastiches, there is a track called [s]Strobo Acceleration[/s], and it's pretty much a throwback to those songs from [a]Refried Ectoplasm[/a]! Only the arrangement is smoother, featuring silky vocal melodies and a muted trumpet, but it has a very [s]Hallogallo[/s]ish bass riff. And isn't the title very reminiscent of [s]Outer Accelerator[/s]? I doubt this was unintentional. It's quite bizarre to hear the band doing such a big nod to the style of old in such a diverse and groundbreaking (for Stereolab's standards) record! Anyway, so is this record: a melting pot of a lot of different songs that sometimes work, sometimes don't. I won't lambast the record, however, but I have to say I don't hear it very often. It's not such an inviting listen, you know? But I gotta say, it's an interesting development for the band, and the effort is appreciated.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[l]Send your comments[/l]! [s]People Do It All the Time[/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="hungers">
      <title>The First of the Microbe Hunters</title>
      <year>2000</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="dust">
      <title>Sound-Dust</title>
      <year>2001</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Space Moth[/s], [s]Nothing to Do With Me[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Black Ants in Sound-Dust</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Space Moth</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Captain Easychord</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Baby Lulu</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Black Arts</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Hallucinex</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Double Rocker</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Gus the Mynah Bird</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Nought More Terrific Than Man</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Nothing to Do With Me</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Suggestion Diabolique</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Les Bon Bons des Raisons</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>So, how do you take the overall sound and form of [a]Cobra and Phases Group Play Voltage in the Milky Night[/a] and try to boost it up a bunch? Why, you write <em>great songs</em>! And it seems that's what Tim Gane & Co. (i.e. L&aelig;titia Sadier) decided to do here. It's hard to point out fundamental differences in sound and style between this record and the previous, other than that the band sounds more laid back here, and the sound, even maintaining the sophisticated jazzy arrangements, is much less busy. Maybe THAT is what this band needs: when they are less worried with stuffing a lot of things into the songs, the actual melodic content and the clever musical ideas all come to the surface. I'll write a letter to Tim Gane with that consideration.</p>

<p>Actually, I won't, but that goes without saying. What does go WITH saying is that the songs in this album are, overall, better than the last time around; not better enough to make this a <em>masterpiece</em> or anything, but enough to make me want to listen to this one more than [a]Cobra and Huge Album Titles Play Practical Jokes With the Poor Reviewer's Fingers in a Milky Boring Afternoon[/a]. Say, just to show how this album is lighter, they open the record up with a short instrumental intro, consisting of many, many layers of buzzing synths, tingling vibraphones, whizzing brasses and woodwinds and instruments going up and down in whole tone scales. It's cute and lasts less than two minutes, and it leads straight into [s]Space Moth[/s], a song that for a good few minutes plays out like a "space drone" or something like that, with an "outer space" arpeggio laying the ground for wordless vocalisations, woodwinds and whatnot. Then, it kicks into a mighty pseudo-disco groove led just by a kick drum, in which the band lays all of its melodic and harmonic magic. Just listen to how the song is filled with arrangements for tuned percussion, woodwinds and brasses, but it sounds oddly playful and gentle. It's not trying to shove complexity down your throat, yet it's still very finely textured. As the song nears a climax, the whole band engages in an extremely nice and invigorating instrumental coda with a really, really tasty horn part that closes every 16-bar phrase. It's beautiful and I like it.</p>

<p>There are very few moments in which the band tries to do something "experimental". One of them is [s]Gus the Mynah Bird[/s], that starts out as a nice, melodic jazzy ballad, and then dissolves into a very long "ambient" coda with faint synthesized sounds bouncing off each other. It is interesting and fairly entertaining, but not much more than that. [s]Suggestion Diabolique[/s] is the "multipart epic" of the record, and for the most part it really grips you and grooves along nicely; it is fun without being overbearing. The closer, [s]Les Bon Bons des Raisons[/s], is a very slow and airy ballad that features some extended lullabyish breaks and L&aelig;titia singing about being given chocolates so she will stop using her brain or something. For the most part, though, the album is chockful with poppy and catchy tunes in the best tradition of... well... looking back, Stereolab never really had an album that focused more on the poppy side than in the others; the catchy tunes were almost always there, but the band was doing all sorts of things besides that. But here, it seems the poppiness steals the spotlight for most of the record! This must be the band's poppiest album ever.</p>

<p>Say, you've got the EXTREMELY sticky and memorable [s]Captain Easychord[/s], that makes a crossover between a country ballad (Gane even plays a lap steel!) and a syncopated Stereolab groove. The title, I imagine, refers to those hammering piano chords that, overall, are quite easy to play except for a rhythmic break that might catch the less experience unguarded. More than halfway through, the song breaks into a faster part, which is great but not better than the first part. Still, it's one of my favourites here. Another one I love is [s]Nothing to Do With Me[/s], a delightful groove with some of the most endearing singing by the two ladies and hilarious lyrics built from jokes by Chris Morris; they exchange lines like they have never done before! It's great, I love it. Elsewhere there is the gentle, gorgeous [s]Baby Lulu[/s] (those ping-pong stereo drums, the middle portion with dreamy vocals and constant harp strumming and the horn arrangement are wonderful, wonderful stuff!), the strangely dark [s]The Black Arts[/s] that, nonetheless, breaks into an upbeat chorus, the excellently upbeat [s]Hallucinex[/s] (it features explosion sound effects and L&aelig;titia going "ka-bang!"), the loungey ballad [s]Nought More Terrific Than Man[/s] and the interesting [s]Double Rocker[/s], that features a deceptively slow and quiet intro and launches into another groovy, catchy rhythm.</p>

<p>Do I recommend this album? Well, for people who got [a]Dots and Loops[/a] and loved what the heard, yes, I definitely recommend it. But if you don't like Stereolab's "lounge" stuff and favour their rockier period, this album probably won't change your mind. You probably won't risk much if you get it, and I think it's quite probable that you'll dig at least a few of the songs in here. You MIGHT be disappointed about the lack of progression in terms of musical style, though; by this time, it seems Stereolab found a sort of "niche" and was all too happy to stick with it. But let's give then a bit of slack, shall we? After all, do they HAVE to be constantly changing or something? Sheesh.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s][l]Everything to Do With You[/l][/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="universe">
      <title>Instant 0 in the Universe</title>
      <year>2003</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Mass Riff[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>"... Sudden Stars"</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Jaunty Monty and the Bubbles of Silence</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Good Is Me</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Microclimate</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Mass Riff</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Of all the inumerable line up changes this band went through, this is probably the second truly memorable change... albeit in a truly terrible way. Mary Hansen was killed in a biking accident, and so the band lost an incredibly talented member and one of its most remarkable features. It's hard to even talk about it, and the band was surely devastated by the news.</p>

<p>This is the first release the band put out after the accident; it's a short EP, just over twenty minutes long, and it is... pretty slight. I'm willing to cut some slack for the band, because I imagine it would be hard for them to get in the proper gear to record, and I guess this is not supposed to be a heavyweight release. So, it's not the kind of record that I would recommend, but even still it's not bad at all. One thing the record features is a pretty unorthodox style of mixing, that involves every instrument being put either on the hard left or in the hard right &mdash; that is, there is no such thing as a "stereo field", but two completely independent channels. When an instrument is put on both channels at the same time, it may <em>seem</em> like there is a "center", but there isn't any. Yeah, this is another of Tim Gane's playful throwbacks to those 60's records that feature "THE SOUND OF THE FUTURE" or something like that. Stuff like that is full of curiosities and relics, and it's exactly that stuff that Gane is obsessed with. Say, have you heard about "binaural" records? Before they figured out how to make proper stereo records (that is, aside from using left-to-right oscillations, using up-and-down oscillations and making simple additions and subtractions between both signals to extract the L signal and the R signal), someone built a cartridge that was actually TWO cartridges attached to each other at a fixed distance, that would be playing two mono grooves at the same time: the outermost groove of the record carried one channel, and the innermost had the other. That involved the record having only half as much music, of course. Oh, and there were/are vinyl records that play from the inside out, but that's for another time.</p>

<p>The production and arrangements here are pretty stripped down and far more minimal than in [a]Sound-Dust[/a] &mdash; no strings, no brasses, no sophisticated textures. This is pretty much a "band effort", and you'll hear much more of the guitars, analogue synths, electric pianos and Vox organs the band likes so much. As for the tracks here, only two really stand out somehow: the extremely pretty [s]"... Sudden Stars"[/s], with an endearing vocal performance by L&aelig;titia and a very charming, gentle, pretty arrangement. The second one is [s]Mass Riff[/s] that kicks in with a bluesy rhythm with organs and the usual Stereolab thingamajik before it suddenly cuts into a <em>disco groove</em> &mdash; and I don't mean those "pseudo-disco" things the band has tried in songs like [s]Contronatura[/s], I mean an <em>actual disco groove</em>! And it's so tight and groovy that you can almost believe it's not Stereolab at all. The melody and distortion in L&aelig;titia's voice also adds a lot to the groove, and the result is amazing.</p>

<p>The other three don't really call my attention, but they're enjoyable while they're on. That extra-jerky electronic groove in [s]Jaunty Monty and the Bubbles of Silence[/s] definitely is jaunty, and it's fun, but not very substantial; it will hardly stick to your mind the first times you hear it. The other tracks are two little hyperactive tunes that feature not one, not two, but THREE distinct grooves each! [s]Good Is Me[/s] kicks off with a really cool, funky rhythm and twisted harmonies, that alternates with a slower, more "chilled out" groove and an exquisite, sophisticated coda. [s]Microclimate[/s] is lighter, and I really like that neat ballad-like part in the intro, that keeps switching into a faster, boppy section before it goes off into a non-sequitur ending. You could call them "complex", but with the band at this state, they sound more "disconnected" instead, and it sounds awfully like the band is lacking direction here. But, hey, there's still time for recovery, right?</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]Good Is [l]Comments[/l][/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="eclipse">
      <title>Margerine Eclipse</title>
      <year>2004</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Feel and Triple[/s], [s]Vonal Declosion[/s], [s]Dear Marge[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Vonal Declosion</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Need to Be</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>"... Sudden Stars"</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Cosmic Country Noir</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>La Demeure</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Margerine Rock</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Man With 100 Cells</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Margerine Melodie</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Hillbilly Motorbike</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Feel and Triple</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Bop Scotch</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Dear Marge</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The first LP without Mary Hansen, [a]Margerine Eclipse[/a] brings the mixing style of [a]Instant 0 in the Universe[/a] and applies it to <em>the whole record</em>. Amazingly enough, it doesn't sound gimmicky or detracting; if you hear it in normal speakers, you might not even notice it, and on headphones, the effect is quite interesting at times. As for the songs, well, they are a definite improvement over the previous release, they certainly are. But, for some reason, they just don't shine, sparkle and stand out as those in [a]Sound-Dust[/a], with just a few exceptions. The production is a little more polished and texturised than in its "little brother EP", but it still has that feel of "We're doing it on our own" from the band. Not that that's bad per se, after all, when it comes to Stereolab, changes should not be feared.</p>

<p>Two things are reprised from the previous EP: [s]"... Sudden Stars"[/s] is exactly the same as before, and in this album, it's sort of a small highlight, better than most of the tracks. Also, the amazing disco groove of [s]Mass Riff[/s] is stuck at the end of [s]Dear Marge[/s], and it definitely sounds like the band liked it so much that they decided to put it here regardless of whether it fits or not, because it definitely does not fit as well as it fit on [s]Mass Riff[/s]... but they did worse in [s]Outer Accelerator[/s] anyway. Instead of being a bluesy groove, the first part of [s]Dead Marge[/s] is actually a very, very beautiful ballad, and one of the best things in the record. Further highlights are the extremely infectious, upbeat [s]Vonal Declosion[/s], and the way it opens the record might make you think that the whole record is going to be <em>amazing</em>. Well... the record doesn't hold up very well, but the song definitely is incredible. As for [s]Feel and Triple[/s], it's the band's tribute to Mary Hansen, and may be one of the very few times that L&aelig;titia wrote actually personal lyrics. The song itself is oddly upbeat and bouncy, yet it has an easily noticeable plaintive sound &mdash; it's sort of like the band wanted to express their sadness but also wanted to express Mary's happiness and energy, and that makes the song all the more touching. All I can say is, if <em>I</em> ever got a tribute song as gorgeous and moving as [s]Feel and Triple[/s], then I will know that my life was worth it. The gentle build-up and release along the song, the heartfelt singing, the delicate arrangements are worthy of a true masterpiece, and by the end when L&aelig;titia sings "As much as I don't want, I have to say goodbye," I am DEFINITELY moved.</p>

<p>Elsewhere, the music ranges from loungey jazzy affairs like [s]The Man With 100 Cells[/s] to the brilliant straight up rock 'n' roll of [s]Margerine Rock[/s]. Along the way we get some of the least remarkable songs, such as [s]Need to Be[/s], which IS beautiful, but that sort of just hangs in there, you know? [s]La Demeure[/s] is similar, featuring a jerky rhythm and all, but it's not very catchy. The fast and jaunty [s]Hillbilly Motorboke[/s] is definitely fun and catchy, but not much more than that. [s]Bop Scotch[/s] combines two different tunes, a little slow groove and a fast upbeat rocker, which are fun and enjoyable but don't jump out at me at all. Yeah, I may be sounding a little mean here, but trust me: these are all great tunes, and I absolutely enjoy them. See, kids? This is the problem with being a brilliant band: it's much easier to disappoint. But really, there's no need to lambast the band or anything. Oh, yes, there was the huge loss of Mary Hansen, but there's no point in trying to justify anything here: we're not putting Stereolab in trial here!</p>

<p>A highlight here is [s]Margerine Melodie[/s], and it kind of stands out from the others because the melody and the arrangements, while not outstanding, feel like they're being developed or worked with. The song feels more like a composition, rather than a simply "put together" thing. The ending is particularly nice, with all the instruments coming together and a great vocal melody adding closure to the proceedings. Maybe that's what lacked to the band: a will to develop the songs further, to beef them up... I dunno. The album is not disappointing or anything; I enjoy hearing it, and there are several songs here that I enjoy quite a bit. Overall, I'd say it's not essential, but not worthy of the garbage bin at all. If anything, listen to [s]Feel and Triple[/s]; THAT is a gorgeous song.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]"... Sudden [l]Comments[/l]"[/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="antisun">
      <title>Oscillons from the Anti-Sun</title>
      <year>2005</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="suture">
      <title>Fab Four Suture</title>
      <year>2006</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="chords">
      <title>Chemical Chords</title>
      <year>2008</year>
      <highPoints>[s]Daisy Click Clack[/s], [s]Neon Beanbag[/s], [s]Chemical Chords[/s]</highPoints>
      <disc>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Neon Beanbag</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Three Women</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>One Finger Symphony</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Chemical Chords</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Estatic Static</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Valley Hi!</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Silver Sands</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Pop Molecule (Molecular Pop 1)</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Self-Portrait With "Electric Brain"</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Nous Vous Demondon Pardons</title></track>
        <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Cellulose Sunshine</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Fractal Dream of a Thing</title></track>
        <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Daisy Click Clack</title></track>
        <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Vortical Phonoteque</title></track>
      </disc>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>It might have occurred to Tim Gane that [s]Margerine Eclipse[/s] was pretty much a dead end, so he took a left turn and started to bring influences from Motown. Or at least that's what he said! After all, when it comes to Stereolab, you can't expect them to take their influences too literally &mdash; they're always willing to twist and turn everything they take into a brand new thing of their own. And that's what happens here.</p>

<p>So, what's new? The rhythms are definitely new: bouncy, snappy, responsive and sometimes jazzy like we've NEVER got from this band. The swaying grooves and frantic syncopations are pretty much gone in here. The arrangements are complex, textured finely detailes to unprecedent levels: there are brasses, woodwinds, strings, percussion aplenty, tuned percussion (wooden and metallic), harpsichord, piano, organs, guitars, synths and probably several other things. Putting things in perspective, this is a lot closer to [s]Sound-Dust[/s] than anything else, but the tempos are overall faster, the rhythms are tighter and the songs are a lot shorter. Why, this is no double LP, no siree! These fourteen tracks sum up less than 50 minutes.</p>

<p>But you may want to remind me that [a]Cobra and Phases Group Play Voltage in the Milky Night[/a] also had a lot of songs, and that was a problem because there were very few truly great songs and a couple of them were quite below par. But that doesn't happen in THIS album, not at all! I seriously can't name a track here that I would dispose of if I could. They are all good, and the few tracks that don't gain any pluses are perfectly enjoyable and worthwhile, especially in the context of the album. And the plussed songs, oh, my! Say, what about the opener, [s]Neon Beanbag[/s]? It already announces what the album has arrived for, with high pitched instruments jingling along a very fast, upbeat rhythm with great melodies scattered around the place &mdash; both the short little phrases played by assorted instruments and the vocal phrases and that VERY taste little tune played by a horn. Also, oddly enough, the song is made of several little segments that fall together like puzzle pieces. Yes, even THAT has changed! No more lingering around the same groove. [s]Three Women[/s] keeps up the quality with a slower R&B groove and very, very poppy melodies, brass arrangements and guitar riffs. As far as pop tunes go, this one is brave enough to compete with [s]Cybele's Reverie[/s], albeit having a completely different mood.</p>

<p>Aside from [s]Three Women[/s], there aren't any tracks here that could be identified as a "pop song" in terms of structure and arrangement, because all other songs are either very twisty and complex, or downright freaked out, like the noisy, buzzy instrumental [s]Pop Molecule[/s] &mdash; no, don't trust the title, which is probably a little joke, as the song is very barebones and repetitive, but absolutely interesting and fun. [s]One Finger Symphony[/s] is funny, featuring very mechanical playing, very short and simple phrases on guitars, marimba and brasses. Both tracks are short and help add variety to the proceedings. On the longer, more "serious" side of things you get the (aptly titled) title track, built on a brilliant rhythm carried forth by keyboards, featuring sparse percussion and magnificent arrangements for strings and brasses, over which L&aelig;titia lays a fairly contemplative melody. This is an easy contender for best song in here, and you don't find many songs in Stereolab's catalogue that match its beauty. [s]The Estatic Static[/s] is more complex, featuring a snappier, faster rhythm and percussive arrangements in the choruses. At the end, it features a beautiful, oddly plaintive instrumental coda, which is then immediately followed by the gorgeous, short 'n' sweet [s]Valley Hi![/s]. I don't really know what it is that makes this song so charming and captivating, but I guess it has to do with those little melodies that bookend the only chorus. It's a headspinning little song and one of my favourites in here. The honour of being my favourite, however, falls to the incredibly pretty, playful and almost silly [s]Daisy Click Clack[/s], that waltzes along like a simple little dance tune with little arrangements cascading around it and L&aelig;titia singing fun onomatopoeic lyrics along to the tune. You don't hear Stereolab being THIS lighthearted and fun all the time!</p>

<p>There is more! Yes, there is definitely more. It's honestly sort of pointless to talk about the individual songs, as they basically form a continuous whole along the song, with maybe just [s]Cellulose Sunshine[/s] sticking out as a kind of pastiche of 60's psychedelic rock led by a harpsichord. Even when the songs themselves aren't extremely noteworthy, they're filled with those little <em>moments</em>, those magnificent hooks that grab your unguarded ears and leave their permanent mark in there, that you can distinctly remember right away on first listen even if you have no idea what was the song they were in. The boppy, upbeat [s]Silver Sands[/s] has an insanely catchy tune in the chorus, as a call-and-response between a horn and a guitar, and later between two vocal layers an octave apart; [s]Self-Portrair With "Electric Brain"[/s] has little breaks with a vibraphone and a bass playing a little 4 note call, which is pure brilliance; [s]Nous Vous Demondon Pardons[/s] has a beautiful little synth melody played over the march-like portions in the beginning and the middle; [s]Fractal Dream of a Thing[/s] is beautiful in its entirety, but has an absolutely gorgeous chorus with a brief moment of almost dissonant haze of strings leading into the chorus; finally [s]Vortical Phonoteque[/s], that closes the album in a downbeat, soothing note, has a wonderfully simple and beautiful guitar solo halfway through. As you see, there's sheer prettiness and fun <em>all over</em> the album, and the songs flow magnificently without ever featuring a dull, unexciting moment. The album is varied, dynamic, complex, and shows once again the ability that mr. Tim Gane has to combine the backwards "retro" movement with his forward thinking. It's releases like these that make me want to slap those who keep whining about how all music nowadays is crap and how everything was better in the 60's/70's/80's... yes! There ARE people who think the 80's were the best decade ever! Of course, those poor sods were born either in the very late 70's or during the 80's, therefore have their sweet childhood memories permanently attached to huge hair, colourful clothes and shitty synthpop; or they were born after the 80's and caught exactly the growing fad of 80's nostalgia and have the same fondness for that time that some older guys have for the time THEY haven't lived, i.e. the 70's, thinking that the radio back then didn't play as much garbage as it plays today.</p>

<p>Okay, I will concede that maybe the radio is focusing more on the "commercial crap" nowadays exactly because access to music is becoming so ubiquitous and easy, therefore the folks who live off this thing have to go berserk in other to survive. That's just a conjecture, and I honestly don't buy it; I think things nowadays are exactly how they were before, we have amazing music being produced today, and the only reason why nostalgia exists is that people tend to overlook the difficulties and bad things of the past times and gather only the positive memories, therefore making everything old seem better in comparison. Bollocks to those folks, I say! My childhood and my youth were crap and I'm a much happiper person NOW, and I live the present and I'm totally hooked on the folks who are making great music today. Unfortunately that's now the case of Stereolab anymore, as they have gone into an "indefinite hiatus" in 2009, and are not making awesome music anymore, at least not for now. But if they ever come back, I'll be waiting with a smile on my face, and I'll be among the first folks who cheer their return. Actually that's a lie, because I am terrible at following the musical news and I'll probably only hear about it after their next album is released.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>13</rating>
      <commentPhrase>[s]One Finger [l]Comment[/l][/s]</commentPhrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="notmusic">
      <title>Not Music</title>
      <year>2010</year>
    </album>
  </artist>
</updateList>