<?xml version="1.0"?>
<update-list>
  <update-title>The Jolly Green presents a Moody Blue update</update-title>
  <update-link>http://sirmustapha.0sites.org/reviews.php?a=blues</update-link>
  <update-text><![CDATA[]]></update-text>
  <artist ref="blues">
    <name>The Moody Blues</name>
    <text><![CDATA[
<p>If you read my Queen page, you'll see me opening the page by saying that Queen manages to be "both overrated and underrated". I suppose you can multiply that definition by 10 and apply it to the Moody Blues, especially the "underrated" part. This band has played a huge role in rock history, especially with their revolutionary "debut" LP [a]Days of Future Passed[/a] in 1967 for Deram, and their importance is still oversated to these days. However, a large part of the world considers them just a bunch of old geezers with moustaches who play every song as if it was a Mahler symphony and still play [s]Nights in White Satin[/s] in every single concert to this very day. In this last aspect, well... I frankly don't blame those people. It's not easy to break the shell and truly get into the core of this band's music, but the truth is, the bombastic and self-important nature of their music was but a product of its time, and if you manage to get past that, you'll find a band that's an <em>absolutely necessary</em> listen to understand all the "art rock" buzz, as a great band in its own right.</p>

<p>The band actually started as a plain and simple rock 'n' roll five piece band, who released a few successful singles and an unsuccessful LP on Decca Records in 1965. At this time, they were consisted of Denny Laine on guitar, Clint Warwick on bass guitar, Mike Pinder on keyboards, Ray Thomas on flute and percussion, and Graeme Edge on drums. The two first members eventually left the group, and were replaced by Justin Hayward on guitar and John Lodge on bass guitar. Under that formation, the band started to grow into a more ambitious unit, creating a song cycle that was performed on their live shows. Such song cycle was released in 1967 by Deram Records, a subsidiary of Decca, with the London Festival Orchestra conducted by Peter Knight, in one of the label's displays of the "Deramic Sound System", a stereo recording system that allegedly replaced the unnatural, artificial stereo sound of yore with a far more natural and authentic sound. Such record was [a]Days of Future Passed[/a], which went on to become a great hit, and spawned the ultra super-smash worldwide master wow I mean like really really multibillion selling hit single [s]Nights in White Satin[/s].</p>

<p>As bold and unusual as it was to bring together an orchestra with a pop group, the orchestra did not play <em>along</em> with the band, but only provided little interludes to link the songs together. Still, this lush and huge sound influenced the band to pursue something similar in their following records. Most of their seven first LPs (called by fans the "Core Seven") are conceptual albums, with songs fading into each other forming sidelong "suites" of sorts, important and painstakingly crafted lyrics, and massive arrangements and instrumentation. Most of the sound was the product of Mike Pinder's Mellotron, one of the classic Prog Rock instruments, which Pinder actually helped to build and perfect. Pinder did not merely <em>play</em> the Mellotron, but he basically knew it inside out, and his work in the Moody Blues is among some of the most complex and rich displays of the Mellotron's power. All five members were songwriters, with Graeme Edge contributing less than the others, and they all contributed somehow to the sound. Another trademark is Ray Thomas's flute, which was used in a far more melodic and less "rock 'n' roll" way than that of Ian Anderson: no playing sound on one foot, but a lot of melody goodiness to the songs. Lodge and Hayward were overall the two central songwriting forces, and the latter had the most distinctive singing voice of all.</p>

<p>But beware, though: they <em>were</em> pretentious. They stuck pieces of recited poetry at the beginning and/or ending of their albums, they usually had self-important and grandiose messages to give, and they usually made everything sound really, really huge. But how can you condemn those things when, at their core, is a very strong sense of melody, true skill and heart at all things beautiful, and a real load of por smoke and acid? There's not much you can do about it other than take it for what it is. If you don't like 'em, just don't say they didn't know how to pen a really good melody; and if you do, you'll really like it.</p>

<p>Ah, yes: after the "core seven", they became a progressively more generic synth-happy pop band and Mike Pinder was replaced with Patrick Moraz. But THAT is for later.</p>]]>
    </text>
    <album ref="passed">
      <title>Days of Future Passed</title>
      <year>1967</year>
      <high-points>[s]Forever Afternoon (Tuesday?)[/s], [s]Peak Hour[/s], [s]Nights in White Satin[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>2</grade> <title>The Day Begins</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Dawn: Dawn Is a Feeling</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Morning: Another Morning</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Lunch Break: Peak Hour</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Afternoon: Forever Afternoon (Tuesday?) / (Evening) Time to Get Away</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Evening: Sunset / Twilight Time</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Night: Nights in White Satin</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>By this point, the band, now with their proper "classic" line-up, was already fed up with playing R&amp;B covers, and already had their set of original songs being played on their live shows. It was time to get <em>big</em>. Conveniently, Decca Records was interested in showing the full potential of their "Deramic Sound System", so the band was recruited to record an album together with the London Festival Orchestra, under the baton of Peter Knight. Things couldn't possibly be more appropriate for the band's ambitions. Tales from the Moody Blue Lore say that Deram Records' intention was the make a "rock" adaptation of the Symphony No. 9 by Antonin Dvo&#345;&aacute;k, and the band decided to embrace the opportunity and change the plans, at first without the label's knowledge, to record their own album. If that story seems too fanciful for you, you <em>may</em> be correct: some Decca employees dispute that story, such as <a href="http://www.soundonsound.com/sos/jul09/articles/classictracks_0709.htm">engineer Derek Varnals</a>, who worked on the album. But honestly, discussing that story only detracts from the actual quality of the music, so let's put that one to rest.</p>

<p>Fact is, I've already mentioned sort of what this album is about on the page introduction: the band's songs are tied together by orchestral interludes written and conducted by Peter Knight, and the five introductory minutes are also done entirely by the orchestra. Thing is, Knight's orchestrations were probably so good, so hip and so right, so groovy it's outasite, <em>way back</em> in 1967. They did it to keep "up with the times", you know? They were not trying to mime classical composers, and instead they were trying to make it all sound like Disney musicals or something like that, and as a result, this stuff sounds <em>dated and cheesy all the way to Hell and back</em>. It's one thing when the music is dated but you can see the quality inside it; another thing is when every arrangement, every rhythm, every "soaring" strings passage, every tinkly harp frill, every "cute" glockenspiel tune, in short, <em>every single note</em> reeks of cheese, to the point that either: a) You love this stuff to death; b) You try really, really hard to tolerate it; c) You despise it to death. Okay, so you can just learn to ignore it, but I fail to see how one would "not mind" it or just "like" it. The cheese is way too much for <em>me</em> to handle. Now, I won't blame it on Peter Knight, as I hardly believe that he would choose this style out of his own accord, much less the Moody Blues themselves. Hell, if the legend is right and they <em>were</em> intended to record Dvo&#345;&aacute;k's 9th, then it means Knight did have the chops to pull off a pseudo-classical piece if he wanted. As it is, he was certainly following the vision of the record label &mdash; it was Decca who wanted this "hip and modern" sound. If I wanted to demonstrate that, I'd look for other "Deramic Sound System" releases from that time, I won't do that. I think it's impossible enough to find a digital copy on the Internet, let alone a physical issue in this world's end They call Uzbekistan (I actually call it Brazil and I don't think it's a world's end, but don't let They hear that, or I'm a dead man!), so I'll leave that as a big question mark hovering above your head. Like this:</p>

<p>
<div style="font-size: 3em;">?</div>
&nbsp;O<br />
/|\<br />
/&nbsp;\</p>

<p>See?</p>

<p>The central thing on the album is not the orchestration, though! It's the band's compositions! And if you wanna check them out, you can simply skip the first track altogether, and the only thing you'll miss is a bit of "conceptuality" and a poem written by Graeme Edge and recited by Mike Pinder, entitled <em>Morning Glory</em> &mdash; in short, you'll miss NOTHING. I mean, what's the concept here? Each song represents one period of the day, with the mood and the lyrics reflecting that. There's no grander scheme of things: the deepest thing you may get from here is an analogy between the day and a man's life, a concept that's at least as old as the myth of Oedipus, though original enough for an "art rock" album. To begin with, I think <em>opening</em> the day with a grandiose, soaring prelude, quoting melodies from the whole album, is completely at odds with the concept. [s]The Day Begins[/s]? Why, I thought dawn was yet to come! It might make sense in musical terms to have such an overture, but I think it's completely at odds with the rest of the album. The only smart bit is that the track opens with a gong recorded backwards, mirroring the gong that closes the album, but that's that. And the poem? "Cold hearted orb that rules the night"? "Brave Helios, wake up your steeds"? <em>There are 14-year-olds writting better stuff and posting it on Fanfiction.net</em>, for Chrissakes! (Sorry, Chris! Didn't mean to use your name in vain!) The less said about Edge's poetry, the better.</p>

<p>But if you skip track one entirely, you'll only have to listen to a few seconds of orchestration before you're welcomed by the first proper song here, Mike Pinder's [s]Dawn Is a Feeling[/s], which is slow, stately and oddly melancholic, with a melody to kill for and lush arrangements for piano and Mellotron. It's a great tune to open the album with, because it shows the guys are <em>really</em> up to no joke here. I used to be a <em>little</em> put off by the song, because it didn't really match what dawn usually feels like to me, but that's no big deal at all. From here, the songs just keep getting better. You'll just have to endure the orchestral interludes and the endless quoting and re-quoting of the songs' melodies. One thing I find bizarre is that some songs are quoted over and over, while John Lodge's rip-roarin' rocker [s]Peak Hour[/s] isn't quoted at all! And even worse is that the song is preceeded by a <em>very</em> long and irritating orchestral passage that simply SHOULD NOT be there. This intro is easily the <em>worst</em> thing in the whole record, and triggers all sort of unpleasant associations with Broadway musicals, old Disney films and other things I despise. Fortunately, it's just a matter of patiently enduring that garbage, because even before the orchestra has faded out, the band kicks in and <em>blows the orchestra away</em>, as if they never did anything at all. Of course, it's not a <em>huge ass-kicking hard rock</em> song, and the muddy production mutes some of the energy, but the song is fast, groovy, features all sorts of catchy melody lines, a dead-simple and memorable chorus, guitar and Mellotron solos and even a solemn, stately middle break. It may show that, while the band didn't have the chops to "rock out", they had all it takes to get you entertained. Great tune.</p>

<p>Most of the other songs range between upbeat pop tunes and slow ballads, usually somewhere in between. Mike Pinder is responsible for the only <em>real</em> surprise, which is the tribal, barebones [s]The Sunset[/s], taking its influences from aboryginal chants and whatnot, combining a primitive drum beat with a sing-singey melody and an easternish strings theme. It's an utterly unusual way to symbolise a sunset, but the effect it causes is great. The other songs may not be "surprising" in that sense, but they are <em>all great</em>. Ray Thomas has the [s]Another Morning[/s] ditty, which represents the imagery of children playing with a galloping rhythm and an absolutely delightful flute tune. [s]Twilight Time[/s], at the other side of the thematic spectrum, uses playful imagery in its lyrics, and the music mixes extraordinarily the fast and upbeat rhythm with a more nocturnal and gloom-ish mood. John Lodge, aside from the aforementioned rocker, contributes the far more low-key [s](Evening) Time to Get Away[/s], which actually contrasts a <em>very</em> gloomy and beautiful verse with a jolly and catchy as hell chorus. By golly, where did they pull these glorious melodies from? Of course, it probably helped them that this album matured through the years, but still! So much great songwriting, it's pretty unbelievable.</p>

<p>The two biggest classics of the album came from the pen of Justin Hayward. Even though they were the biggest hits here, I don't think they outshine the rest of the tracks by such a large margin. I'm not playing the "cool alternative dude" here by saying that [s]Nights in White Satin[/s] is not my favourite track; if you're never heard that one, do yourself a favour and look it up on YouTube or something, because it's a stone cold classic and <em>everyone</em> needs to know it, and know it well. It's a brilliant track, in which the band conjures a solemn and, in fact, pretty depressing mood and launch it to the skies in the form of a chorus that will <em>never</em> leave your mind. Overblown to all hell, yes, but you can't deny the power of that melody and, especially, Ray Thomas's flute solo in the middle. Of course, if you think the song itself is overblown, you'll probably have a heart attack when you hear Knight's closing orchestration; not to mention Graeme Edge's closing poem, which doesn't present such "gems" of poetry as in the opening one, but doesn't help matters much. Anyway, I still think [s]Forever Afternoon[/s] is the best one here, with a graceful, evocative melody entwined with a lovely work by Pinder on the Mellotron, constrasting with a more upbeat and snappy middle portion. Very catchy and sing-alongey, and the soaring transition between the "verse" portions and the swingy middle breaks are amazing. A real gem.</p>

<p>One final warning for those who got interested in this: after being released in 1967, the album got remixed for a Quadraphonic version. The mix was pretty different though, with subtle changes in the instrumentation of a few songs, and even dropping <em>entirely</em> a whole harmony layer in the bridges of [s]Time to Get Away[/s]. Due to the deterioration of the original master tapes, every issue from 1978 onwards was based on the Quadrophonic mix, and <em>EVERY</em> issue includes every single CD reissue, even the most recent remastered deluxe ones. Thing is, the original tapes were permanently lost, and the <em>only</em> way to get it is looking for the LP's released before 1978. There are some good digital transfers floating around the Internet and you can find it relatively easily if you look for it. The changes are not radical enough to make the reissues <em>worthless</em>, though: if you're not an obsessive collector or an extreme purist, the latest reissues shall be <em>perfect</em> for you. Main thing is, this album is a definitive classic and a <em>necessity</em> for any music fan with the slightest drop of dignity. Despise the orchestrations as much as you want, you can't miss the songs. If, however, you happen to dig Knight's interludes (as some people actually do), this is going to be the ultimate Moody Blues thill. If you find the songs pretentious and overblown, well, you might want to miss the rest of the Moody Blues oeuvre (except maybe [a]A Question of Balance[/a]), but by no means ignore [a]Days of Future Passed[/a]. Grab it, dig it once, dig it twice, dig it once more, let it rest if you must, but at least make sure you remember how [s]Nights in White Satin[/s] goes.</p>
]]></review>
      <rating>14</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Another [l]Comment[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="chord">
      <title>In Search of the Last Chord</title>
      <year>1968</year>
      <high-points>[s]Legend of a Mind[/s], [s]House of Four Doors[/s], [s]Ride My See-Saw[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Departure</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ride My See-Saw</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Dr. Livingstone, I Presume</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>House of Four Doors</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Legend of a Mind</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>House of Four Doors, part 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Voices in the Sky</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Best Way to Travel</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Visions of Paradise</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Actor</title></track>
          <track><grade>2</grade> <title>The Word</title></track>
          <track><grade>2</grade> <title>Om</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Thank goodness the band didn't choose to use the orchestra anymore! Now we can <em>finally</em> admire the band in full flight, without a conductor trying to "cheesify" every little space between the songs to the taste of the record label. Phew! On the other hand, this must have left the band with a daunting task: now they were <em>fully</em> responsible for their material, and if they failed to deliver, it would be all too easy for the critics to say that [a]Days of Future Passed[/a] owed its glory to Peter Knight and the orchestra. Imagine that? The horror of imagining such judgement makes my skin crawl, and I don't doubt that some phillistines did say that. Time made justice due, though, and now people either praise the band and admire their efforts, or <em>hate everything about them</em>, including the orchestration.</p>

<p>One thing jumps to our sight here, though: the band was still aching to keep up with the times. And what was the best way to do so than to show you were into the psychedelic, love-and-peace, free-your-mind spirit? The whole album <em>reeks</em> of dope smoke and is loaded to the brim with LSD-induced colourful visions. Like before, there is a concept running through the album, but this time around, not all songs follow the concept to the letter. There are a couple of "digressions", and some songs that are only tangent to the grand scheme of things. Anyway, the story arc tells about the band's journey to find the mythical lost chord, starting off with Graeme Edge delivering some verses. Towards the end of the first side, the band visits four periods of music (medieval, baroque, romantic and rock 'n' roll) in the <em>House of four doors</em>. On side two, however, the band turns the whole thing into a search for inner peace and completeness, concluding that the lost chord is not "outside", but "inside", and the key to unlocking it is Om. It's all nonsense, of course, but it's, like, totally <em>groovy</em>, man! Totally <em>out there</em>! Cosmic and, like, <em>spaced out</em>! Now pass me the dope, man.</p>

<p>Before you become annoyed at the drug jokes, keep in mind I'm not condemning or dissing the band: they have openly admitted not to have "experimented" drugs, but at being "experts at it". If I'm not mistaken, Justin Hayward said that, but I'm too lazy to look for it right now. No, I'm not stoned.</p>

<p>The band is stoned as hell, though. However, the music is <em>absolutely</em> professional and polished all the way to near perfection, with Pinder's Mellotron adding sparkle and elegance to every corner, and the composers' melodies shining like stars. Of course, when you compare these songs to the glory of [a]Days of Future Passed[/a], you can't help but feel a wee bit disappointed, but come on! Let's cut the guys some slack here. For starters, Graeme Edge reciting his poetry on [s]Departure[/s] is nowhere as horror inducing as it could have been: instead of the "heavenly" orchestral backdrop and Pinder's deep and booming voice, we have Edge gradually freaking out over a "kozmik" backdrop, and the result is just plain funny. I don't know if that's the <em>real</em> intention, as Edge's descent into laughter is more maniacal and delusional than humourous, but the effect just <em>can't</em> be taken serious. I don't take it at face value and that's fine. The closing poem, [s]The Word[/s], is a different matter: Pinder recites it with his booming voice, but without any musical backdrop at all. Good thing it's short.</p>

<p>As for the actual songs here, the <em>only</em> weak link that I can point my finger at is [s]Om[/s], a track that is so hopelessly clumsy in its purpose <em>and</em> its execution, that I can't help but feel a little sympathetic at the band. They were <em>trying</em>, you know? But they failed: the attempt at getting close to traditional Indian music and mantras just sends us straight into a mess of stereotypical pseudo-cosmicness, and it's not catchy or interesting at all. It's not entirely monotonous, as the instrumental break in the middle does have that intense, unexpected build-up with an ever increasing tempo, but it's just a nifty detail and that's all. As for the rest, I really have no complaints: be it on the ballads or the "rockers" (does anything here actually "rock"? Hardly), they definitely deliver.</p>

<p>For one, the big central core of the album, the little suite at the end of side A, is triumphant. Lodge's [s]House of Four Doors[/s] is a beautiful, slightly gloomy-sounding ballad with a wonderful set of melodies. Its main "feature" is the representation of four different stages of music, but that's not the only thing the song has going on: it's beautiful in its own right. As for the "four stages", the Medieval, Baroque and Romantic stages are represented with rearrangements of the song's own melodies (the "Romantic" bit actually has Pinder incarnating the "piano virtuoso" and giving off a really short, entertaining toccata), and the fourth, final stage is Ray Thomas's [s]Legend of a Mind[/s], a song about Timothy Leary. No, it's not metaphorical or allegorical or anything: they refer to Timothy Leary by name, and is all about tripping on acid. You doubt me? Listen to it yourself! But the thing is, the song is great! It's a heck of a tuneful and catchy song, with vocal harmonies aplenty and stylish Mellotron arrangements, and a glorious, extended instrumental break with Thomas and his flute showing all he's got, and Pinder going along nicely. This song has it <em>all</em> to be a disaster, but it's not, and it shows that, even when they are trying to be accepted, the Moody Blues do not surrender their musical skills and ambitions. Kudos for them.</p>

<p>The rest of the album is, fortunately, quite detached from the "kozmik" concept, only dropping a few mentions here and there, like in Pinder's [s]The Best Way to Travel[/s]. I actually really like this one: it's boppy, bouncy, Pinder's singing is uplifting and the melody is cute. What's not to like?... well, that organ interlude is really very goofy, and in a bad way. But come on! They could have made it a lot worse. There are some contributions in the happy and upbeat side &mdash; namely [s]Ride My See-Saw[/s], which is catchy as intoxicating heck, though not being <em>that</em> happy, and [s]Dr. Livingstone, I Presume[/s], which may turn off some due to its childlike nature, but entertains me quite a lot &mdash; and also some contributions in the meditative and gentle side &mdash; namely [s]Voices in the Sky[/s], which has Hayward's singing and Thomas's flute playing off each other quite nicely, and [s]Visions of Paradise[/s], which conjures the mandatory <em>sitar</em>, but makes up for the dorkiness with a beautiful melody and dreamy vocal harmonies. Somewhere in between you have Hayward's [s]The Actor[/s], which indeed achieves a wonderful effect with the contrast between the understated-and-barely-there verses and the soaring, cathartic choruses.</p>

<p>Now, if you have little tolerance for the drug-induced philosophy mumbo jumbo, you'd be better off skipping the last two tracks. [s]The Word[/s] is nothing but Pinder reciting another of Edge's "masterpieces" (without even some sound effects in the background), and [s]Om[/s] is <em>every bit as stupid as the title makes it seem</em>. The "ethnic" rhythm and texture, the spaced melody and vocal harmonies, the frantic climax halfway through and the 6 minute length &mdash; <em>nothing</em> makes the song truly take off into something noteworthy. I usually don't mind it when it's on, but let's be frank: it pretty much sucks. The really happy thing about this album is that [s]Om[/s] isn't at all representative of the album as a whole &mdash; not <em>musically</em>, at least. Today, the musical relevance still outweighs the lyrics and the concept, so it's unfair to dismiss it as a mere product of its time: it is certainly a lot more than that. However, it is a lot weaker than the other albums in the Moody Blues' classic era. Don't try too hard to put your hands on it, but if the other albums make your head spin with joy, do get this one eventually.</p>
]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s][l]Comments[/l] in the Sky[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="dream">
      <title>On the Threshold of a Dream</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <high-points>[s]Send Me No Wine[/s], [s]Never Comes the Day[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>In the Beginning</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Lovely to See You</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Dear Diary</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Send Me No Wine</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>To Share Your Love</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>So Deep Within You</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Never Comes the Day</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Lazy Day</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Are You Sitting Comfortably?</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Dream</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Have You Heard? part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Voyage</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Have You Heard? part 2</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The psychedelia is mostly all gone. The drugs are not, of course, but at least you won't have to feel the scent of marijuana oozing out of your speakers while this album is on. There is still philosophy mumbo jumbo, a pretty-darn-silly concept and Mike Pinder reciting Graeme Edge poetry (oh! Why didn't the guy start writing <em>songs</em> sooner? If he were busier putting chords together rather than rhymes, we could have had a bit of a quality boost in these albums &mdash; <em>or not</em>, of course, but I am not that pessimistic). But at least, this time around, the concept is far less obtrusive. Through much of the album, you'll even forget that there <em>should</em> be a concept in here!</p>

<p>As for the songs, they keep getting better. As far as ambitious and overblown compositions, in the likes of the [s]House of Four Doors / Legend of a Mind[/s] suite, Pinder brings a closing suite consisting of the instrumental [s]The Voyage[/s] and the tuneful bookends [s]Have You Heard?[/s], but it is far less pop-oriented and it suffers from being a bit <em>too</em> far-reaching. Still, it is a well crafted composition, and Pinder leaves no holes. Still, there's nothing here indicating that the Moody Blues are better at composing pseudo-neo-classical suites than their brand of "baroque pop" or whatever you wanna call it. On the contrary: the songs are so catchy and strong that they convince me otherwise.</p>

<p>There are a few weak spots, but they are minor. Pinder's lustful [s]So Deep Within You[/s] is a bit too heavy on the bombast and too flaccid on the melody, and the final result is a bit icky. Edge's poetry still manages not to please at all, but at least the introductory poem has some interesting sound effects and "dialogue" in it, so it's far less obnoxious than Pinder's "Voice of God" effect on [s]The Word[/s]. No, the weak spots are not worth going on for so much. We've got some upbeat and rock 'n' roll songs! Hayward contributes the guitar-riffy and catchy-chorusy [s]Lovely to See You[/s], while Lodge brings two of them: the ultra fun and catchy [s]Send Me No Wine[/s] and the not-as-fun and not-as-catchy [s]To Share Our Love[/s]. Yes, so the three tunes are all concentrated on side A, and I have no idea why. Oh, wait, I do! Side B is mostly reserved to Pinder's suite, so yeah. But it does have one brilliant song: [s]Never Comes the Day[/s], which really doesn't score as high as the brilliant songs from the previous albums, but Hayward's vocal delivery and the dynamics between the verses choruses work a lot. Thomas's [s]Lazy Day[/s] somehow makes a lot of justice to its title, but not in the "pleasant day" sense and more in the "empty life" one. If you think that's downbeat, though, just check out [s]Dear Diary[/s]! There was <em>none</em> of this stuff in the last album, and only a small sample of it on [a]Days of Future Passed[/a]! Yes, it seems these guys are not all that cheery after all.</p>

<p>Well, one thing is certain: this is the first time in the band's career in which we can take a look at the band's songwriting skills in a focused way, without any distractions... err, well, with <em>far less</em> distractions than usual. The only problem is the lack of <em>truly stand out</em> songs in here. It's obvious they gave a lot of importance to [s]Never Comes the Day[/s], but, well... I don't know, maybe there was a bit of a lack of self-confidence going on here. And what's with Ray Thomas doing those introspective and downbeat songs? The album feels a bit like "we're kinda not ready to do things all on our own, guys, let's take it easy!". BUT! It's way too easy to make judgements, right? And, honestly, as a full package, this album is better than the last one: less stand-out songs, but a better overall impression. Or maybe it's just me: I'd rather have this band talking about dreams rather than drug-laced hallucinations. Is there any difference? For those guys, I don't know, but for <em>me</em> there is.</p>
]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Are You Sitting Comfortably?[/s] Then send your [l]comments[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="children">
      <title>To Our Children's Children's Children</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <high-points>[s]Out and In[/s], [s]Gypsy[/s], [s]Higher and Higher[/s], [s]Floating[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Higher and Higher</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Eyes of a Child I</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Floating</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Eyes of a Child II</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>I Never Thought I'd Live to Be a Hundred</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Beyond</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Out and In</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Gypsy</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Eternity Road</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Candle of Life</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Sun Is Still Shining</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>I Never Thought I'd Live to Be a Million</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Watching and Waiting</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Lack of self-confidence, eh? Well, either they started to take some bottles of it, or it was the use of yet another "concept" that infused them with some motivation. This time around, the whole album is built around a unifying concept; but this time around, it makes <em>sense</em>, you know? They're talking about the passage of time, the notion of infinity, using space travel as a symbol of progress and posterity. This way, all songs are linked together, and even when they are <em>really</em> outreaching, the songs have an actual message to deliver. And it sounds less like the work of five wise prophets with something important to say, but five guys who want to share some of their personal views on this subject. You know when you're trying to sleep at night, and you're sort of swallowed by the realisation that the universe is much, much, <em>much</em> bigger than you? And that, at the end, you're really just a speck of dust living away a life that will eventually vanish into nothingness? This album is something like that, but not <em>that</em> downbeat. In fact, the positive aspects are finely balanced with the negative ones.</p>

<p>But, since when do we listen to this band for the concepts, anyway? This album represents a massive leap forwards in the two most important aspects of their craft: the melody writing and the <em>sound</em>. Yes! The <em>sound</em>! This is the album that gave the band a really hard time to reproduce their sound in a live setting, because there's a <em>huge</em> reliance on Mike Pinder's work with the Mellotron. The arrangements, the textures, the production &mdash; it's a massive leap forwards, and we finally have an album that truly condenses everything that's so unique about the band. And it's not just the sound, because, like I said, the song writing itself also advanced a lot. They're writing stuff that's up there with [a]Days of Future Passed[/a]!</p>

<p>It's hard to even start to pick out flaws on this album, so it's much better to simply neglect them. "Wait", you say, "but what about Graeme Edge's poetry?" Well, you wouldn't believe it, but the man is finally writing <em>music</em>! And the only poem in the album, [s]Higher and Higher[/s], is countered by an absolutely kick-ass rock 'n' roll jam with soaring Mellotron strings, Hayward rocking out on his guitar, and the vocal harmonies going, indeed, higher and higher. And instead of a second poem at the end, Edge contributes the instrumental [s]Beyond[/s], which counters a fast-paced and riff-laden rock performance with "cosmic" Mellotron effects. The energy and sophistication of the performances certainly helps to neutralise the "goofiness" of the effects, but either way, the thick and powerful Mellotron sound is far, far better than the "spaced out" effects in [a]In Search of the Lost Chord[/a], so it's a win-win situation.</p>

<p>All the other tracks are songs, and there's no space for aimless "exploration". Okay, so the two tracks with very lengthy titles are short vignettes performed by Justin Hayward on the acoustic guitar, and they are cute and inobtrusive. We have the hard rocking [s]Gypsy[/s], which is far more on the "mean and dark" side than [s]Higher and Higher[/s], but we also have the gorgeously playful and uplifting [s]Floating[/s], which sounds just like the title suggests, and is catchy as all hell. And there's also Pinder's Mellotron masterwork [s]Out and In[/s], which I love to bits, despite the fact that it's not as catchy as some of the other songs. As far as catchiness is concerned, there is Lodge's two-part [s]Eyes of a Child[/s], Thomas's flute-laden [s]Eternity Road[/s] and Pinder's eastern-ish and joyful [s]Sun Is Still Shining[/s], all of which are excellent. But we do have downbeat tunes too, particularly the slow and solemn piano-and-Mellotron [s]Candle of Life[/s]. The only truly inexplicable thing about the album is the highlight they placed on [s]Watching and Waiting[/s], which was released as the album's single. It's a great ballad, but it's among the album's most gentle and humble tunes. A completely bizarre choice, but a great song nonetheless.</p>

<p>Great songs, great arrangement, great production. The only quibble I have with the production of this album &mdash; and, in fact, the production of all their albums so far &mdash; is why the drums are so muffled and inaudible. The Mellotron is top-notch, the guitars pop up in lots of strategic places, the vocal harmonies, keyboards, bass, they're all here. But the drums? Meh. Fortunately Edge is not the kind of drummer you'd want to place on the spotlight, and on the faster songs, you can hear him merrily banging away. But I have absolutely no hesitation in giving this album the highest rating. It fully, absolutely deserves it. But it's not the album that I'd recommend if you want one and only one Moody Blues album: [a]Days of Future Passed[/a] still deserves that honour. But what I have to say about that is: don't get only one album, get two! Get this one as well! And <em>then</em> you'll understand what's the deal with this band after all.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>15</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]I Never Thought I'd Live to [l]Receive a Comment[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="balance">
      <title>A Question of Balance</title>
      <year>1970</year>
      <high-points>[s]Question[/s], [s]And the Tide Rushes In[/s], [s]Melancholy Man[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Question</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>How Is It (We Are Here?)</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>And the Tide Rushes In</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Don't You Feel Small?</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Tortoise and the Hare</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>It's Up to You</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Minstrel Song</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Dawning Is the Day</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Melancholy Man</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Balance</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Lack of self-confidence, eh? Well, either they started to take some bottles of it, or it was the use of yet another "concept" that infused them with some motivation. This time around, the whole album is built around a unifying concept; but this time around, it makes <em>sense</em>, you know? They're talking about the passage of time, the notion of infinity, using space travel as a symbol of progress and posterity. This way, all songs are linked together, and even when they are <em>really</em> outreaching, the songs have an actual message to deliver. And it sounds less like the work of five wise prophets with something important to say, but five guys who want to share some of their personal views on this subject. You know when you're trying to sleep at night, and you're sort of swallowed by the realisation that the universe is much, much, <em>much</em> bigger than you? And that, at the end, you're really just a speck of dust living away a life that will eventually vanish into nothingness? This album is something like that, but not <em>that</em> downbeat. In fact, the positive aspects are finely balanced with the negative ones.</p>

<p>But, since when do we listen to this band for the concepts, anyway? This album represents a massive leap forwards in the two most important aspects of their craft: the melody writing and the <em>sound</em>. Yes! The <em>sound</em>! This is the album that gave the band a really hard time to reproduce their sound in a live setting, because there's a <em>huge</em> reliance on Mike Pinder's work with the Mellotron. The arrangements, the textures, the production &mdash; it's a massive leap forwards, and we finally have an album that truly condenses everything that's so unique about the band. And it's not just the sound, because, like I said, the song writing itself also advanced a lot. They're writing stuff that's up there with [a]Days of Future Passed[/a]!</p>

<p>It's hard to even start to pick out flaws on this album, so it's much better to simply neglect them. "Wait", you say, "but what about Graeme Edge's poetry?" Well, you wouldn't believe it, but the man is finally writing <em>music</em>! And the only poem in the album, [s]Higher and Higher[/s], is countered by an absolutely kick-ass rock 'n' roll jam with soaring Mellotron strings, Hayward rocking out on his guitar, and the vocal harmonies going, indeed, higher and higher. And instead of a second poem at the end, Edge contributes the instrumental [s]Beyond[/s], which counters a fast-paced and riff-laden rock performance with "cosmic" Mellotron effects. The energy and sophistication of the performances certainly helps to neutralise the "goofiness" of the effects, but either way, the thick and powerful Mellotron sound is far, far better than the "spaced out" effects in [a]In Search of the Lost Chord[/a], so it's a win-win situation.</p>

<p>All the other tracks are songs, and there's no space for aimless "exploration". Okay, so the two tracks with very lengthy titles are short vignettes performed by Justin Hayward on the acoustic guitar, and they are cute and inobtrusive. We have the hard rocking [s]Gypsy[/s], which is far more on the "mean and dark" side than [s]Higher and Higher[/s], but we also have the gorgeously playful and uplifting [s]Floating[/s], which sounds just like the title suggests, and is catchy as all hell. And there's also Pinder's Mellotron masterwork [s]Out and In[/s], which I love to bits, despite the fact that it's not as catchy as some of the other songs. As far as catchiness is concerned, there is Lodge's two-part [s]Eyes of a Child[/s], Thomas's flute-laden [s]Eternity Road[/s] and Pinder's eastern-ish and joyful [s]Sun Is Still Shining[/s], all of which are excellent. But we do have downbeat tunes too, particularly the slow and solemn piano-and-Mellotron [s]Candle of Life[/s]. The only truly inexplicable thing about the album is the highlight they placed on [s]Watching and Waiting[/s], which was released as the album's single. It's a great ballad, but it's among the album's most gentle and humble tunes. A completely bizarre choice, but a great song nonetheless.</p>

<p>Great songs, great arrangement, great production. The only quibble I have with the production of this album &mdash; and, in fact, the production of all their albums so far &mdash; is why the drums are so muffled and inaudible. The Mellotron is top-notch, the guitars pop up in lots of strategic places, the vocal harmonies, keyboards, bass, they're all here. But the drums? Meh. Fortunately Edge is not the kind of drummer you'd want to place on the spotlight, and on the faster songs, you can hear him merrily banging away. But I have absolutely no hesitation in giving this album the highest rating. It fully, absolutely deserves it. But it's not the album that I'd recommend if you want one and only one Moody Blues album: [a]Days of Future Passed[/a] still deserves that honour. But what I have to say about that is: don't get only one album, get two! Get this one as well! And <em>then</em> you'll understand what's the deal with this band after all.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>15</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]I Never Thought I'd Live to [l]Receive a Comment[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
  </artist>
</update-list>