<?xml version="1.0"?>
<updateList>
  <updateTitle>Pink Floyd</updateTitle>
  <updateLink>http://sirmustapha.0sites.org/reviews.php?a=floyd</updateLink>
  <updateText><![CDATA[]]></updateText>
  <artist ref="floyd">
    <name>Pink Floyd</name>
    <text><![CDATA[
<p>It's hard to find a better instance of a rock band which shows how <em>serious</em> and <em>artistic</em> rock music can be other than Pink Floyd. Not everybody is willing to admit that about the Beatles, and other relevant rock bands may be far more obscure. But Pink Floyd? You can't go wrong with them! In some circles, enjoying them is a sign of <em>worth</em>; in others, it's unthinkable not to like them; in some, the coolest thing you can say is that [a]Piper at the Gates of Dawn[a] is, hands down, the best Pink Floyd album ever. You can't go wrong with them.</p>

<p>I'm not the greatest reader of music boards and discussions out there, but I don't recall ever seeing a lot people whining about Pink Floyd's popularity. Usually, popularity is a <em>bad thing</em>, because it supposedly "cheapens" the band's value. I think that's bullshit, of course, but that's just me. But with Pink Floyd, their hugeness and insane popularity only give them more credit. Yet, about 80% of the band's popularity is focused on about, what, 20% of their output. I could whine about that, I seriously could. But I won't. I mean, [a]Dark Side of the Moon[/a] set a record for the longest period for an album to stay on the charts, [a]The Wall[/a] sold like cupcakes and so on. How many people know about their pre-[a]Dark Side of the Moon[/a] period? How many know that a guy named Syd Barrett was actually one of the founding members of the band? Not a crowd, certainly, but guess what? <em>Not everybody knows everything</em>. That may not be news, but many people just seem to refuse to accept that. Yes, it's a shame that so much of the band's great material is relatively obscure, but the most I can do about it is review the albums and spread the word. Complaining will do nothing about it.</p>

<p>In case you never heard the band, well, you have to do it. They are hyped to all hell, they are a boring clich&eacute;, but that's just how huge and important they are! You may simply not enjoy their style at all, but the least you should know is just how unique and peculiar their style is. They rarely ever set out to "ROCK YOUR SOCKS OFF!", their music was usually slow, the guitars slippery and watery, the keyboards very prominent, and the arrangements and production extremely sofisticated and complex. And THAT is how they reached the pantheon of rock music: no sheer power, no rocking out, just a lot of weight and effort. And what is good about their music? The melodies? Not really: usually the melodic content of their music was just enough to give the songs something to bite and chew, and only sometimes does something truly jump out and grab your brain. So, the playing? Except for David Gilmour's ultra-hyped guitar solos, the band's performances were extremely restrained and limited to working in favour of the songs and nothing more, no showing-off and soloing only as much as necessary. So, the innovation? Well, in terms of pushing the envelope, the band was truly into it in their first years, to the point of producing some works that they consider as true missteps themselves, but on their more popular stage, they were more concerned with expanding their field and not with "innovating". So... what is it?</p>

<p>It's easy, or maybe too easy, to define Pink Floyd's strength as a perfect combination and balance of many different, fine-tuned elements. Pink Floyd's songs, and sometimes their albums as a whole, seem to reveal a whole vision, a whole world of atmosphere and texture before you. Even the simplest and most basic songs seem to receive a herculean amount of work to make them sound profound and interesting. This can have opposite results, of course: just as you can praise that effort and the sheer depth of their work, you can complain about how overproduced and heavyhanded the whole thing is. Which attitude you'll take is entirely up to you. Is either of them "wrong"? No, I don't think so. It just depends on which side of the board you happen to land on. I happened to land on the former, therefore I <em>really</em> appreciate the incredible depth and meticulousness of their output. And that's what you get: even the simplest ideas end up taking an unbelievably huge scope, and they use every resource to open that scope as wide as possible. Their albums are incredible experiences for one to lose himself in &mdash; you can just let yourself drift away in the music and the atmospheres. Of course, this is no ambient and no new-age: the music will grab your attention and refuse to let go. It's no background music or easy-listening, that's for sure.</p>

<p>All things considered, when first entering their catalogue, you can just go and pick up any of their "four big" 70's records ([a]Dark Side of the Moon[/a], [a]Wish You Were Here[/a], [a]Animals[/a] and [a]The Wall[/a]). You'll make no mistake: those records distill the very essence of the band ([a]The Wall[/a] a little less so, but even still, all four records are quite distinct), they are excellent AND accessible. But don't miss out on the earlier releases: [a]Meddle[/a], in particular, is worth a listen, and their earliest, "psychedelic" records, are fascinating in their own right. As for their later output... well, tread carefully. But suffice to say, you'll probably have to own all their studio records anyway, so just go for it. And DON'T MISS OUT the soundtracks &mdash; they are essential.</p>]]>
  </text>
  <comments>
  <![CDATA[
<p><em>Reader comments:</em></p>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:seanduvall4@hotmail.com">Sean Duvall</a> (December 18, 2003):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p>
Excuse me for a moment but I must correct you. To say that David Gilmour's guitar work is slow and over calculated and (good god) COLD? Is just wrong my friend. You're telling me the solo on 'Another Brick in the Wall' wasnt one of the best ever played? The tone was perfect, the phrasing sublime...I feel bad that you cant see it.<br />
If I'm in the dark here please let me know what guitar players I should be listening to. Obviously I'm out of my fucking mind.<br />
<span class="edNote">[editor's note: Well, that's pretty much it. These are the basic feelings I get when listening to Dave Gilmour, and I guess neither of us is wrong - after all, it's just a matter of taste. But like I said, there <em>are</em> moments when David pulls off something real great out of his guitar. 'Another Brick In The Wall, part 2' is a good example, and so is 'Echoes' like I mentioned above. But his work on stuff from <strong>A Momentary Lapse Of Reason</strong> and <strong>The Division Bell</strong>, and even 'classics' like 'Comfortably Numb' never hit any nerve on me. And that's really the opinion I hold. If you want suggestions of other guitarists, I wholeheartedly recommend Mike Oldfield with his <strong>Ommadawn</strong>, <strong>Tubular Bells</strong> and <strong>Amarok</strong>. And thanks for the comments. Feel free to send more.]</span>
</p>
</div>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:straker@clear.net.nz">Jeff Stone</a> (November 20, 2004):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p>I must agree with you as re: most of your Pink Floyd comments.  However, I LOVE Fat Old Sun and Atom Heart Mother's one of PF's best tunes!  Nice site, sir. The South Park characters add that extra frisson.</p>
 
<p>Best of luck with your music!  I will recommend your site to others.</p>
 
<p>Regards<br />
Straker</p>
</div>

<p><a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail your ideas</a>!</p>

<hr /> ]]></comments>

    <album id="dawn">
      <title>The Piper at the Gates of Dawn</title>
      <year>1967</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Astronomy Domine[/s], [s]Interstellar Overdrive[/s], [s]Lucifer Sam[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Astronony Domine</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Lucifer Sam</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Matilda Mother</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Flaming</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Pow R Toc H</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Take Up Thy Stethoscope and Walk</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Interstellar Overdrive</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>The Gnone</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Chapter 24</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>The Scarecrow</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Bike</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>It's always a good idea to start from the beginning, especially when it comes to Pink Floyd. It has to be said, though, that their debut LP isn't even the proper "beginning" here. The Syd Barrett-led formation of Pink Floyd was known at the time mostly because of their wild, envelope-pushing live performances with huge, extended psychedelic jamming; a 3-minute ditty would basically turn into a 16-minute long sonic exploration with astral noise and whatever else they'd throw in the brew. In fact, when this album came out, some of the fanbase actually considered it <em>disappointing</em>, because it didn't mirror those performances, and the psychedelic noise and the astral jams <em>are where it's at, maaaan</em>.</p>

<p>Don't be misguided, though. If you're completely unfamiliar with this kind of music, you will <em>still</em> be utterly blown away by what you hear here. The jamming and the noise-making <em>are</em> here, but concentrated on a few of the tracks. The primary example of that is the opener of side B, the instrumental [s]Interstellar Overdrive[/s], which is pretty much the ultimate summation of the band's capabilities. It's bookended by a really mean, gruff, heavy riff, starting out with Syd plucking his guitar like there's no tomorrow, and the whole band crashing into a real blast. And <em>then</em>, it just keeps dissolving into dissonance, and turns into this massive, completely uncompromised... jam? I think it's demeaning to call this a "jam", because there's basically no concern for rhythm or structure or anything! No, sir, this is actually an experimental avant-garde composition, not a "jam". And while this thing would go on for 20 minutes or more in a live setting, the band and producer Norman Smith made the wise decision to keep this version trimmed down to 9 minutes, giving it a much bigger effect and raising its impact when placed along with the rest of the tracks. Imagine a whole side of this thing? It wouldn't really fit.</p>

<p>Everywhere else, the improvisational and exploratory aspect of the band is considerably more restrained, but not less exciting. [s]Astronomy Domine[/s] is a classic in every sense, with guitar work that combine the spaced-out starry-eyed with the heavy and menacing with absolute mastery, and a rhythm that sounds like it's constantly stubmling and crashing into you, instead of merely propelling itself forwards. Throw in Syd's evocative, alliterative lyrics, assorted studio effects and exhilarating band performance and you get one hell of a good reason to pick up this record. It had the harmful effect of making Pink Floyd pretty much synonymous with "space rock", and you should know that that's never been the case. However, if there is such a thing as "space rock", it wouldn't be such a stretch to say that [s]Astronomy Domine[/s] is the beginning <em>and</em> the end of it.</p>

<p>In other tracks, the band occasionally freaks out as well, but in a far more chaotic way. [s]Pow R Toc H[/s], for example, is basically an excuse for the band to go completely nuts with dissonance and bizarre animal noises (!!), dressed up in a pleasant little jazzy shuffle. I won't be a hypocrite and say I don't enjoy this, but it's much more of a little oddity rather than a true achievement. And there is Waters's [s]Take Up Thy Stethoscope and Walk[/s] (which is the only solo composition here that doesn't belong to Barrett), which is an awfully inane and obnoxious little "snippet" of a composition bookending an incredibly fast and whacked-out jam. Yes, the "song" portion is awful, but the jam is amazing! I can't help but enjoy it. Besides, in the studio, the jam went up to about 15 minutes, urging Norman Smith to do some severe editing and keep it down to three minutes. Phew! Smart move.</p>

<p>But Barrett is, first and foremost, a songwriter, and his skills in penning melodies and compositions is in full display here. Side two hosts some oddly folk-like, acoustic guitar laden tunes with fairy-tale lyrics such as [s]The Gnome[/s] and [s]The Scarecrow[/s], which is basically at complete odds with the rest of the album, but help a lot to create a slightly more complete picture of Barrett's world. [s]Chapter 24[/s] is more pot-induced than acid-induced, and uses the I Ching as source of inspiration, and maybe is a bit TOO slow and airy to create some substance, but it's still beautiful. Side one, however, has an amazing stretch of songs with begins with the aforementioned [s]Astronomy Domine[/s] and ends with [s]Flaming[/s]. [s]Lucifer Sam[/s] is head-spinningly fantastic, a sort of "surf-spy-rock" thing with an out-of-this-world guitar riff, fun lyrics about a cat, and entertaining band performances in the breaks between verses &mdash; even featuring Barrett using a bow on his guitar, and sounding <em>much, much</em> more fun and less ridiculous than Jimmy Page ever sounded. [s]Matilda Mother[/s] balances the psychedelic tendencies (check out that weird, menacing instrumental break with chilly whispers on top!) with Barrett's fascination with childhood and bedtime stories, all wrapped in a beautiful song, filled with tension-and-release. [s]Flaming[/s] is simply gorgeous and fun, featuring Barrett's most heartwarming and nice melodies in the album, and peppered with nice little "psychedelic" features.</p>

<p>Closing the album, there is the crazy, crazy [s]Bike[/s], with a very odd "stream of consciousness" vocal performance by Barrett and the band hilariously trying to keep track of his abrupt rhythmic left turns and unpredictable verse lengths. It's sort of like he doesn't give a damn about what they are playing behind him and just goes on singing whatever he feels like at the time. The result is odd, endearing and frightening all at once. It ends with an "illustration" of the "room of musical tunes" which already predicts the band's intense work with tape manipulation and sound effects in the future. The song must be heard to be believed, and it's oddly appropriate as a coda for the album. Is it representative? Heck, to this day I'm highly unsure about what track here is "representative". The best contenders are [s]Lucifer Sam[/s] and [s]Matilda Mother[/s], but certainly not [s]Astronomy Domine[/s] and [s]Interstellar Overdrive[/s]. Maybe these two were representative of the band's live act, but of the album? Don't even think about it. So, when you approach this album, be careful with your expectations. You'll not listen to the be-all-end-all of psychedelic avantgarde. It may take a while until you truly get what the album is, but then again, maybe you never will. And that is why the album is so legendary.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>13</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]YouComment[/l]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album id="secrets">
      <title>A Saucerful of Secrets</title>
      <year>1968</year>
      <highpoints>[s]A Saucerful of Secrets[/s], [s]See Saw[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Let There Be More Light</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Remember a Day</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Set the Controls for the Heart of the Sun</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Corporal Clegg</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>A Saucerful of Secrets</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>See Saw</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Jugband Blues</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>The most notable thing about Syd Barrett, aside from his groundbreaking guitar work and knack for grandiose, spaced-out writing, is the complete decline of his mental health. The story of his decadence is widely documented, told and retold in books and all over the Intnernet, so I won't be boring to tell it all over again, since I have nothing do add. The consequences of Barrett's fall were pretty severe, and the band was on the brink of collapse. Syd would ruin their live performances by "zoning out" and becoming completely alienated from the band and the audience, walking out mid-song and so on &mdash; well, most of the audience probably found his antics very cool and <em>cosmic, maaaan</em>, but the band was getting fed up with it and brought David Gilmour to act as a "contingency plan", by stepping in when Syd would zone out. Eventually, they decided to simply not pick up Syd on the way to a gig, but decided to keep him in the band as a songwriter and studio musician. Therefore, for a short while, they were a five piece band, and this album is the only document we have of that phase.</p>

<p>Still, only a few tracks here have Barrett's participation, and he composed only one song here. During the recordings, he left the band, after a series of misfortunes and sorry incidents. In my opinion, one of the most remarkable stories regarding this phase is when Barrett arrived to rehearsal one day with a new song called "Have You Got It Yet?", which was essentially a practical joke on the band, with Barrett changing the verses every time the band tried to join, while the chorus consisted of Barrett singing "Have you got it yet?" <em>to the band</em>. Eventually Waters walked out and never played with Syd again. It's hard for a story to be so hilarious and so depressing at the same time. But yeah, that pretty much illustrates the state of the band back then: Syd was on his way out, and the band had no idea of what to do. The only clue they had was to try to keep on doing exactly what they were already doing, and try to emulate Barrett's imagination and wackiness. The result is a definite far cry from [a]Piper at the Gates of Dawn[/a], and also shows a band pretty much without future, not only due to the lack of a musical leader, but also to the mistrust of the managers.</p>

<p>The band's biggest bet here was on the title track, an 11 minute psychedelic instrumental powerhouse, which on studio takes the form of an extremely elaborate work, and live would become a hellish beast. The main difference between this one and [s]Interstellar Overdrive[/s] is that [s]A Saucerful of Secrets[/s] is carefully structured and planned-out beforehand. It isn't merely free improvisation and experimentation on the spot. Quite the contrary: they were willing to see how far they could get on studio. The finished product is a piece that counts more on dynamics than on wild instrument flailing, and it even has an almost cathartic ending, with David Gilmour supplying wordless vocal harmonies. It's less noisy and daring, and whether that's good or bad, depends entirely on you.</p>

<p>Well, I think it's great. The song more than shows that the band has more than enough material to keep going, and it also shows that the band doesn't seem very in the mood for being "psychedelic". I would dare say that there is nothing "psychedelic" about this track; it's more related with science fiction than psychedelic. Okay, so [s]Astronomy Domine[/s] was all "space rock" too, but compare the two tracks and you'll hear what I mean. On the rest of the album, though, the attempts at being psychedelic are painfully obvious. They even "psych-up" Rick Wright's two songs, which are basically inoffensive, tuneful ballads. [s]Remember a Day[/s] suffers the most from it, and it doesn't help that the song isn't really very melodically strong, but it is still a good, atmospheric effort. Now [s]See Saw[/s] is a great one, tuneful, wistful and delicately bittersweet. And not even the "psychedelic" noise outbursts could spoil this one. Wright's understated vocal delivery does this one a real favour, as well as the high pitched falsettos. In my opinion, this is the first true great Wright songs; and there are many yet to come, just to keep you informed.</p>

<p>Most other songs fall very strictly on the "psychedelic" camp, with little subtlety and no holds barred. Yet, they aren't all completely alike. The "classic" [s]Set the Controls for the Heart of the Sun[/s] is, oddly enough, on the "meditative" side of psychedelia, which means: haunting and ominous bass line, sparse percussion, Waters semi-singing-semi-whispering, and even ambient "nature" sounds. I don't know why, but on live settings, they'd take this and turn it into a buffed-up psychedelic powerhouse. In here, the song doesn't really grab much of my attention; the main melody is a good one, but there doesn't seem to be a truly woven atmosphere in it. [s]Let There Be More Light[/s] swings all the way to the opposite way of the spectrum, straight into space-sci-fi-mumbo-jumbo with very radical dynamics between quiet and mantraic verses ("far-far-far-far away-way people heard him say-ay" and so on) and the loud 'n' blaring choruses. The two noteworthy moments in the track, though, are: the extra-cool intro with Waters delivering a fast bass riff, complete with organs and cymbal hits; and the coda, with David Gilmour displaying his famed, trademark guitar solo style: slow and methodic, letting the notes linger for as long as they may. This solo doesn't hit my nerves at all, though the band does bring up a pretty convincing sound-fest around him. Worth a listen.</p>

<p>The two remaining songs are more interesting cases. [s]Corporal Clegg[/s] features some dark humour with Waters talking about a disabled war veteran with an alcoholic wife. The music may be a little over-the-top and chaotic, but it works wonders in this context. It almost makes me believe that the band's "psychedelic" style, at this point, works best as humour as anything else &mdash; which is by no means an insult, after all, Syd Barrett did have a sense of humour. Besides, the way they combine ominous and mean guitar riffs, exaggerated vocal deliveries and a military march led by a kazoo is pretty brilliant. Not genius, but brilliant enough for me to award it a little red cross. As for [s]Jugband Blues[/s], Barrett's only composition in the album and <em>last</em> Barrett composition to appear on a Pink Floyd studio album, it already displays his lack of touch with reality. The lyrics are disjointed and almost meaningless. <em>Almost</em>: Barrett sings about his absence, as if he already knew his fate. The melody is just as disjointed as the lyrics, and the only thing that really keeps this song together is the imaginative arrangement, featuring even a brass band. Oh, yes, and the ending with Barrett alone with his guitar is gut-wrenching. It's obvious that this was the way for the band to give him a &mdash; fully deserved &mdash; nod of respect. In spite of all the flaws, it's impossible to deny that the song is a wonderous achievement. Yes, it's a weird conclusion for a weird album. For those who want to "document" the musical evolution of Pink Floyd, this album is a necessity. But it's heavily transitional, hit-or-miss nature may put off a few. For those who are interested mainly in their best material, this is not really very recommended; if you're thinking of getting it solely for the title track, well, there is [a]Ummagumma[/a], which may be a more compelling and interesting acquisition overall.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Let There Be More [l]Comments[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album id="more">
      <title>Soundtrack from the film More</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Cymbaline[/s], [s]Cirrus Minor[/s], [s]Green Is the Colour[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Cirrus Minor</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>The Nile Song</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Crying Song</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Up the Khyber</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Green Is the Colour</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Cymbaline</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Party Sequence</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Main Theme</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Ibiza Bar</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>More Blues</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Quicksilver</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>A Spanish Piece</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Dramatic Theme</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>There is a fact that many people are willing to overlook: a soundtrack album is, in many ways, very different from a studio album, and it's indeed hard to listen to a soundtrack record without thinking "oh, this was merely made to follow a film" (unless we're talking about Vangelis, but let's not make unfair comparisons, shall we?). But the truth is that a soundtrack album has the potential of unearthing aspects of a band that a regular studio album may never reveal. A band that puts itself on a different modus operandi is naturally going to produce uncommon results; and in some cases, this can greatly help a band to grow and evolve. I do believe that's the case with this record, a soundtrack to a film by Barbet Schroeder which I have never watched. It seems to be a good film, but I never felt compelled to watch it anyway, and it won't help you "understand" the album any better either way.</p>

<p>Thing is, it's easy to overlook this album, but I don't think it has any less merits than [a]A Saucerful of Secrets[/a]. In fact, it has <em>More</em> (ha!): though the music is still tinged with psychedelia, it is neither exaggerated or forced, and this allows the music to truly flourish. We have songs here that are only concerned with being good songs, without asking every 10 seconds "Am I psychedelic enough?". And the instrumentals and noisy freak-outs all have a sense of purpose and direction. In short, the band doesn't have to prove anything; after all, if they were asked to do this soundtrack, it's because they already proved their worth, right? So, don't be put off by the "soundtrack" stigma. In fact, get this before [a]A Saucerful of Secrets[/a] if you are willing to.</p>

<p>Not don't go thinking that this is a "hidden masterpiece" or something like that. It's not a "masterpiece": side 2, in particular, gets kind of tiresome and aimless, and the highlights of the record can't be compared to the highlights of the band's overall career. But as far as their early career goes, this album is a revelation, and an important key in unlocking some of the band's secrets. The "avant-garde" bits have quite a lot of worth. The only place in which they let their sounds drag on and on is [s]Quicksilver[/s], which is not actively bad or anything, but it doesn't achieve much in all its seven minutes of "sonic exploration" &mdash; it tries to be ominous and quiet, but doesn't really succeed. There's also the band playing the blues ([s]More Blues[/s]), a sort of stupid gag with Waters and Gilmour playing some quite cool Spanish guitar and Gilmour impersonating an unfunny stereotype ([s]A Spanish Piece[/s] &mdash; ain't it good how these titles are self-descriptive?), the whole band playing bongos and congas in a faux-African setting ([s]Party Sequence[/s]) and a <em>really cool</em> jazzy exchange between Nick Mason (man, listen to those drums! The guy could really play!) and Rick Wright. This kind of variety would be completly unlikely in other places, isn't it? Besides that, where else could we hear Pink Floyd doing <em>heavy metal</em>? [s]The Nile Song[/s] became something of a minor classic, with distorted guitars, powerhouse drums aplenty and Gilmour shouting his lungs off. But the most memorable thing is the trick of raising the song a full tone at the end of every verse. [s]Ibiza Bar[/s] doesn't have the same luck, unfortunately, even though it has a nice quiet section at every verse. Both songs are pretty cool, indeed.</p>

<p>The [s]Main Theme[/s] is also a minor highlight, boasting a cool, jazzy groove and a spaced out atmosphere that's convincing and relaxed. I also love that Farfisa organ sound that Wright produces. This is a fine indication that the band was getting mature, and already had a much clearer idea of what they wanted to do. But what about the "non-avant-garde" tunes? Well, you probably wouldn't guess, but they more <em>folk</em> than anything else, and you don't need to get past the opening track to hear that: [s]Cirrus Minor[/s] is led only by Roger Waters on voice and guitar, with Wright adding some Farfisa organ for good measure. The melody is as simple as you can get, but it's so convincing and beautiful it's almost scary! I mean, where did they pull <em>that</em> off? Of course, being purely folk is not good enough: they complete it with a gorgeous coda led almost entirely by Wright on the organ, with some tape sounds and effects completing the scene. It's a tremendously good song. Likewise is [s]Cymbaline[/s], a more rock based ballad with a slightly ominous atmosphere and a melody to kill for, which also boasts a brilliantly atmospheric coda. [s]Green Is the Colour[/s] and [s]Crying Song[/s] are shorter and cuter; I've always been a great fan of the earlier, which combines simplicity and beauty in a way that the grating tin whistle (played by Nick Mason's wife) couldn't spoil even if it tried to, and the latter is surprisingly great with its very hushed mood.</p>

<p>I am sure that, if this material were worked into a more cohesive and coerent work and freed of the "soundtrack" label, it would have easily become a minor classic. I'm tempted to give this album a bigger rating than I gave to [a]A Saucerful of Secrets[/a], and I can say that this album is sort of in between a 10 and an 11. I just don't give it an 11 because of the overall lack of cohesion and some unconvincing tracks. But the uninitiated should try this out eventually.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Green is the [l]Comment[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album id="ummagumma">
      <title>Ummagumma</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Careful with That Axe, Eugene[/s], [s]Grantchester Meadows[/s], [s]Sysyphus[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc title="Live album">
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Astronomy Domine</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Careful with That Axe, Eugene</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Set the Controls for the Heart of the Sun</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>A Saucerful of Secrets</title></track>
        </disc>
        <disc title="Studio album">
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Sysyphus, part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Sysyphus, part 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Sysyphus, part 3</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Sysyphus, part 4</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Grantchester Meadows</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Several Species of Small Furry Animals Gathered Together in a Cave and Grooving with a Pict</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>The Narrow Way, part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>The Narrow Way, part 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>The Narrow Way, part 3</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>The Grand Vizier's Garden Party: Entrance</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>The Grand Vizier's Garden Party: Entertainment</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>The Grand Vizier's Garden Party: Exit</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>There's no more appropriate way for me to call this album than "Crossroads". The nature and the origin of the album are both very confused, and it sounds like the band really didn't know what they wanted to do next. This was originally meant to be a live album, featuring the staples of their most psychedelic period, but then they had the idea of splitting the second LP in four parts, with each member recording a solo piece. So, this album is half live-psychedelic, half avant-garde-freak-out. And what I gotta say is that, at this point in their career, the band didn't quite have the chops to make a masterpiece out of <em>that</em>.</p>

<p>The four tracks on disc one were collected from two live performances, and as you can see, the only "new" title is [s]Careful with That Axe, Eugene[/s], which is excellent in every aspect. it doesn't waste a single second of its running length, and develops steadily through gentle variations of intensity and mood. The playing is extraordinarily simple: Waters's bass lines are minimal, while Mason and Wright sprinkle their drum+organ combo in the right doses and Waters builds some additional tension with floating, wordless falsettos. But that's only until the sudden turnaround halfway through, when all the built tension erupts with Gilmour unleasing his guitar and Waters producing an unbelievable, gut-wrenching shriek. <em>This</em> is how you do a psychedelic instrumental, dammit! No chord changes are necessary, no freaky sound effects are needed &mdash; just an extraordinarily tight bandwork and a clever song construction. The album is worth having for this track alone, and you may be sure that's saying quite a lot.</p>

<p>As for the other three, I'll be very honest: only [s]Set the Controls for the Heart of the Sun[/s] happens to improve on the album version. But maybe that's just because I never liked much the "meditation" atmosphere of it, and this noisier, more chaotic and dynamic version actually develops something worthwhile. [s]Astronomy Domine[/s] happens to sound <em>way</em> too meek and tame for my tastes, as if they mercilessly stripped the song of everything that made it so good in the first place. The only added a passage with Wright playing the organ nearly "a capella", which is noteworthy, but being surrounded with such a flaccid performance, its effect is pretty much lost. On the other hand, [s]A Saucerful of Secret[/s] fails for being too over-the-top. Mason does an excellent job in keeping up with that drum loop, and I think that's the best thing about the track. The ending replaces the heavenly vocal harmonies (which, I guess, they had no way of reproducing live) with a massive climax, leaving poor David Gilmour to carry the vocals all on his own. He definitely pulls off a valiant effort, but man, do I wish they had kept it entirely instrumental.</p>

<p>The studio record is, as you must have expected, a complete mess, a mixed bag of hit-and-miss material. But it's a lot, lot more interesting than the first record, and it's the only place in which you'll hear such avant-garde and unrestrained material from the band. Listening to this, it becomes pretty clear that only Wright and Waters were fully prepared to take on this project. Mason had to ask for the help of avant-garde musician Ron Geesin to put together the flute intro and outro of [s]The Grand Vizier's Garden Party[/s], played by Mason's wife, Lindy. The main part is, as should be expected, mostly drum and percussion dominated, though he spends much of it with tape experiments, and only in the few final minute he does play a drum solo. Gilmour's piece, [s]The Narrow Way[/s], sounds far more accomplished, even though its also mostly a "hodge-podge" of stuff; but he really puts his guitars to work on those pieces, creating an accoustic joyful little thing on part 1, a very eerie and menacing overdriven guitar riff on part 2, and finally delivering a song with vocals and lyrics on part 3, which is surprisingly good and well performed, and pretty much sets the standard for other Pink Floyd songs that would come along. Even though it does feature some tape manipulation and effects, Gilmour's work is the most straightforward in the album.</p>

<p>Wright's work, on the other hand, is by far the most avantgarde. [s]Sysyphus[/s] is completely unabashed and unmodest, completely going for something that is more "neo-classical" than "rock" at all. Wright uses timpani, percussion and Mellotrons to create a pseudo-orchestral sound in the thunderous opening theme, which moves on to a solo piano piece. At first you may think that you've got the hang of it, with pretty piano chords and contemplative semi-melodies and so on, but that only lasts for a few minutes, and shortly the whole atmosphere is wrecked mercilessly. And the following part only makes things more radical, with Wright manipulating the piano strings directly and throwing in all kinds of percussion effects and tape manipulations. There are really no moderation here: he is truly out to make the most upsetting and disturbing sound with whatever tools he had available to him. Yet, the composition as a whole is beautifully framed and complete: the second half of the composition ties it all together with a lengthy, contemplative passage on a Mellotron, which stumbled into a massive and definitive grand finale. What a trip, man! Now you see how it is when the musician knows <em>exactly</em> what he is doing.</p>

<p>Waters's contributions are, by far, the oddest. [s]Grantchester Meadows[/s] may seem ominous with its length, but it's actually a folk tune played entirely on acoustic guitar. It's even more straightforward than [s]Cirrus Minor[/s], and the only bit of "experimentation" is the addition of sounds of animals and other "ambience" effects. The second track, however, is a major experiment with tape manipulation, featuring mainly vocal sounds played on high speeds, body slapping, tapping on the microphone and so on, all with the objective of creating <em>exactly</em> what the title of the track describes. And it works! I doube that Waters intended it as a "serious art statement", as it seems extremely facetious, especially when he suddenly goes on a long rant at the end with an exaggerated Scottish accent. It's a piece of humour, and a great one. In this way, you can argue that only Waters truly understood the meaning of the album. But then again, maybe the band members were right when they said there was just no meaning at all: is a meaning even necessary? I don't think so. Fact is, the album is horribly inconsistent, but it is an extremely unique item in the band's catalogue. You <em>have</em> to listen to it, if only to say that you did listen.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Careful with That [l]Comment[/l], Eugene[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album id="mother">
      <title>Atom Heart Mother</title>
      <year>1970</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Summer '68[/s], [s]If[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Atom Heart Mother</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>If</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Summer '68</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Fat Old Sun</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Alan's Psychedelic Breakfast</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Boy, it sure can be difficult listening to a band that has no idea of what they want to do. But then again, what fault do they have? Even though the only <em>real</em> masterpiece they had released so far was their debut album &mdash; which was, in turn, the brainchild of Syd Barrett, who was long gone &mdash; they were praised to death by basically everyone, their live performances were highly successful, and, in short, they were BIG. But they just didn't know how to translate that BIGness to an LP. In other words, they had no idea how they were supposed to match people's expectations. This album was clearly an attempt, though. They were <em>trying</em>.</p>

<p>The title track is 24 minutes long and is entirely instrumental. Its main portion was based on a sequence of chords Gilmour came up, and it was mostly a matter of sticking pieces together until they didn't fall off, and recording it as best as they could. But it still needed that avant-garde boost, so they passed the tapes to Ron Geesin, who proceeded to write and record an elaborate orchestral arrangement with plenty of brass and choir, while the band was out touring. When they were back, they weren't <em>quite</em> satisfied with the recording as it was (there were several synchronization problem between the band and the orchestra, result of Geesing having to record on top of an already recorded tape) and wanted to do it all over again, but the EMI execs gave them the red light. So, they put out what they had, the album was largely well received, and the band went on having extremely mixed feelings about it. Waters repeatedly said he hated the track, while the others were warmer towards it. But fact is, the song remained a staple of their live shows for quite a few years.</p>

<p>Basically, the best thing about the song is its scope and its confidence. Well, I don't know, it <em>does</em> sound like the band knows what they're doing all the way through; but maybe that is largely the merit of Ron Geesin, who was able to use his orchestrations to fill in the blanks left deliberately by the band on the recording. You don't hear a band on the top of their game, but you hear a geniune <em>effort</em> to come up with a piece that could stand on its own two feet. And, well, it goes on for 24 minutes, and never does it falter. It's not a masterpiece, by no means, but taken as a whole, it's far superior to the "sum of the parts" of the last albums. Another thing that pleases is that the band doesn't force anything: much of the song is devoted to a very straightforward, slightly mournful ballad (Gilmour's theme), which is complemented by some very melodic additions by Waters, Wright and Co. It never pushes its "avant-gardeness" down the listener's throat, and when it eventually switches gears and goes into elongated band jams, abstract "scat-singing" by the choir, and even a hellish collage of tape effects and whatnot, the transitions happen naturally, and always with a sense of direction. It's not an inconsequent hackjob at all: it's a fairly mature piece. I don't think that rerecording the track would have turned it into a full masterpiece, really: the problems with the track are mostly technical, though it's quite probable they would have changed a lot of things if they had had the chance. But [s]Atom Heart Mother[/s] is something to be happy with. I'm happy with it. Waters isn't, but he is not the reviewer here, right?</p>

<p>But then, I did say that the band didn't know what they were doing. That is still true: [s]Atom Heart Mother[/s] grew as a sort of organic thing, with litttle or no foresight. And the second side of the album is even worse in this aspect: we have three "solo" songs from the three songwriters in the band (they are all full band performances, but each composer wrote on his own), and a collaborative 13-minute piece called [s]Alan's Psychedelic Breakfast[/s], which is the kind of track that sounds awesome on paper but, on tape, leaves a little to be desired. The idea was to create a "musical breakfast", with pieces of music interwoven with sounds of roadie Alan Styles making and eating breakfast, and it probably was really fun to perform life and such. But on record, it sounds merely like three pieces of pleasant, folk-tinged acoustic instrumental music joined together with assorted kitchen sounds. The "breakfast" is not truly integrated with the music or vice versa, and it ends up sounding a little lazy, a lacklustre execution for a pretty good idea. But the music is pretty, all three segments, especially the last one; and it's sort of funny hearing Alan muttering randomly among all the different noises.</p>

<p>Now, the three songs are a major winning streak. Waters's [s]If[/s] and Gilmour's [s]Far Old Sun[/s] are very understated and mellow &mdash; particularly [s]If[/s], which is pretty much on the "depressing" side of the scale, gorgeously written and played <em>just</em> with the right amount of feeling and tenderness; really, the band is on an all time high here &mdash; while [s]Fat Old Sun[/s] is more uplifting, and already shows a big tendency of David Gilmour of closing his songs with very lengthy guitar solos. But the song is really good, and the soloing doesn't get to the point of being annoying, though it does have that traditional Gilmour thing of <em>never really taking off</em>. You know, a solo must somehow grab your full attention and keep you on the edge of your seat, otherwise it's not soloing, but just <em>noodling</em>, ya know. It's unfair to say that Gilmour is noodling here, but he just seems content with "extracting pretty sounds" without delivering a truly massive payload. Oh, what the hell. Either way, Wright's [s]Summer '68[/s] is easily, <em>easily</em> the best thing in the record, a highlight to end all highlights. It is a true wonder of song construction and arrangement, moving from part to part with grace and elegance, with surprising twists of arrangement (the big entrance of the full brass band halfway through are certain to get my hairs standing on end), and connecting it all together with beautiful melodymaking. This is easily Floyd's best song in the post-Barrett-pre-[a]Meddle[/a] period, full stop. And you know what's interesting? Even though the song doesn't sound very "psychedelic" at all, it was used, with great effect, in a pretty "psychedelic" advertising montage which led to a Brazilian TV news program in the early 70's, and you can see it <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DGyejhNu8Ac">here</a>. Pretty amazing.</p>

<p>As for the record, just don't be misled by the hype around it. The album cover is an extremely iconic classic, and overall the name "Atom Heart Mother" always raises a few ears when it's mentioned; but that is more because this album <em>was</em> a breakthrough for the band. Or, more properly, this album broke the doors open, and they would truly move on through on the next record. It is a seminal release, but not an outstanding classic. It deserves praise, it's a must hear for any Floyd fan, and if you're getting interested in the band, you'll have to get it eventually. Just don't expect a masterpiece and you'll be alright.]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>"... and if I were a [l]commenter[/l], I'd talk with you more often than I do..."[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album id="meddle">
      <title>Meddle</title>
      <year>1971</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Echoes[/s], [s]One of These Days[/s], [s]Fearless[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>One of These Days</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>A Pillow of Winds</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Fearless</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Saint Tropez</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Seamus</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Echoes</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>At least, we reach the album that showed to the world just exactly <em>what</em> these four guys were up to all the time. This is the first time we hear the band truly <em>joining forces</em> to produce a coherent and consistent album, you know: instead of staggering to fill up the sides of the record with material, it seems like the band clearly wanted to push the boundaries and stretch their abilities to their limit. And the effort pays off, and how!</p>

<p>For one, this album nails down the unique, inimitable "sound" of Pink Floyd, watery, fluid, spacey and profoundly organic. And what better place to check it out than in the 23-minute-long tour de force [s]Echoes[/s], which occupies the entire second side? You may be led to think this is [s]Atom Heart Mother II[/s], but that couldn't be further from the truth. This time around, the band relied entirely on their own composition, arrangement and production skills, and worked hard to combine ideas and form a very large, complete whole that works on its own. It is well documented that the whole composition sparked out of a single, very high piano note (a B6, if I'm not mistaken), which was sent through a rotating speaker (the Leslie, which is actually <em>not</em> a "rotating speaker" &mdash; only the horns inside the speaker actually rotate), and the result is the sound that opens the track. But from that point on, the song develops marvellously, with vocals shared by Wright and Gilmour, and a full, beautiful sound aided by Wright's Farfisa organ and a memorable "descending" guitar riff that Waters claimed were plagiarised on Andrew Lloyd Webber's theme from <em>The Phantom of the Opera</em>. The instrumental segues that make up the inner portion of the song are all marvellously performed and integrated with the rest of the material, including the polarising "noise-making" part in the middle. I'll probably sound corny saying this, but this is the perfect music for you to "lose yourself" into. It is a complete journey, and once you manage to dig into its core, you'll never want to leave. It's extremely rewarding.</p>

<p>Side A, however, does not end up as a letdown; though it was a wise idea to leave [s]Echoes[/s] on side B, as it is pretty much impossible to follow up that track with <em>anything</em>. Besides, [s]One of These Days[/s] is a brilliant album opener, and by far the most vicious and ominous thing they band recorded to this point. Well, maybe only second to [s]Careful with That Axe, Eugene[/s]; but [s]One of These Days[/s] packs a much bigger punch in a much more condensed form, and it's carried mostly by Waters and Gilmour playing a one-note bass riff simultaneously, ran through an echo effect. The result must be heard to be believed, and to top it off, the band spices it with Wright's organ effects, backwards percussion hits and Gilmour's heavy guitar chords. Eventually, the whole band crashes in for a grand finale with Gilmour putting his soloing skills to maximum effect. But this is the only truly all-out rockin' track on the album, but with a song <em>this</em> good, it's silly to ask for more. Everywhere else you get more of that classic watery sound, and the only difference between side A and side B, in terms of texture, is a much smaller reliance on Wright's keyboards: while on [s]Echoes[/s] we have loads of Farfisa organ, Hammond organ, piano and whatever else, the four songs are far more guitar based, and both Waters and Gilmour make their contributions. [s]A Pillow of Winds[/s] features a kind of gorgeousness not found anywhere else in the band's catalogue so far. Really! Give it a listen and see if you can find anything similar. The mixture of gently picking acoustic guitars and Gilmour's slide is a gift from Heaven, and even the vocal melody is pretty much an accessory. Towards the end the band adds a faint tinge of organ and Mason's hi-hat, just for extra spice, and the effect is tremendous. Meanwhile, [s]Fearless[/s] is a wonderful, robust, memorable song, featuring a vocal melody and a repeated ascending guitar riff to kill for. Interestingly, Gilmour's singing voice are used to great effect on both songs, with its hushed, mellow quality. [s]Fearless[/s] also displays the band's increasing mastery of arrangements, switching beautifully between the jangly and rhythmic verses and the gently floating choruses.</p>

<p>The side is closed with two far less dense and more relaxed songs, which are surprisingly maligned by a portion of fans. Okay, so [s]Seamus[/s] is indeed entirely based on a pretty grating gimmick: it's a short piece of generic blues in which Gilmour "duets" with the eponymous dog, which howls his way through the entire track. But it is funny! And it is cute! Okay, so a dog's howl isn't exactly the most pleasant of sounds, but the band intended to do a little, unpretentious musical joke, and they succeeded. [s]Saint Tropez[/s], on the other hand, doesn't have anything grating or annoying at all: just Waters pulling off an enjoyable, catchy little jazzy tune with some soloing on slide guitar and on piano. Just that. And the band pulls it off surprisingly well. The tunes are pretty much at odds with the rest of the material, but they arrive as a breather of fresh air before the magnum opus on side B. In my book, that's a smart, unexpected move, and it improves the album overall. I don't share the view that the album would be better off without those tracks, and unless anyone can prove they could have written another stupendous track to replace them, I stand by my opinion. It's not that I consider this album <em>perfect</em>, but it is a prodigious work, and we can finally hear Pink Floyd on full flight here. Or, to be more precise, <em>almost</em>. But let's go by parts, shall we?</p>]]></review>
      <rating>14</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[a][l]Meddle[/l][/a]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album id="clouds">
      <title>Obscured by Clouds</title>
      <year>1972</year>
      <highpoints>[s]Wots... uh, the Deal?[/s], [s]Free Four[/s]</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Obscured by Clouds</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>When You're In</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Burning Bridges</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>The Gold It's in the...</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Wots... uh, the Deal?</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Mudmen</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Childhood's End</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Free Four</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade><title>Stay</title></track>
          <track><grade>2</grade><title>Absolutely Curtains</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>In 1972, the band took a break from the sessions of their next album to record the soundtrack for the French film <em>La Val&eacute;e</em>, directed by Barbet Schroeder (same director of <em>More</em>). Oddly enough, this album doesn't sound at all like a sountrack on first listen, as most of the album consists of short, friendly tunes, and most of them with vocals. There are no spaced out sonic explorations, no short interlinking pieces, no unexplainable gags, and the only truly soundtrackish piece is the closing track (which is kinda lame, truth be told). In short, the only thing that hints that this is not a "regular" Pink Floyd album is its rather unpolished nature, due to the extremely tight deadline the band had when recording the music.</p>

<p>There are two notable things about this record. The first is the use of synthesizers, which was new to the band. They employ a VCS3 analogue synth, which would be a key piece of their next album. The second thing is that some of these tracks are <em>really</em> good. And, this being a soundtrack, the band was free to poke at some places they would usually not poke at; for example, drivin' hard rock, which Gilmour dabbles with on [s]The Gold It's in the...[/s], which is surprisingly fun and engaging. Gilmour's guitar is really good here, and about half of it is a guitar solo that really keeps up the level of fun. On the other end of the spectrum is [s]Childhood's End[/s], which is pretty bitter and angry, and boasts a funkish, chopped rhythm that also represents a step towards the band's near future. And what's with that atmospheric, synth-laden intro?  Whoa! Not even [a]Meddle[/a] was so bold in integrating pop tunes with experimentation such as this! Okay, [s]Fearless[/s] had the football chant and all, but that was something else. Anyway, in case you haven't listened to [a]Dark Side of the Moon[/a] yet, give this song a listen on YouTube or something before you move on. Keep that song in mind.</p>

<p>Waters's contribution is just as surprising as his folky digressions: [s]Free Four[/s] tackles the subject of war and death in an extremely bitter, sorrowful tone (which would become very, very typical for him), but on top of a jangly and joyful music. The way the sung verses lead into a bumpy, playful "baaam!" synth chord, as well as the harder-edged instrumental passages, only increase the fun factor of the song. This kind of smart, twisted sense of humour would not be common at all in the next records. As for the other songs, they are all ballads. Gilmour's [s]Wots... uh, the Deal?[/s] is particularly beautiful, with a gentle, but aching delivery and a measured, exquisite performance by the whole band. And once again Gilmour pulls out his slide guitar for great effect. [s]Burning Bridges[/s] is also beautiful, maybe a bit too draggy for its own sake, but featuring a really beautiful keyboard pattern on Wright's Hammond organ. Only Wright's collaboration with Waters, [s]Stay[/s], sounds way too generic and bland to cause an impression, in spite of the dramatic and catchy chorus. Sorry, Rick.</p>

<p>But there are instrumentals in the album, too, and the only one that's really hard on the ears is the aforementioned album closer [s]Absolutely Curtains[/s], which consists largely of Wright making ambience on his keyboards and Mason creating dynamics on timpani and cymbals. It drags on for too long and too aimlessly; I think Wright's playing suffers when there's no real musical theme being delivered, and this would become very, very clear on some of his later pieces (in fact, if you've heard his solo piano piece written for Michelangelo Antonioni's infamous film <em>Zabriskie Point</em>, entitled [s]The Violent Sequence[/s], you probably know what I mean). Many people complain about the elongated coda of the track, featuring an aboryginal chant, but I actually think that's the best part of the song. Maybe the voices will sound too foreign to you, but hey! maybe it's time for you to look at some things beyond your national frontiers, right?</p>

<p>The pair of opening tracks actually form a suite, and it sounds far groovier, spaced-out and psychedelic than anything the band recorded since, um, since [a]More[/a]! The title track has some synth drones and a mechanical, dull drum loop serving as a foundation for a cool, slightly bluesy guitar solo by Gilmour, and on [s]When You're In[/s], the whole band crashes in with a riff based on power chords. Really good stuff! Definitely worth checking out. To end the namedrops, [s]Mudmen[/s] is an unbelievably slow, morose ballad extending on the main theme of [s]Burning Bridges[/s]. But it sounds <em>really</em> beautiful, and the slowness is actually an asset here: the dramatic chord changes and the huge climaxes on the choruses work extremely well. It's a great piece. So, if you like this band, do yourself a favour and give this album a spin once in a while. It may not be [a]Meddle[/a], and not even a very adequate record for converting the unfaithful and making the join the ranks of Floyd followers, but in all aspects, this is the same Pink Floyd we've grown to love and respect. Yes, with a few tracks and a slightly rough-around-the-edges feel. But if you've already got [a]A Saucerful of Secrets[/a], there's no reason to neglect this one.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>1</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Wots... uh, the [l]Deal[/l]?[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album id="moon">
      <title>Dark Side of the Moon</title>
      <year>1973</year>
      <highpoints>All of them!</highpoints>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Speak to Me</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Breathe</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>On the Run</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Time</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>The Great Gig in the Sky</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Money</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Us and Them</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade><title>Any Colour You Like</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Brain Damage</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade><title>Eclipse</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>It may not be very evident in my reviews, but I don't like making assumptions about any of my readers (yes, <em>both</em> of you!). So, if you have never heard a single minute off this album, worry not: this review is for you.</p>

<p>If you look at the history of Floyd's albums so far, you'see that nearly all of them came off as a result of a pretty difficult process. Even [a]Meddle[/a] had to go through a fair bit of staggering before being completed. For their next release, they decided to let the musical ideas mature a lot more before committing them to tape, and this way, a suite of songs was formed and performed in nearly all of their live performances. That suite eventually became this album, and that explains why the album sounds so coherent and confident, to the point of making [a]Meddle[/a] sound almost like a mere rehearsal. Not only <em>all</em> songs here are built on very deep and strong foundations, but the album incorporates many studio techniques in quite novel ways, with really innovative results. This merit belongs not solely to the band, but also to engineer Alan Parsons, and it's absolutely necessary to do that justice. Parsons was responsible by several solutions and effects employed on the album. But that brings up another mistake many people make: the sound effects, elaborate recordings of ringing clocks, tape collages and excerpts of people giving interviews are <em>not</em> what make this album so distinctive. The musical material here is supreme, and taken as a whole, easily beats all their previous records. It's not terribly productive to talk about isolated songs in here: just recall how [s]Echoes[/s] presented 23 minutes of glory, extend that to 40 minutes, and you get this album. Essentially.</p>

<p>Now, the band was not new to including all kinds of sounds and recording in their albums, as well as using studio effects and tricks to enhance their music (remember the echo unit on [s]One of These Days[/s], the piano-on-a-Leslie of [s]Echoes[/s], the synthesizer soundscape of [s]Childhood's End[/s], etc.). But in this album, all that accumulated skill and experience favour the entire album, not just a few select tracks. The VCS3 synthesizer returns to play some key roles, the stereo-ping-pong echoes are very present, and the sound effects are very intelligently integrated in the songs. It's important to mention that this, unlike the previous records, is a concept album. Waters wrote all lyrics, and they are all interlinked to form a bigger statement; so instead of abstract sonic landscapes and football chants, you have a room full of deafening ringing clocks to represent the ruthlessness of passing time, a dance of cash registers and falling coins making a rhythm, voices of people answering questions related to fighting, death and insanity, and so on and on. If you're pretentious enough, you can say this album is more of a "tone poem" than a mere rock album, and I won't argue against you. This is not a band toying around with ideas or struggling to make something work: this is a band with a complete idea of what they want and a complete idea of <em>how to get there</em>.</p>

<p>With this fairly odd construction, though, it's fairly easy for people to dismiss the album as a collection of weak, pale songs tied together with novelty noisemaking; and knowing how this is one of the best selling albums <em>of all time</em>, such backlash is only to be expected.
]]></review>
    </album>
  </artist>
</updateList>
<!--
<h2 id="moon" class="best">Dark Side Of The Moon (1973)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <em>The whole thing.</em>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li><span class="good">Speak To Me / Breathe ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">On The Run ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Time / Breathe (reprise) ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">The Great Gig In The Sky ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Money ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Us And Them ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Any Colour You Like ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Brain Damage ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Eclipse ++</span></li>
</ol>

<p>In case you're not aware already, you should get prepared for <em>a lot</em> of raving and ranting ahead. See, it's not at all because the historical importance of the album, or because how long it has been in the charts, or because how many people love the album to death, or whatever. The thing between me and this album is <em>strictly personal</em>, because it has hit my nerves in very special ways right since the first time I heard it. No, wait... I'm not sure about the <em>first</em> time, but there was a certain moment that I realsed this album was just something different. Not as a unique, completely unusual item that sounded like nothing else in the world. It was the way it affected me, you know. And from then on, it was just a matter of listening to it over and over and being immersed on that amazing world of sound.</p>

<p>And with that bit of personal rambling, I just described exactly what's the big deal about this album: "world of sound". With <strong>Meddle</strong>, Pink Floyd more or less found out their interest in creating sonic landscapes, or whatever you call it. And that style of music making makes much of the basis for this record. The band finally found just the <em>perfect</em> combination between the sounds of their instruments to create an ensemble that's just... well, I can't think of any word other than "otherworldly". Nick Mason now sticks to that slow, gentle tapping style that makes the "typical" Floyd rhythm from now on, and over that, Rick Wright and David Gilmour lay their smooth, fluid duetting. I tell you it's pure bliss to hear the soft electric piano chords on one channel, and the rhythm guitar on the other, soundng like one, solid body. That, to me, is a triumph. Also, they discovered interesting uses for the VCS3 synthesizer, which almost all of them play here. Combined with the usual keyboards, Farfisa organs and whatever else, the sonic pallete the band assembled here is rich and impressive. It also helps that the songs weren't all put out in one batch, but were already being perfected in live shows from that time. So, the songwriting <em>and</em> the performances help to make the album very consistent.</p>

<p>But anyway, there are mainly two things that make this album transcend any barrier that had been blocking Pink Floyd albums from absolute superstardom. First of them is the lyrics, which are all written by Roger Waters. Once and for all, he took the responsibility for himself, which allowed the band to make their first, full-fledged concept album, and eventually one of the greatest, most successful concept albums in history. For one, he doesn't talk about war, aside from a side comment on 'Us And Them'. The main focus here is in all sorts of ugly things that can potentially turn a man insane - probably inspired by the destiny of his friend, Syd Barrett. As you can see, it's not a very focused concept, and the album touches <em>various</em> topics surrounding that theme - some of them are obvious judging by the song title. The real "concept" here, though, is how these topics and songs are linked to each other, and make a bigger sense when taken as a whole. Taken alone, Waters's lyrics don't necessarily display "genius", and at certain points even sound pretty clich&eacute;d and, dare I say it, silly. But I won't be the dorky dude to point out that "The lunatic is in my head" could have been written by a five year old, and I'll say that it's the sense of meaning that makes this album look so ahead of the previous Pink Floyd albums. One thing is to have a "masterpiece about nothing" (<strong>Meddle</strong>), and another entirely different thing is to have a masterpiece with an actual meaning. <em>And</em> this album would be mainly a launchpad for Roger to start investing on his talent as a lyricist. Which is good.</p>

<p>The big advantage is that the lyrics aren't central to the album. They aren't even central to the concept. The album also delivers its messages with music, sound effects, speeches, and other kinds of sonic tricks. And that's what I mean with the album being a world of sound: you might listen to the album as a collection of simple, half-baked songs with a layer of "sounds" on top, but that's not how <em>I</em> take it. This album is a masterpiece in creating a picture with sounds, to the point where there isn't any kind of strict separation between what is "music" and what is just "sound". Sound becomes music, and music itself is reduced to a simple combination of sounds. The way the songs are constructed and combined makes me even hesitate in speaking in terms of "songs". The album is a solid piece, and I can only view it as such, really. And through the entire album, the band's playing and the sound effects give an incredible dimension and deepness to the music. It's really like diving headfirst into a bottomless ocean of sound. I believe Alan Parson's work as sound engineer was a crucial element in making this album work so well, but the band deserves a lot of credit for their clever uses of sound, innovative techniques, and the clever meth od of interviewing people - that is, placing them before a microphone in a darkened room and making questions simply showing flashcards. Those interviews granted them with memorable bits of speech, like the "I've been mad for fucking years" which opens the album, the bit about death on 'The Great Gig In The Sky', the superimposed lines about getting in a fight and being "in the right" at the end of 'Money' ("I don't know, I was very drunk at the time"), classic lines like "Live for today, gone tomorrow, that's me" and "There's no dark side of the moon, really; matter of fact it's all dark", and the glorious laughter that pops up in several places through the album. Everything is part of the experience, you know; dismiss any of that as silly gimmickry, and the album's not for you.</p>

<p>And anyway, how you're supposed to think of track like 'On The Run' as one big piece of gimmickry and be expected to enjoy the rest of the album? Of course you can just not like it, but I <em>do</em> think it's a cool, hypnotic piece, with all those different sounds, underpinned by the constant, unforgettable synth loop, forming a haze inside my brain.It's not quite the feeling of being <em>mad</em>, but very close to those moments of near-paranoia when you can't think straight not even for a split second. They do that very well, you know, eventually culminating with the crashing airplane. I'm surprised that I never heard about anyone using that song as an allegory of the World Trade Center incident. I think that's a pretty obvious "stupid thing to say", but I never heard it. Instead, I heard about how Bloodrock's 'D.O.A.' was "the ultimate 9/11 song". HUH?! What are those people? <em>Stupid</em>? Oh, dear. Anyway, if you think I'm being extremelly inadequate in bringing this topic here, you're right, and I'm doing this intentionally. After all, if people already took their time to do some "United 93" movie and cash in on the event, why can't <em>I</em> be obnoxious too? They didn't even catch Osama yet! MORONS! You can see <em>my house</em> on Google Earth, and they didn't find the guy yet? Man.</p>

<p>Either way, 'On The Run' is the only track in which the sound effects might definitely get in the way of the music, aside from the opening collage of sounds ('Speak To Me') which makes an introductory crescendo that works as a nice warning of what's about to come - it's also pretty freaky to realise how scary Clare Torry's singing sounds when taken out of context. More on that later. And then, you have all the, ahem, songs that more-or-less make the bulk of the album. Whatever I've said about the album working as a whole, without the compositions, this album would be at best an "experimental" Frank Zappa wannabe pseudo intellectual's delight. <em>With</em> the compositions, it's Floyd's defining moment. <strong>Obscured By Clouds</strong> showed the band's potential as songwriters, and <strong>Dark Side Of The Moon</strong> puts that potential to good use. As a result, you have classics like 'Time', which is just plainly gorgeous, switching from more agressive verses with David's singing into quieter, pleasant choruses with Rick's soft singing and beautiful backing vocals. I admit that David's guitar solo's here is, quite frankly, a pain. Yeah, it gets pretty melodic when he hits the chorus, but otherwise, it just meanders on and on with that "rocking" distorted sound at snail pace. The doubletracking effect is cool, but other than that? Pfah. Fortunately, I can just get lost in the gorgeous sound of it. And anyway, there's always the unforgettable intro to counter it all. Say whatever you wish, but I'm a <em>sucker</em> for that intro, with the clock effect, the deep, loud chords and Nick Mason's calculated playing on the rototoms (that is, toms that you can tune by rotating the top). It's brilliant, it's clever, <em>and</em> it features the disturbing, nearly-obnoxious symphony of ringing clocks at the beginning.</p>

<p>Maybe unsurprisingly, Rick Wright contributes two stunning compositions. The first of them is 'The Great Gig In The Sky', an entirely instrumental interpretation of death which doesn't need any sung words whatsoever. Rick's piano, the occasional slide guitar and bass is absolutely sufficient - that is, until it takes off into an intense, dramatic middle section with Clare Torry's frenzied singing topping it off. I fail trying to find words to describe it. Suffice to say, it's one of my favourite tracks on the album. There's an interesting story, taken from a Totally Reliable Source&trade;, telling that Clare felt she really went over-the-top in one of the takes, burst into the recording booth apologising for such a terrible take. That take is the one they used in the album. A confirmed story is that she went through a court battle to get credits for the song - which <em>is</em> fully deserved, and did happen in the latter releases of the album. Think of it: the song wouldn't be half of what it is without her. His second contribution is 'Us And Them', which is the definitive culmination of his watery sound. It's all about that interesting chord progression he plays on the organ, David's perfect guitar arpeggios and his short, echoey vocal deliveries, which eventually erupt into loud, intense choruses. The lyrics are Waters', of course. Dick Parry also contributes a fine, fine pair of saxophone solos here.</p>

<p>Of course, I can't stay without mentioning 'Money', which features the band's best bass riff ever, and the awesome use of sound effects as perfectly synchronised percussion instruments. Mason's snappy drumming and the jazzy, unexpected rhythm makes the song pretty unique in their repertoire, and the way David's guitar and Rick's electric piano play ping-pong on the speakers is really entertaining. The instrumental break features a great band performance and Dick Parry's sax, but unfortunately, there's another annoying, uninspired guitar solo in it. I mean, what's the possible excuse for playing the same lick <em>three times</em> in a single solo? Oh, come on. Other than that, the song is brilliant - and like I said, the band's performance saves it, as do all the other great elements in it. There's also Roger's 'Brain Damage', which retains a bit of his folky style, in special in the verses, and leads into the glorious, climatic ending of 'Eclipse' - which U2 ripped-off for 'Walk On', *nudge nudge*. There are also other things that I didn't mention, like 'Breathe', that forms the album's main recurring theme, and the spaced-out instrumental 'Any Colour You Like', with a title borrowed from the old Ford advert: "You can have any car you like in any colour you like, as long as it's Model T and it's black." But it's more important to have a grasp on what the album represents, and what it stands for, than getting down into every detail. After all, you can always read other articles and texts about it, and, you know, you can always LISTEN to it, in case you haven't already. Either way, it's not a question of liking Pink Floyd or not; this is a record you <em>must</em> know, and if you want to be drastic, it's a record you must own. Want it or not. It is <em>that</em> relevant, you know, and that's something you'll have to accept. You can still feel the effects of this album even today, and you can still see it being worshipped everywhere by all sorts of people. The record breaks barries of time, space, technology... heck, even culture. Or do you think Johnny Rotten <em>really</em> hated the band?</p>

<p>Okay, go ahead and call me a lunatic, or a fanatic, or both. I don't care. I have no problems in giving this album a rating bigger than the maximum, in spite of all its "glaring" flaws and problems. This album is an amazing accomplishment, in terms of music <em>and</em> in terms of technical innovations, which match some of the Beatles' experiments. Can you even call this album "experimental"? I know I can't. After all, experimenting means "trying the possibilities". And eventually, producing an experimental record means showing to the world all your possibilities and what you can do with them. Pink Floyd doesn't show their possibilities here: they <em>put them to good use</em>. As such, the record is the result of a series of successful experiments, but also a work of labour and care. And it totally matches my tastes, which <em>is</em> the definitive reason why it gets such a rating. After all, I don't deny the Beatles' importance, for example, but you don't hear me shattering the world with my bombastic statements of how much I love them. <strong>Dark Side Of The Moon</strong> is a different matter entirely. And if you think it's just me contributing to the hype, go read my review for Mike Oldfield's <strong>Amarok</strong>. Find it for yourself. I won't give the link here.</p>

<p>I only lament the fact that I don't have the original artwork for it. I don't own it on vinyl, which is a travesty, and the CD edition I have has that "remixed" cover, without the cool "backwards prism" at the back. But the CD itself, as an item, is something that I treasure dearly, since it's argueably the best Christmas gift I ever got.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>15/15</strong></big> - I don't think I need to say anything here, do I?<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>15/15</strong></big> - <em>This</em> is resonance, man. I can even feel my brain vibrate when it plays.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>14/15</strong></big> - It's only not totally original in the musical aspect, but everywhere else...<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>15/15</strong></big> - Everything here is brilliant. Really.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>15/15</strong></big> - It <em>is</em> the album I use to define solidness, actually.
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Bonuses:     <strong>+1</strong></big>    - It deserves it. It transcends ratings.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/16.png" alt="16" />
</p>

<p><em>Reader comments:</em></p>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:kartikeyam03@IIMB.ERNET.IN">Misra Kartikeya</a> (January 23, 2005):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p>Yeah it sucks... it does.....and you do overrate it ....</p> 

<p>Why? Cause it gets boring...you can't listen to these songs over and over again...unlike "<strong>Revolver</strong>", "<strong>Sticky Fingers</strong>" and all...Cause the melodies have been substituted by a pretentious, "serious-sounding" atmosphere....and you're an absolute jerk for docking points of <strong>Revolver</strong> cause it gets too serious (yup the apocalyptic "And your bird can sing" should make everyone shake in their boots <span class="edNote">[editor's note: hey, but 'Tomorrow Never Knows' is <em>exactly</em> like that. If that one isn't serious, I don't know what is]</span>)...Man, get a grip...</p> 

<p>Anyways, I hate this album more 'cause I hate Roger Waters' stupidity (Mom, Dad, the damned world, all bad, all tried to push Pinky into the Wall, see) than the actual quality of the songs...But still, there are a few gems....Specially "Us and them", the brilliant poignancy of the song shows what Floyd could (and should) have been....And "Time" is wonderful too, in a very British way, with its nice atmosphere based around the regret of having not trying hard enough in life (though The Kinks wrote probably 10 numbers better than this on the same theme)....The remaining numbers (except the totally wasted "Great gig.." and "On the run") are bearable too....</p> 

<p>So, give this a solid 7 from me.....A mediocre album from a mediocre band.....Oh and they did outshine themselves sometimes: just listen to the next two efforts....</p>
</div>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:awoehrel@netcarrier.com">Andrew Woehrel</a> (January 29, 2005):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p><strong>Dark Side Of The Moon</strong>-<big>9</big><br />
Best Song- Us And Them<br />
Goddamn, I am sick of Floyd. The most overrated band ever, the most flaccid, weak, energy-lacking performers outside of Sigur Ros on valium. They wrote about one recognizable riff, their vocalists are either nasal and annoying (Waters) or dreary and boring, (Gilmour) their rhythm section is weak and they usually used studio musicians because they weren't skilled enough to play anything on The Wall (Mason). They're known for sound effects, pretentiousness, concepts, and ceaseless bitching, but not for their music, Roger Waters is the most despicable jerk musician outside of Robert Fripp, David Gilmour is a money-grubber who makes money from fanatical Floyd fans,(more on those later) and has about the most boring guitar style imaginable. I'm surprised that he even played guitar live, I would imagine they'd lip-and-guitar sync their performances. Rick Wright's cool though.<br />
And their fans? Lazy stoners who think Roger Water's lyrics are "totally deep" and think they're fighting the man when they're sucking on their bongs and fucking their sisters. Pink Floyd are the art rock band for idiots. They play slow, boring, processed arena rock, soaked in pretension and capped off with a fucking lame guitar solo that's supposed to be expressive but sounds more like tedious time in the studio spent to make the most marketable "gorgeous" guitar solo possible.<br />
But you know what? <strong>Dark Side</strong>'s pretty good, so it gets a 9.</p>
</div>

<p>Comments? Rants? "<strong>Dark Side</strong> is overrated" remarks? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail me</a>!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="here">Wish You Were Here (1975)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>Shine On You Crazy Diamond</big><em>, all nine parts.</em>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li><span class="good">Shine On You Crazy Diamond, parts I to V ++</span></li>
  <li>Welcome To The Machine</li>
  <li>Have A Cigar <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Wish You Were Here <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Shine On You Crazy Diamond, parts VI to IX ++</span></li>
</ol>

<p>The bad thing about reaching your peak is that, well, it's downhill from there. And the disturbing thing is that, somehow, the band knew that <strong>Dark Side Of The Moon</strong> <em>was</em> their peak. They were having to deal with a lot of tension and pressure during that time, and this album reflects that. It was a sort of band decision to make their next record a sort of self-referential concept album, with part of it as a reference to the music industry and the way it deals with artists, and most of it dedicated to Syd Barrett - who actually appeared in the studio, by the time it was being made. Yes, this is the record that contains the longest Floyd composition ever, 'Shine On You Crazy Diamond', which was split into two tracks in order to fit in the record. I named 'Echoes' as my favourite single Pink Floyd track ever, but taken as a whole 'Shine On You Crazy Diamond' is every bit as good as that one. This time, the band didn't use sonic panoramas and landscapes to create the song, and almost all of it can be described as a Floyd-flavoured blues.</p>

<p>And all of it is gorgeous. Even though the song initially <em>was</em> a single track, it's pretty clear that the first five parts flow much more seamlessly, while the second half is made up of four parts that don't sound at all like each other. Either way, the first three parts or so feature mainly Gilmour and Wright exchanging solos, one on the guitar, the other on a Moog synthesizer. This piece has some of my favourite Gilmour solos, in fact. I guess the song's solemn, slow sound allows him to play his slow, solemn solos without sounding artificial. Still, Rick Wright's synth work is far better, and I can't imagine these solos being played in another way. They're the finest example of solos that sound "previous written" without lacking spontaneity. This part also features the famous, four note "Syd's Theme",which just fits the song like a glove. Part four is when the lyrics come in, and reportedly this is the only place where you'll hear Roger, David <em>and</em> Rick singing together. Needless to say, it's gorgeous, and Roger's lyrics definitely hit a nerve in me. Immediately after them, comes Dick Parry's sax soloing, which leads the piece into a tense finale, which is brought back for the sixth part, on the flipside. Interestingly, I always preferred that second half somewhat. Part seven is just the final verse, and part eight is a cool, but not very impressive funkish synth jam,but it does have my favourite bits: part six, which is the heaviest, most intense moments in the album, featuring Roger's insistent bass riff and some really loud, really high lap steel soloing by David. But the highlight, for me, is the final part, credited solely to Wright. The music considerably slows down and turns into a lengthy, weepy, gorgeous synth solo over a subtle, mellow backing by his piano, Roger's bass and drums. With each verse, the backing grows a little, eventually being joined by Gilmour's slide guitar, and ending with a glorious major key, as if finally resolving the entire song, which was on a minor key. Careful listeners will hear a snippet of 'See Emily Play' being played on Wright's synth as the song ends. Very clever, that.</p>

<p>That song takes up more than half of the record, you know. And that's good, because you'll know more than half of the album's great by default. And I recommend you to take the two tracks as one composition, seeing that they could easily be edited into one single track. The other tracks, though, are no slouch. One of them is the classic title track, one of the band's gentlest, most beautiful ballads, devoted a bit to Syd and a bit to themselves. The main guitar theme is one of David's best contributions to the band, and the main vocal melody and lyrics only help make things more beautiful. You know, maybe it is a bit overrated, especially since the big thing about Pink Floyd wasn't radio-friendly pop ballads. But so what? It's a beautiful song, either way. I also like 'Have A Cigar', Roger's "tribute" to record company executives, featuring vocals by Roy Harper, who was recording on a studio nearby around that time. Neither Roger nor David could do a good take, after straining their voices for 'Shine On You Crazy Diamond', and Roger reportedly regrets not having sung the track. I mean, I don't find it a <em>highlight</em>, but it's a cool, groovy, funky song, and features another solid, mean guitar solo; not to mention that synth riff, which is just awesome. As for 'Welcome To The Machine', it sounds a bit obvious, you know. But the use of sound effects is clever (in particular the "lift", in the beginning of the song, which takes you down to the actual machine), and the music builds tension and intensity very, very well as it goes. The ascending line, played on the acoustic guitar in the middle break, is something of a classic. I admit I'm not a fan of the song, but it fits the album and works very well in context.</p>

<p>But then again, what <em>is</em> the context? Roger moaning about how much record executives suck? Hmm, yes, but that's more like a small part of the album. The real theme of the album is absence, and not just the absence of Syd Barrett. It's like the kind of absence portrayed in the album's artwork. Oh, and by the way, this album has my favourite Pink Floyd album artwork, done by Hipgnosis, obviously. It's all about the burning guy, you know. I couldn't think of a better album cover, myself. I had that album on vinyl, once, but I gave it back because there was a little scratch on the beginning of side one which made it skip - that is, the annoying "backwards skip", if you understand me.That was a dumb thing to do, I know. This is an album I really, really like. It might sound a bit crazy to give <strong>Meddle</strong> a higher rating, but you shouldn't face it as a big thing. <strong>Wish You Were Here</strong> is excellent, but I prefer the former's musical and textural richness to the latter's "conceptuality". But it's not like it makes much of a difference, in the end.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>14/15</strong></big> - Not a single weak moment.<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>13/15</strong></big> - For one, Pink Floyd leaves the realm of "sound coolness" and reaches actual emotional ressonance. Only in a few places, though.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>13/15</strong></big> - There's not a lot of <em>new</em> stuff here, is there? Pretty authentic, still.<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>14/14</strong></big> - Great music, mainly.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>14/14</strong></big> - Really, really solid. Not that that's too surprising.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/13.png" alt="13" />
</p>

<p><em>Reader comments:</em></p>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:awoehrel@netcarrier.com">Andrew Woehrel</a> (June 20, 2004):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p>
<strong>Wish You Were Here</strong>-1975, Capitol<br />
Best song: Wish You Were Here<br />
Shine On You Crazy Diamond (part 1)<span class="good">+</span><br />
Welcome To The Machine<span class="bad">&times;</span><br />
Have a Cigar<span class="bad">&times;</span><br />
<span class="good">Wish You Were Here++</span><br />
Shine On You Crazy Diamond (part 2)<span class="good">+</span>
</p>
 
<p>Where does a band go after releasing their biggest album? For most bands, they try to make another, and fall flat on their face. I've decided, that the best thing to do, after creating your best album yet, is to TRY SOMETHING DIFFERENT. Beatles understood this. None of the Beatle's albums are ripoffs of their others, except maybe for <strong>Magical Mystery Tour</strong>, but that album is much more cohesive and has some much better songs on it than MOST of <strong>Sgt. Pepper's</strong>, (except for Day In The Life, of course. Masterpiece. Not even I Am The Walrus, or Strawberry Fields Forever are as good.) But where were we? Oh yes. Floyd tries to make <strong>Dark Side Of the Moon 2</strong>, and, they fail. Shine On You Crazy Diamond is a beautiful song, as is Wish You Were Here, but I don't like the other two. There's NOTHING redeemable about Welcome To The Machine. Roger's vocals are atrocious, the synths are horrible, etc.  What the hell? This band made "Us and Them" 2 years ago!! Have a Cigar is just as dumb, with an unmemorable, hookless melody, dumb vocals and lyrics, and you know a guitar solo must suck if you hear people talking about the solo in a song, but you never noticed it was there. Shine On You Crazy Diamond is a little too mellow and samey for 20 minutes to be one of the best songs ever, but it's at least GOOD. and Wish You Were Here is gorgeous. It saves the album from being a shitload. Pretty acoustic guitarwork, heartfelt vocal delivery, and one of Roger's best lyrical moments, a worthy ode to Mr. Barrett.<br />
All in all, the pretentiousness outweighs the beauty. This album proves both that it's hard to make an album after your masterpiece, and that Roger Waters is pathetic when pissed off.<br />
<big><big>7/10</big></big></p>
</div>

<p>Comments? Random blabberings? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail me</a>!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="animals">Animals (1977)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>Pigs (Three Different Ones)</big>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li>Pigs On The Wing, part 1</li>
  <li><span class="good">Dogs ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Pigs (Three Different Ones) ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Sheep ++</span></li>
  <li>Pigs On The Wing, part 2</li>
</ol>

<p>Say whatever you want, <strong>Wish You Were Here</strong> was the end of Pink Floyd as we knew it. And the band knew it, as well. We can only speculate about the reasons, but the fact is that the band was completely open and ready for Roger Waters to assume full leadership and creative control over it. And this album already shows it; having the whole concept and lyrics by Roger Waters is nothing new, but of these five tracks, only 'Dogs' is credited to both him and Gilmour. All the others are Waters compositions. You know, at this point, it doesn't make <em>that</em> much of a difference. The only clearly noticeable change is in the overall sound of the album. The production no longer values that profound, oceanic sound, and instead brings everything upfront and makes it all clear and crisp to-the-max. You have less piano and organ, and more guitars; less atmospheric balladeering, and more actual rock. The songs are all multipart, more intricate than usual, but you know what? I still don't call this "Progressive Rock". Just listen to the album once and you'll understand why, but this is what I call "<em>Agressive</em> Rock". I know it's a lame pun, but I can't think of any other way to describe this.</p>

<p>The titles of the songs more or less say everything, but the deal is that Roger was inspired by Orwell's <em>Animal Farm</em> when making this album. So, instead of pitying and sulking on the band's condition, he chooses to plainly use animals to make a bitter, angry allegory on the whole world. And each of the three categories, as you can see, is represented by a song - with the two-part acoustic ballad 'Pigs On The Wing' framing the whole thing. You know, the song doesn't have much to do with the concept directly, since it's dedicated to Roger's wife. Yes, it only gets actually happy on the second part, so it feels like a "relief" from the weight of the world Roger put on his back, but hey... it's still an "unrelated" thing, but what do I care? It's a fine song, and the three main tracks are where the action happens, anyway. I have no choice but to talk about them separately, okay? I know it's boring, but there isn't anything else I can do, since the three songs are all very different from each other. The most I can say is that, over these years, I realised that 'Pigs' is my favourite song in here. It's got something to do with the eerie organ riff that opens it, that completely mean groove the song is built in, Roger's singing and the awesome instrumental break, with David using a voice box on the guitar to give it a "piggy" sound. But in the end, the best thing is the combination of those elements, which makes a very hard-hitting, memorable and entertaining song. Oh, yes, and it namechecks one Mary Whitehouse, a censor of rock music at that time. It's particularly cool, since she had tried to censor Pink Floyd in the past, and Roger shows no fear at all and viciously trashes her - "and do you feel abused?". Heh heh.</p>

<p>The other two songs are actually reworked from previous Pink Floyd songs, which were performed in concerts, and were intended to be recorded for <strong>Wish You Were Here</strong>. The first one is 'Dogs', based on David's 'You Gotta Be Crazy', which here turns into a "homage" to the cutthroat capitalists of the world. The song is mostly slow and bluesy, giving David the opportunity to engage in several solos. The coolest bit is the "drowning" middle part, with one word echoed on and on and distorted over time, and Rick doing a weird synth solo over it. Now is that the atmosphere Pink Floyd used to show us? Why, certainly! It's not like the rest of the track is not good, but that passage especially great because it's adequate, and serves as a counterpoint for the tense, climactic finale, which to me always sounded like the "dog" being tortured to death by Roger's words. "Who was born in a house full of pain?" Man,that must have resonated with a lot of people out there, I figure. But then again, I'm just guessing.</p>

<p>The final song, 'Sheep', might be the fastest, heaviest song the band released since... well, since 'One Of These Days', or maybe 'Money'. The "verses" are a classic, with the interplay of Rick's organ and David's chugging distorted guitar, and Roger extending the notes he sings until they are transformed into weird synth notes. But the song wouldn't be so cool if it didn't have quieter, slower sections, like the middle-break with one of the band's roadies reciting a parody on the Psalm 23. His voice is distorted by a vocoder, which gives it an eerie, cool sound; shame that we can't understand his words very well. But the instrumentation is very cool as well, with vague synth notes reminiscent of 'One Of These Days', and a gradual build-up to the final verse, which eventually erupts with a grandiose, victorious-sounding guitar climax. Though I wonder what's supposed to be so victorious, since even though Roger tells us "heard the news? The dogs are dead!", the sheep just go on being every bit as blind and weak as they always were. Hey... maybe that <em>is</em> a good thing, for some people. Heh heh.

<p>It's also a bit ironic that 'Dogs', which is dedicated to the vicious and greedy hunters, is slower and quieter, while 'Sheep', which describes the pathetic and meek people, is one of Pink Floyd's fastest and heaviest songs. But that isn't too important, is it? It took me a while to fully appreciate the record, for some reason, but maybe it had to do with the reduced importance of Rick Wright in the band - which would go down to near zero (... oh, okay, absolute zero) in the next album. But then again, even though the give tracks complete each other conceptually, they are a bit isolated from each other - the complete opposite of <strong>Dark Side Of The Moon</strong>, as you might guess. So, this album doesn't score as high as their previous ones, but hey... it <em>is</em> a great Pink Floyd album with all respects. And, to me, the last great Pink Floyd album. Yeah, yeah, I can hear you all moaning and hissing. Let's just go on with the show.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>13/15</strong></big> - Boring moments? Nil! Only plenty of good music.<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>12/15</strong></big> - Less atmospheric sound, more Roger Waters anger. I guess it compensates, somewhat.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>12/15</strong></big> - It's a different sound, yes, but is it new?<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>13/15</strong></big> - Good songs all over. A tad more repetitive than before, perhaps.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>12/15</strong></big> - I can't demand much more. Yes, maybe a bit more of cohesion, but I won't be such a dick.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/12.png" alt="12" />
</p>

<p><em>Reader comments:</em></p>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:raven4x4x@hotmail.com">Alex Holman</a> (July 31, 2004):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p>This is the album, along with <strong>Meddle</strong>, that highlights the unfair media focus on <strong>Dark Side of the Moon</strong>. We all know about how Pink Floyd were totally invisible in the media until <strong>Dark Side</strong>, but what about since that album? It's almost as if <strong>Dark Side</strong> was the only album they ever made. And that's really unfair, since this album is a total masterpiece, more so than <strong>Dark Side</strong> in my opinion.</p>

<p>I'm not really sure what to make of the start and ending tracks, which I'll handle together because the're nearly identical. They are nothing like the rest of the tracks, not entirely bad but I'm not quite sure what they do. Roger thinks they are important anyway: in his <strong>Live In the Flesh DVD</strong> (total masterpiece by the way) he plays 'Pigs on the Wing Part One' before 'Dogs'. I suppose he should know what they're about since he wrote the things.</p>
 
<p>Anyway, onto Dogs. I don't like this song as much as the other two on this album, but it's still a great piece of music and songwriting. Dave's guitar solos are great, especially the 'duet' bit which is played twice throughout the song, but the ones on <strong>Live in the Flesh</strong> are better in my view. Also the synthy middle section has a funky keyboard solo. Back to the proper album now. I do like the feel of this song: that sort of desolate, empty music and the angry solos. It's good. Just not as good as the other two songs here.</p>
 
<p>If Dogs was angry, Pigs is even angrier. I really really love the intro: those funny keyboards, interesting bass and vicious guitar. And again after the verses into the intrumental bit with the freaky riff and pig squealy guitar. Wonderful atmosphere. The verses themselves are great: I can never resist singing along to "ah ha, charade you are". Roger writes some really nasty lines such as "you radiate cold shafts of broken glass". Great lyricism, and the delivery is pure evil. Nasty. This is an angry album.</p>

<p>Sheep just flat out rocks. From the funky keyboard intro it just explodes intro an awsome song. Again, there is anger here. The lyrics are just awesome. I have to nominate "bleating and babbling I fell on his neck with a scream. Wave upon wave of demented avengers march cheerfully out of obscurity into a dream" as my favourite song lyrics ever. The middle section with the 'Lord's prayer' is spooky, and the guitar at the finale: wow.</p>
 
<p>This is in my view the classic Pink Floyd album. Roger is at his most nasty, Dave does some great solos on Dogs and all round great guitar work throughout the album. Rick may be pretty much absent but he does some good bits, and Nick is solid throughout. This is The Floyd the way I like them. 9.5/10</p>
</div>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:awoehrel@netcarrier.com">Andrew Worhrel</a> (August 14, 2004):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p>Pink Floyd-<strong>Animals</strong><br />
1977<br />
Best Song: Dogs<br />
Pigs On The Wing Part 1<br />
Dogs<span class="good">++</span><br />
Pigs<span class="good">++</span><br />
Sheep<span class="good">++</span><br />
Pings On The Wing Part 2</p>
 
<p>Yeah, <strong>Wish You Were Here</strong> wasn't that good. I suppose Waters was planning to outdo that one with <strong>The Wall</strong> or <strong>Pros And Cons Of Hitchhiking</strong>, but then, BAM THWOK!* The Punk Rock Revolution! Barre chords! Distortion! Leather Jackets! Anarchy! Sniffing Glue! RRRRRRRRRRRRRROCK. Yeah...whatever. Waters, being the King of Pink Floyd, wasn't exactly a hero to bands like the Sex Pistols, who hated him and his pretentiousness. In fact, The Sex Pistols hated everything. Especially the Queen. They took political music to the extreme, with songs about anarchy, and other stuff that seems cool until you realize you're not a 14 year old teenager anymore. Waters actually was a political guy with opinions. Especially about "The Man". Ohhh, Waters hated "The Man", and his buddies the rich, their brutes, the police, and their mindless followers. So why not make a concept album about it?</p>
 
<p>AND MAKE HE DID.</p>
 
<p><strong>Animals</strong> is a pissed-off complaint (more of a whine than the scream of anger that Waters described it as) at the English Government. The Pigs are the rich greedy fatcats, the Dogs are the people with power and influence who do whatever it is to get to the top, and the Sheep have no power, they are the mindless followers. So he writes three songs about them. Dogs is the first, and the best. Waters himself is a Dog, by his own definition, and he puts some emotion into the delivery of his lyrics. It's an awesome song, 17+ minutes with some good Gilmour leads and such. I'd go as far to say the best Floyd song ever.<br />
Pigs is a complaint against censorship, and the fatcats. Aside from the angry political lyrics (big man, pig man, ha ha charade you are) the song is probably the "wimpiest" of the three, but it's still a good one. Cool rhythm and pig noises. Rock On, Mofo.<br />
Sheep is the worst of the three, in my opinion, the lyrics are rather silly (RISE UP, SHEEP! AND KICK THINE ASSES OF YOUR OPPRESSORS!! THEN BECOME DOGS YOURSELF! YOU FUCKIN' DUMBASSES)</p>

<p>(Man, that was quite Prindle-esque. I've been reading him a lot lately. Funny man. Funny, funny, poop-obsessed man)</p>
 
<p>Where was I? Oh yes. Sheep sucks. No, wait, it doesn't, it's Quite Kickass (tm) but it's not as good as the other two. The guitar finale is cool but..hokey? Eh, I dunno, something feels weird here.</p>
 
<p>Oh and the other two tracks are little acoustic bookends that are exactly the same other than the lyrics.</p>
 
<p>Now, my opinion: The plot is a little wacko, but it's fun and interesting (I was quite obsessed with it when I first heard it) and it has some relevance today. There are no bigger Pigs in the world than George Bush's Carlyle group. Ha ha. Charade you are. Motherfucker!<br />
Anyway, 3 fabtabulous songs, and two silly filler tracks. But they're only 3 minutes long as opposed to the rest of the album being the other 42 minutes. Sounds good to me. No problems here. 10/10. The Floyd's crowning achievement.</p>
 
<p>*Name the reference, get a quarter!</p>
</div>

<p>Comments? Comments? Comments? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail me</a>!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="wall">The Wall (1979)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>Another Brick In The Wall, part II</big><em>, and now do yourself a favour and keep quiet.</em>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li>In The Flesh? <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>The Thin Ice</li>
  <li>Another Brick In The Wall, part I <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>The Happiest Days Of Our Lives</li>
  <li><span class="good">Another Brick In The Wall, part II ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Mother ++</span></li>
  <li>Goodbye Blue Sky <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Empty Spaces <span class="bad">&times;</span></li>
  <li>Young Lust <span class="bad">&times;</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">One Of My Turns ++</span></li>
  <li>Don't Leave Me Now <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Another Brick In The Wall, part III <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Goodbye Cruel World</li>
  <li>Hey You <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Is There Anybody Out There</li>
  <li>Nobody Home</li>
  <li>Vera</li>
  <li>Bring The Boys Back Home</li>
  <li>Comfortably Numb</li>
  <li>The Show Must Go On</li>
  <li>In The Flesh</li>
  <li>Run Like Hell</li>
  <li>Waiting For The Worms</li>
  <li>Stop</li>
  <li>The Trial</li>
  <li>Outside The Wall</li>
</ol>

<p>Fantastic album! Absolute, timeless masterpiece recommended to everyone. 15 out of 15. I'm talking, of course, about <strong>Clube Da Esquina</strong>, the original one from 1972, not the 1978 sequel, though that one is good, too. As for this one, well, it's the culmination of Roger's dominance over the band, the ultimate Roger Floyd album. You know, this isn't just Roger writing all the lyrics and stuff: this is him putting his own personal details into the album, taking virtually all the decisions and very little input from the other band members. Oh, yes, and talking about band members, he brings a <em>horde</em> of extra musicians, as well as backup from an orchestra, a choir, and even a substitute drummer for some songs - including the countless sound effects and bits of speech. This is Roger Waters making Pink Floyd bow down to him, and as a consequence, creating one of the most famous and celebrated rock albums in history. But the aching question is: does it deserve that status?</p>

<p>Well, hold your horses, because I won't try to answer that. No, I can't be that pretentious. All I can give here is a very personal, very biased opinions. And, hey, if you're reading <em>my personal website</em>, that's what you ought to expect (just in case you didn't know). The concept, I hopefully don't need to explain much. But suffice to say, I'm not in full agreement with those who say the album's concept is silly, or makes no sense, or whatever. The concept isn't supposed to <em>make</em> sense, in a traditional sense, so I can't complain about that. What I know is that it <em>is</em> well executed, and if it's over-the-top, it's because it's supposed to be. I have no complaints about it, but who am I to speak? I don't listen to Pink Floyd because of the concept... well, maybe that's the problem, because from some point, the album builds more and more on the concept and kind of leaves the music on the background. It's like many of these songs were written just to satisfy a plot point. And, well, I couldn't care less for them. Luckily, that doesn't happen too often on the first disc, so that means... yes, it happens a lot on the second disc.</p>

<p>To be fair, though, I'm pretty sure this album was really important to Roger, at that time, and came across as a real moment of catharsis, as overblown as it could possibly be. In the 1977 tour, Roger was growing more and more alienated and frustrated by the audience's reaction to their playing (i.e. cheering and yelling regardless of what the band was doing), which caused him to shout abuse to the fans and, ultimately, spit at one of them. After the show, he had the concept of creating a wall between himself and the rest of the world, which is the basis for the plot of the album, as everyone knows. You can face it all like an opportunity for Roger to blame all his misery on other people (like David Gilmour did, on occasions), but you might as well see it as an in-your-face commentary of how the world can screw up a person's life against his will and, through the clever "cyclical" trick, how it's not an isolated case, but something that happens all the time. The concept for what would become Roger's solo album, <strong>The Pros And Cons Of Hitchhiking</strong>, was also developed by that time, and it was the band's choice to make <strong>The Wall</strong> instead - so they at least had A BIT of input, heh. But fact still stands that this is Roger's album, with small collaboration from Gilmour, but still a Roger album.</p>

<p>Well, okay, so let's review it. You know, the thing that annoys me isn't the isolated fact that this album was so successful. What bugs me is that, in many places, Pink Floyd and <strong>The Wall</strong> are virtually the same thing, and the album has basically <em>nothing</em> of what made the band so good through all those years. Roger brings in a bit of blues, a bit of hard rock, a bit of overblown orchestration and some other stuff. And while that brew would be rather commonplace for Roger Waters, it's very unusual for Pink Floyd. It <em>does</em> give us some undeniable classics, though, and I have no problems in admitting that. Like I said, the first disc has the most "actual music" material, and it's overall better. And, say what you will, but the side A medley of the first two parts of 'Another Brick In The Wall' is outstanding, both because of the songs' quality and the way they fit each other so well. Part 1 is quieter and more atmospheric, with just one verse and a long "coda" with sound effects and subtle synth work. 'The Happiest Days Of Our Lives' serves as an entertaining, brief interlude - featuring that memorable, pulsating drum rhythm - which throws us headfirst into a climactic ending, and then, part 2. I suppose I <em>should</em> rant at the song's popularity, but I can't do that! The song's too good. The melody, ridiculously simple to the point of near-banality, which worked so well as ominous atmosphere on the first part, here becomes something of a psychotic anthem. And the school choir? And the awesome, pounding martial-disco rhythm? The groovy rhythm guitar? Totally rocks. David throws a good solo at the end, but I don't care much about it - usual Gilmour stuff, anti-climactic here, in fact. Not that that's necessarily a bad thing.</p>

<p>I also really like 'Mother', an almost-acoustic blues-ballad of sorts, for which Roger needed another drummer because Mr. Nick Mason couldn't master that incredibly, mind-bendingly single 5/8 bar in between perfectly normal 4/4 bars. I'm being ironic here, notice. It's not a difficult rhythm, though I wouldn't doubt that Nick's inability was mostly due to the stress of working for such a psychotic despot like Roger Waters. But, like I can only say, I'm speculating. The song itself is good, anyway. I also love the album opener, 'In The Flesh?', which bursts in with those memorable-as-heck heavy-metal-ish chords, takes off into a "soulful" bluesy song, and comes tumbling down with a mess of noises, shouting and instrument-whacking - halting with the sound of a crying baby. <em>THAT</em> is an awesome intro. 'One Of My Turns' has always been something of a favourite - the first half isn't very special, with some synth droning serving as the base for some speech (a groupie coming into the apartment where Pink Floyd - that is, the protagonist - is staying) and a few sung verses. It eventually burts into a loud rock song with an excellent groove. It could have easily been longer than that, even, but it's fine. The third, final part of 'Another Brick In The Wall' is also good; the shorter of the three, angrier but not as rhythmic as the second. And has that memorable TV smashing intro. Goodie.</p>

<p>There's plenty of stuff that I definitely don't like, though. For example, the combination of 'Empty Spaces' and 'Young Lust' could easily be dismissed. The former's mainly just a long synthesizer intro to a song that never actually begins (though it has the cool backwards message, that one which says "congratulations! You just discovered the secret message"), and the latter's a stupid parody on stupid macho rock music. I <em>know</em> it's important to the plot, but see? It's like they just needed a song to suit that space, and wrote a throwaway that would fit. There's no cool riff, no catchy melody, and just a lot of dorky Gilmour screaming lyrics that are the stupidest kind of "raunchy" that I ever saw. Of course, they weren't really serious, but that only makes things worse: it's a parody, but it's not entertaining. "Take this rock 'n' roll refugee / Ooh, baby, set me free!", David sings. "Oooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooh, I need a dirty girl," they vent in the chorus. Yeuch.</p>

<p>Oh, yes, and I <em>didn't</em> get to the second disc, which features a load of on-the-spot vignettes like 'Bring The Boys Back Home' and 'The Show Must Go On', and more throwaway songs, this time in the shape of ballads. The short 'Vera' has a beautiful melody, and 'Is There Anybody Out There?' has beautiful acoustic guitar, but 'Nobody Home' doesn't have a lot to offer: orchestral piano ballad (I'm sure Rick didn't play that piano), with lyrics that don't particularly grab my attention. And don't even get me started on the dreaded 'Comfortably Numb', in which Roger allows David to waste metres and metres of tapes with go-nowhere guitar solos of the worst kind. The song itself is the usual "atmosphere" without melody, which is really just an excuse for David to show off. I have no use for it. I used to dislike it, but it's a waste of emotions to dislike it. It would just roll by unnoticed, if it wasn't so long. Roger's "dizzy" singing is quite fun, though. If you want ballads, the first disc has much better material, like 'Goodbye Blue Sky', and the aching, hard-hitting 'Don't Leave Me Now', which might as well be one of the eeriest, scariest "lost love" ballads ever written: dissonant chords, pulsating organ chord, scary atmosphere, and lyrics that go "how could you go / When you know how I need you / To beat to a pulp on a Saturday night, oh babe!" and so on, until the sad, lonely finale bursts in. <em>There</em> is a song that fits its context and works well.</p>

<p>Second disc is somewhat saved by the opener, 'Hey You', a beautiful song portraying desolation very well, with gorgeous guitar line and vocal melody - and a gruesome, "heavy" guitar solo for good measure, of course. But then, for the final side, it finally turns into a lengthy winding up of the plot with little memorable music in sight. The reprise of 'In The Flesh' isn't very special, and 'Run Like Hell' is a pretty generic, un-spectacular groove-rock with nothing catchy about it. Finally, it breaks down into the bombastic, puffed-up 'Waiting For The Worms', in which Pink is already transformed into the wanna-be crazed fascist. The only cool moment is at the end, with the crowd chanting along to the rhythm, which grows more intense and never seems to reach its end. 'Stop', well... <em>stops</em>, and takes us into 'The Trial', the album's theatrical grand-finale. At least, it's puffed up in the goofiest way possible, but I think it's awfully underdeveloped - maybe it's just the way Roger handles all the voices. He's awesome as "The Schoolmaster", but I just can't imagine him as Pink's wife or his mother, if you understand me. Bob Ezrin's orchestral arrangement is brilliant, but the song as a whole, I feel, is quite a letdown. I must admit that I was utterly <em>thrilled</em> the first time I heard it, but it lost its novelty value very quickly. Fortunately, after the wall is torn down, you have the pleasant, folky 'Outside The Wall', which slows down the ride to a very faint melody with a clarinet, an accordion and a children choir, which actually takes us all the way back to the beginning of the album. If you're masochistic, or if you worship the album <em>that</em> much, you can try manually linking the end of the last track to the beginning of the first one (which completes David's spoken "So this is where we came in" line) to make an endlessly repeating Pink Floyd album. Hooray! All thanks to the digital technology. You can't do that on vinyl, can you? THANKFULLY not, and it's a shame I don't have the album on vinyl. I resist the temptation, though. I'm not masochistic.</p>

<p>But it's not like I don't like the album at all. I'd be lying if I said that. The truth is that, well, I can't give it a definitive veredict, and I can only say that, yes, I kinda like it. I <em>respect</em> the album, and I <em>understand</em> all the people who love the album (as well as all the people who hate it!). Hey, seriously, I have no problem with it! <strong>The Wall</strong> <em>is</em> an excellent album, just as much as it is an awful album, so whomever you side with, it's okay. I'm not siding with anyone, anyway. What is definitely sure is that this album isn't "Pink Floyd" anymore. This album is Roger Waters, in lyrics and music. If you want Pink Floyd, get <strong>Dark Side Of The Moon</strong>, or, for the purists, <strong>Piper At The Gates Of Dawn</strong>. This is Roger's opus, so be prepared for something different. You know, Rick is just totally absent from the record, and he was actually fired from the band during the sessions. Good for him: the huge tour that ensued left the band out of money, while Rick just got his payment as a backing musician and carried on with his life. You can get <strong>Is There Anybody Out There?</strong> to listen to what the tour sounded like, but it would have been much more fun <em>watching</em> it, wouldn't it? I know I'd like watching it, if only for curiousity. As for <strong>The Wall</strong>, it can stick around. It still can be fun, sometimes.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>10/15</strong></big> - Depends A LOT on my mood. But disc one is <em>always</em> much better than disc two.<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>9/15</strong></big>  - Again, depends on the mood. But this isn't stuff to relate to. This is stuff to <em>think deeply about</em> i.e. stupid. Just kidding.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>12/15</strong></big> - Okay, gotta give Roger the due credit. Musically, it's not very new, though.<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>10/15</strong></big> - Some good material, some crap.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>11/15</strong></big> - It works as intended, I guess. But listening to the whole thing gets tiresome, eventually.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/10.png" alt="10" />
</p>

<p>Comments? Raves? "<strong>The Wall</strong> is the best album ever" remarks, in case you're Mark Prindle? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail me</a>!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="cut">The Final Cut (1982)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>Paranoid Eyes</big>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li>The Post War Dream</li>
  <li>Your Possible Pasts <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>One Of The Few</li>
  <li>The Hero's Return <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>The Gunner's Dream <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Paranoid Eyes ++</span></li>
  <li>Get Your Filthy Hands Off My Desert</li>
  <li>The Fletcher Memorial Home <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Southampton Dock <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">The Final Cut ++</span></li>
  <li>Not Now John <span class="bad">&times;</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Two Suns In The Sunset ++</span></li>
</ol>

<p>At this point, there wasn't even such a thing as "Roger Floyd". Pink Floyd was but an excuse, a moniker that didn't mean anything anymore. The music, which once belonged to all members of the band, now belongs solely to Roger Waters and nobody else - to the point where the album credits the album as being written by Roger Waters, and "performed by Pink Floyd". But this album being "performed by Pink Floyd" doesn't mean it will have anything similar <em>whatsoever</em> to the classic Floyd albums. See, this isn't just a band changing directions: this is a band ceasing to exist. Just think: Rick Wright was nowhere to be seen. Playing just as a hired musician during the short-lived <em>The Wall</em> tour, he just left and went to follow his own solo carreer. Nick Mason, well... there's nothing in the drumming here that assures us it's actually him playing. As for David Gilmour, he just stood there by Roger's pressure, and all he does is provide a bit of guitar here and there.</p>

<p>But wait... If David plays little guitar, and if Rick is totally absent... <em>who is playing</em>? Well, an orchestra. And the usual sound effects, of course. See, the music takes the route of "symphonic rock" suggested somewhere on side 3 of <strong>The Wall</strong>, with the usual blues twists and <em>lots and lots</em> of patented Roger Waters lyrics about war, war and more war. It was an adequate time to talk about war, in fact - i.e. the Falklands. And lyrically, the album isn't just some self-indulgent gimmick: it was <em>clear</em> that Roger was really into the thing, and had a genuine, personal motivation to do this - remember that his father died in the war when he was still young. So, yes, we can give him credit for that. The lyrics are all very good, in fact. Yes, it <em>might</em> become a bit obsessive, at times, but this is a concept album, for goodness' sakes. Well, musically, the album was put together starting from leftover songs from <strong>The Wall</strong>. You <em>can</em> hear influences from that album if you listen close enough, here, but there is new material, too, so it doesn't sound like a collection of outtakes.</p>

<p>Well, if anything, this album shows a bit of Roger's weaknesses as a songwriter. There isn't the diversity that <strong>The Wall</strong> had, so in addition of being a little monotonous, it also lacks those things that are really supposed to make an album like this truly memorable: solid melodies. Not that there aren't any, but the album overall seems more filled with "stuff" than I would be comfortable with. That stuff being meandering orchestral arrangements, SFX, singing that sounds more like talking than singing, etc.. But you know? Pink Floyd was never a band widely famous for their endless source of melodies. In fact, they were always very creative and original with arrangements, unusual twists, building of atmospheres and everything else. So, why should I be complaining that this album lacks melodies? Primarily because there's only about <em>one</em> atmosphere in the whole album. Yes, it's very, very well constructed and the orchestral arrangements are always spot on. But that doesn't mean that it will hold the attention of everyone as it goes. It's easy to get bored, or even annoyed, at the endless mumbling and moaning.</p>

<p>But that's not my case. I'm not into this album really because of the lyrics (even though Roger's voice is <em>always</em> in the centre of everything); I like it because the songs are, well, beautiful. And to be honest, I like it more than I like <strong>The Wall</strong>. All tracks here are full fledged <em>SONGS</em>; some shorter, some longer,but they are all fully developed songs. There aren't stretches of "plot development" like there was on <strong>The Wall</strong>, and there aren't either songs with the sole purpose of suiting the story's needs. After all, there isn't a plot here. And almost all those songs are just very, very beautiful. It helps that Roger hardly goes for the "catharsis" effect, so there are very few moments here that I could name as bombastic. The most that he does are the wild, unexpected dynamic shifts, like when he's just softly singing on the corner for one second, and then belts out an Earth-shattering scream; or when a disturbing sound effect bursts into the song. But Roger never takes the approach of "when you have nothing to say, say nothing, but say it VERY, VERY LOUD". Yeah, it gets <em>close</em> to that on the album's "rock and roll" song, 'Not Now John'. It sounds a tad similar to 'Young Lust', but instead of going for the goof factor, it's just an attempt to sound bitter and angry (with lyrics that refer to Hollywood and movies - most sources inform me that it reflects Roger's discontentment with the movie adaptation of <em>The Wall</em>, though I always thought it suited very well as a commentary on war movies in general). Yeah, it <em>does</em> sound bitter and angry, but it has those AWFULLY ANNOYING backing vocals. Not that they ruin the song singlehandedly, but they help.</p>

<p>Other than that bad spot, everything is just fine and dandy. I've always loved 'Paranoid Eyes', with its gentle sadness and beautiful piano line. The title track, which has 'Southampton Dock' as a sort of acoustic preamble, is also gorgeous, with one of the album's most memorable melodies - and a David Gilmour solo, that comes out of nowhere and goes to the same place. He's also present in the sad, bluesy 'The Fletcher Memorial Home', and on the slightly more beautiful 'Your Possible Pasts' (a part of that song appears on the movie adaptation of <em>The Wall</em>), while Roger prefers a sax solo for the wonderful 'The Gunner's Dream' - shame it's not Dick Parry, though. 'The Hero's Return', with another great melody, is fairly reminiscent of 'Another Brick In The Wall' - check out the guitar rhythm. The album ends with the fabulous 'Two Suns In The Sunset', with strange, apocalyptic lyrics - call me crazy, but the title seems to make an allusion to the explosion of an atomic bomb. That's how I interpret it, anyway.</p>

<p>Those who particularly liked <strong>The Wall</strong> might want to check out this album, though I can't guarantee total satisfaction. After all, this isn't "rock and roll". This is serious, introspective music that <em>actually</em> works if you're feeling introspective. And if you enjoyed the previous album as a fuel to chemically-induced trips, this record won't do at all. This is music for the sober. Okay, it has a mood of depressed drunkenness at times, but it's better to listen to this record with a clear, fresh mind - if you want to like the record, that is. Anyway, I'm not sure if this is one of those albums that eventually "grow on you". Not that it <em>won't</em> do so, but for most people, I believe, it's either instantaneous "love it" or "hate it". Either way, remember that this isn't essential Pink Floyd. It's a good idea to look for solo Roger Waters if you want more of this stuff. As for Pink Floyd, well, the band fell apart for good here. Permanently? Ah, no! Read on, but be careful.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>12/15</strong></big> - Say whatever you wish, I like this stuff.<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>12/15</strong></big> - It works well for me. Roger meant all of this, and he delivers the message well.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>11/15</strong></big> - Well, you know...<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>12/15</strong></big> - Not a whole lot of memorable musical material, but plenty of genuine beauty to be found.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>11/15</strong></big> - I can't deny it's monotonous. It demands the right mood to work well as a whole.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/11.png" alt="11" />
</p>

<p><em>Reader comments:</em></p>

<div class="commentsHeader">
      <strong><a href="mailto:bmovaqar@yahoo.com">Bahman Movaqar</a> (August 14, 2004):</strong>
</div>

<div class="comments">
<p>Hello,</p>

<p>I admire your subtle musical view on the album, (I mean '<strong>The Final Cut</strong>') but I think there's more to it than you have mentioned. The album is about WAR, as you have mentioned, and that sounds no joyful. I believe there should be sometimes in my habitual life to think about the facts the happen around me, around the world; about how a man's life is burned due to war, as two of my uncles' and about the hundreds of people being raped, murdered and killed everyday all over the world. Something should warn me that I am forgetting that I am not the only one on this sad old patient planet and my acceptable state of life does not mean that the others are the same.<br />
The album gives me the chance to think. I do not listen to the album just for interest or enjoyment, but to think; and that is what pure art should be: To make people think.</p>

<p>Finally, I did not mean any offence. If I did so, I am so sorry. <span class="edNote">[editor's note: Absolutely none taken!]</span></p>

<p>Thank you for your interesting site. I learned a lot about Pink Floyd here.<br />
Good Luck.</p>
</div>

<p>Comments? Rants? "Waters sux" remarks? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail me, please</a>!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="reason">A Momentary Lapse Of Reason (1987)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>Learning To Fly</big>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li>Signs Of Life</li>
  <li><span class="good">Learning To Fly ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="bad">Dogs Of War &times;&times;</span></li>
  <li>One Slip <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>On The Turning Away</li>
  <li>Yet Another Movie / Round And Around <span class="bad">&times;</span></li>
  <li><span class="bad">A New Machine, part 1 &times;&times;</span></li>
  <li>Terminal Frost <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="bad">A New Machine, part 2 &times;&times;</span></li>
  <li>Sorrow <span class="bad">&times;</span></li>
</ol>

<p>A legal battle ensued, and David Gilmour managed to retain the Pink Floyd name. So, he was very happy to bring Rick Wright and Nick Mason back into the band and release brand new Pink Floyd album. Well... in theory, at least. This sounds like a painful, desperate attempt by David to make something that deserves to be called a Pink Floyd record. The result is not too far from a late-eighties product made by someone who doesn't really remembers <em>what</em> is it that made the band so good, in first place. On second thought, that's what it <em>is</em>!</p>

<p>See, on surface, all the right elements are here: the surreal Hipgnosis cover, long tracks, lots of keyboard atmosphere, guitar solos, serious lyrics, slow rhythms, etc.. But that's just the surface. On essence, this is a David Gilmour solo album, every bit like <strong>The Final Cut</strong> was a Waters solo album: there isn't at all the sound of a <em>band</em> working together. It's just a lot of David Gilmour, a shadow of Mason and Wright, and a HUGE back-up band. There are so many additional musicians here, I'm even in doubt whether the two other Floyd musicians play here at all. As for the songwriting, well, it's basically Gilmour and a lot of other people - like, for example, Phil Manzanera. So, you should be aware of what you should expect: a rip-off.</p>

<p>Yes, a rip-off, because David is <em>intent</em> on making this a genuine Pink Floyd record. That, on itself, isn't necessarily a bad thing. If the music was good enough, I wouldn't complain too much. Problem is, the music <em>isn't</em> good enough. In fact, it's bad enough to make me complain. And a lot of people complained, as well, which motivated David to say something along the lines of "If it weren't Pink Floyd, it wouldn't be so bad." Well, firstly: it is Pink Floyd <em>only in name</em>. Secondly, OF COURSE it wouldn't be so bad! Heck, David should be actually surprised that people weren't praising it all over <em>because</em> it was Pink Floyd - which would have been more predictable. If it were a David Gilmour solo album, the album's weaknesses would be understandable. The album would be just as sucky, but it wouldn't be such an insult. But <em>no</em>: it just had to be released under the Pink Floyd moniker. So, what can I possibly do other than consider this the worst Pink Floyd album ever? I'd be lying if I said it weren't, really. Of course, that's to <em>me</em>, but most Pink Floyd fans weren't happy either with it.</p>

<p>For starters, you can imagine the album as an updated, hi-tech version of <strong>Meddle</strong>, with all the atmosphere removed. Instead of the profound, evocative sounds made by all sorts of things, you get the metallic, lifeless meanderings of synthesizers and guitar solos - yes, <em>plenty</em> of guitar solos. There aren't as many guitar solos as David would have the pleasure to stuff their live releases with, which means that when the guitar isn't whining and squealing for hours without stopping, there's... well, pretty much <em>nothing</em>. The record's awfully empty and hollow - with a few exceptions. For example, 'The Dogs Of War' is downright <em>atrocious</em>. Say whatever you will about Roger Waters's obsession with war, but you gotta agree that he never did something so in-your-face, ridiculous and pathetic as this. I'm even in doubt whether David was serious when doing this, because there's absolutely <em>no way</em> I could take the "menacing" synthesized strings, the "angry" yelling and the stomping Blues rhythm seriously. If he <em>wasn't</em> serious, well, the result is just not funny. And what it is? <em>Worst Pink Floyd song ever</em>. The fans of the album will excuse me, but 'The Dogs Of War' is a carcrash, and there's little I can do about it. Still in the "atrocious" section, I have to show here my utter confusion regarding the two-part 'A New Machine', which is formed by nothing other than David's singing encoded by some wild effect that I can only describe as a sort-of vocoder with heavy reverb, which ends up turning every word he sings into a creepy synth chord. It's a cool effect to be used for a while, but to make an entire track with? And what's so important about it to be used as "bookends" for 'Terminal Frost'? What's this, 'Pigs On The Wing', by any chance? David doesn't seem to be singing anything important at all, and no melody is detectable there, so no; sounds like hi-tech wizardry show-off, and of the worst kind, to me.</p>

<p>Other than that, the track that's "bookended" by that <em>thing</em> is a quite pleasant, though inessential instrumental song. It also gets kudos for sounding just like what the title suggests, with a lonely piano line popping up at times, and a soprano sax filling in the blanks. To me, it's just, <em>just</em> fine. On the other hand, the opener 'Signs Of Life', is just nothing worth listening: a slow synth arpeggio, which gives in to a no-great-shakes-at-all snipped of a guitar solo. The only good part of it is when it finally allows 'Learning To Fly' to begin. That song was the staple of Pink Floyd at the time, artsy MTV video at all. And, you know, it's a nice, well-written song, with a lack of a vocal hook but a well-built, upbeat backing track that makes up for it, sort of. The "typical Pink Floyd" middle-break, with the voices and all isn't detracting at all, and the only annoying thing is that idiotic "tinkling", almost random sequence of synth notes running through parts of the song, which writes "LATE EIGHTIES" all over the song and brings back memories of the soundtracks of movies like <em>Flashdance</em>, <em>Top Gun</em> and <em>Dirty Dancing</em>. I know, I know, it probably was "ULTRA HAWT" at that time, and after all, Dave was keeping up with the times, but a dated synth effect is a dated synth effect, no matter what. A similar thing pops up on the otherwise great pop song 'One Slip', which builds from a totally unnecessary, unexplainable intro that sounds like an alarm system being set off.Why? Dunno. I just know the song itself is really nice. And, you know, I don't have much against 'On The Turning Away',which is his attempt at sounding really "anthemic"; it's got a really good melody, after all! Yes, it's overblown, but it's a good melody nonetheless. And, oh yes, it's got a really long guitar solo at the end, too. After all, how could the side end with <em>anything</em> other than a long guitar solo? No way, man. Dig that soulful playing, MAN.</p>

<p>The remaining two songs are so hollow that I can hardly think of something to say about them - except that 'Sorrow' is the longest song in the record. Eight minutes! 'Yet Another Movie', with its seven minutes and 'Round And Around' coda, isn't too far behind, either. And they are also murderously slow and filled with synth noises that are supposed to sound eerie, I assume. It might sound eerie for some people, but I'm not one of them. Not that I have a problem with them, you know. Us and them, and after all, we're only ordinary men. As for me, personally, my slot of "slow, atmospheric" music is already filled with Sigur R&oacute;s, for example, so this album is totally unecessary - not that it ever <em>was</em> necessary for anything other than filling my Pink Floyd collection. Oh, no, I don't own all Pink Floyd records - only the more important ones. And, want it or not, this is an important record. So, it gets an important <em>5</em> - which is at least higher from the unimportant 4 I gave to <strong>Tubular Bells II</strong>. You happy now, Gilmour fans?</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>5/15</strong></big>  - Aside from the bad spots, it's good. Err... I mean, aside from the good spots, it's bad. Uh... Er...<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>4/15</strong></big>  - Guitar solos? No, thanks. Dull synthesizers? I'll pass. Entertaining rhythms? Those can stick around.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>5/15</strong></big>  - How original is a Pink Floyd rip-off? That's right: Oh, for goodness' sakes!<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>6/15</strong></big>  - Okay, that's <em>some</em> good fluff here. Fluff, but good. Good, but fluff. You know.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>5/15</strong></big>  - Solid? Does it even matter?
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/05.png" alt="5" />
</p>

<p>Comments? Suggestions? <em>Flames</em>? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail me</a>!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="bell">The Division Bell (1994)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>Poles Apart</big>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li>Cluster One</li>
  <li>What Do You Want From Me?</li>
  <li><span class="good">Poles Apart ++</span></li>
  <li>Marooned</li>
  <li>A Great Day For Freedom</li>
  <li>Wearing The Inside Out <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Take It Back</li>
  <li>Coming Back To Life <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Keep Talking</li>
  <li>Lost For Words <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>High Hopes <span class="good">+</span></li>
</ol>

<p>Again? Another surreal Hipgnosis cover? Yep, you betcha. This is one puffed-up record. And it isn't really because of the beautiful cover, not even because the whole album is <em>sixty-six</em> minutes long, or because it's again assembled like one big medley. Nope: the really big deal is the <em>Publius Enigma</em>, which surrounds this entire album, and that went for <em>over one decade without being solved</em>. You know, what else could make an album so good as an Internet puzzle that was actually a big marketing trick by EMI?</p>

<p>Anyway, this album is good. Yes, I said it, and I can say it again: this album is <em>good</em> - as in <em>enjoyable</em>. For one, it at least <em>seems</em> to me that good ole David spent some more time coming up with good material for the album. Also, it might be just an impression, but it <em>seems</em> like I can hear a bit more of Mason and Wright on the album. In fact, Rick even contributed and sung one song in here; that is, 'Wearing The Inside Out'. And the fact that the song has a <em>quite</em> memorable and catchy melody makes me more convinced that David's idea of taking over Pink Floyd just wasn't bound to work. Wright was so important to the band, it's just silly to forget him. But then again, he just contributed <em>one</em> song in here; and it sounds unlikely that it's because David was stopping him from contributing more. The song? Well, it's beautiful - horribly slow, maybe a bit too slow for its own good (not that slow songs suck by default, but heck, making a really good slow song is <em>no trivial matter</em>), but enjoyable.</p>

<p>David doesn't really disappoint, though, and he's responsible for actually <em>very good</em> songs in here. The thing is, this is really a return to the past; if <strong>A Momentary Lapse Of Reason</strong> was an attempt to bring Pink Floyd all the way to 1987, <strong>The Division Bell</strong> is an attempt to bring us all back to 1973. Yes, the sound is updated and modern, but in terms of atmosphere, he's really trying to resurrect the old feel here. Not necessarily a <em>bad</em> thing, but the lack of progress can be annoying for some. Myself, I'm already happy that this "resurrection" is <em>far</em> more convincing than the previous album, only because the band sounds more authentic here, without all those 80's electronic gimmicks. There <em>is</em> a fair bit of gimmickry here, but it's much less accentuated. And, yes, there's a fair ammount of Pink Floyd immitation going on here - like on the very beginning, with 'Cluster One', a slow introductory instrumental that sounds like all the Pink Floyd clich&eacute;s wrapped up into a single package. It works, though, because it's just a subtle welcome, instead of some long, self-indulgent solo or some self-important nothing like 'Signs Of Life'. 'What Do You Want From Me' brings back the bluesy, angry groove for David to vent his frustration about people's expectations. Ooo, he sounds pissed off there! "What do you want from me?" he asks you, over a not very convincing rhythm; "Do you want my blood? Do you want my tears?" No, Dave, I just want your <em>MELODIES</em>, you know. "You're so hard to please?" Geez, Dave, nice way to diss your fans."Do you want me to sing 'till I can't sing anymore, play the strings 'till the fingers are raw?" <em>NO</em>, for goodness's sakes, David! You <em>already do</em> that all the time, and that's <em>definitely</em> not what I want. Like good old Geddy Lee would say, YOU BEEEEET YOOOOUR LIFE!</p>

<p>It's not like I'm complaining, see. There <em>are</em> some songs that don't do much for me, like the second attempt at being "anthemic" - that is 'A Great Day For Freedom' - and the mechanical groove of 'Keep Talking', which even reaches out for the guitar effect from 'Pigs' and an extract of speech from Stephen Hawking's voicebox (!); it also features backing vocalists a la <strong>Dark Side Of The Moon</strong> (like several other songs here) and is quite meandering, but not bad. I could do with less guitar, of course, but that's the usual complaint. As for 'Take It Back',it's upbeat and poppy and really, <em>really</em> lightweight - which means that "typical Pink Floyd" middle-break <em>is</em> kinda unecessary and detracting. Just sounds like another attempt at making it <em>clear</em> that they are, after all, Pink Floyd. The same happens on 'Poles Apart', but the small difference is, 'Poles Apart' is <em>gorgeous</em>. The title refers to Syd Barrett and Roger Waters, apparently, and the song's melody and guitar line really do them justice. And really, I don't mind the "spaced-out" break, since the song comes back for a particularly touching finale,justifying the song's length and all. And after that song comes 'Marooned'. You know, I <em>was</em> very partial for that song in the past, but I can't say I am anymore. See, it's a guitar solo. A <em>five minute guitar solo</em>. The band is playing, for sure, but it's a five minute long guitar solo. You know, I could stop talking about it right now, since it'd be easy to guess my feelings for a five minute long David Gilmour guitar solo. Suffice to say, I have more use for that guitar solo at the end of Mike Oldfield's <strong>Tubular Bells 2003</strong>. That's supposed to be shocking, by the way.</p>

<p>Oh, but there are other songs that I like. For example, the catchy ballad 'Coming Back To Life' - with more Gilmour soloing, yes, but it's catchy nonetheless. And in 'Lost For Words', he switches to the acoustic guitar to deliver a pleasant, beautiful country-tinged ballad, and I actually like the lyrics about useless fights that never get resolved (yes, another indirect jab at Roger), and the sounds of a boxing fight in the middle, in which the actual winner is never announced. And in the end, comes the long, dramatic 'High Hopes', which works as a sort of recollection of the band's carreer to that point. I could play "spot the reference", by noticing how elements like the fly from 'Grantchester Meadows' and the cathedral bells from 'Fat Old Sun' (except in complete disorder), as well as the final lines referencing 'See Emily Play', appear in the song. It's a beautiful, dark song, and at this point, I don't even bother about the closing guitar solo (is there any other possible way to close the album?). It's all fine and dandy.</p>

<p>To be honest, I don't even know why I'm so positive about the album. But then again, I'm probably not <em>that</em> positive about the album; it's just that the good spots stand out a lot more, when you consider the previous album. Also, it's a much more pleasant album to listen to. Though it's not much more than pleasant, and a few parts of it aren't even that. So... what's the point? Well, it has 'Poles Apart'. <em>And</em> Rick Wright contributed with one song. And... er, it could have been much worse. And yes, it's the last Pink Floyd studio album, and if you allow me to say so, let it be just that. I mean, it was awesome to see the four guys joining together for Live 8, but let's leave the possibility of a new studio album out of question.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>11/15</strong></big> - It's pleasant, and moderately entertaining.<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>11/15</strong></big> - I can't say they don't get a real mood going on here, though.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>9/15</strong></big>  - Well, it <em>is</em> somewhat fresh.<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>11/15</strong></big> - There <em>is</em> good music to be found, here.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>10/15</strong></big> - Sure. It works well. It's <em>LONG</em>, but works well.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/10.png" alt="10" />
</p>

<p>Comments? Raves? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Send 'em in</a>!</p>

<h2 class="artistHeader">Syd Barrett</h2>

<h2 id="laughs">The Madcap Laughs (1970)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>Octopus</big>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li>Terrapin <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">No Good Trying ++</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Love You ++</span></li>
  <li>No Man's Land <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Dark Globe ++</span></li>
  <li>Here I Go <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">Octopus ++</span></li>
  <li>Golden Hair <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>Long Gone</li>
  <li>She Took A Long Cold Look</li>
  <li>Feel</li>
  <li>If It's In You</li>
  <li><span class="good">Late Night ++</span></li>
</ol>

<p>Before Syd Barrett turned into a real myth, he had a short lived solo career - and not a very obscure one, I say. In fact, among the works of Pink Floyd solo members, Syd's might be the most interesting, and <strong>The Madcap Laughs</strong> is a true classic in all respects. There are some pitfalls and traps here, though, for those who want insight into Syd's creative mind, because many (myself included) made it look like this album is a closer look into a completely insane mind. It isn't. Of course Syd wasn't the sanest of men back at that time, but the danger comes from listening to the man as if he were a caricature, and not a man. And the case is so serious that even David Gilmour and Roger Waters, who produced portions of the record, get very close to depicting him in a disfigured way. That's a shame, because this album is, primarily and mostly, a record of <em>music</em>, not of psychiatric theses.</p>

<p>I can't pretend you'll find an "album for the whole family" here, though. Many things here are definitely strange, but that's more due to the modus operandi of Syd Barrett and Malcom Jones, who was the initial producer of the record. Firstly, most songs were recorded firstly with Syd on the guitar and vocals, and the rest of the instruments were added <em>later</em>. This was the case of, for example, 'No Good Trying' and 'Love You'. And Syd wasn't at all bothered with keeping the rhythm steadily, so he'd skip or add beats, stum a single chord away for an indeterminate amount of time - not to mention that he'd have a new idea with each take, so you have an idea of how things were going. On those two particular songs, members of The Soft Machine were invited to record the backing track. They had little or no time to rehearse, had to try to follow Syd's unpredictable playing, and he'd insist that everything was completely okay, so the finished results almost sound like a car crash, at times. But what do you know? They are both <em>excellent</em> songs,and really, after listening to THESE versions of the songs, trying to make a "normal" recording of them would sound just wrong. Syd is caught on a very spontaneous moment, and the Soft Machine's efforts only add to the "normality is so boring!" spirit of everything. 'Love You', in particular, is a total delight, with those quirky romantic lyrics and a nursery-rhyme-ish melody.</p>

<p>Stepping away from those two songs in particular, the album is built with many different bits and pieces from many different sessions. There are songs taken from the very first sessions with Malcolm Jones, there are tracks recorded live-in-the-studio with Syd and some invited musicians, there are tracks produced by Gilmour and Waters, and so on. So, I can't really talk about the whole album in the same breath. So, yes, we have all sorts of stuff here. Side A focuses on the more rock-oriented material, with two songs already covered above. The fuzz-rocker 'No Man's Land' is really good and fresh, and 'Here I Go' is a very fun and very pretty "oldies style" tune to close the set. The other two tracks feaure only Syd and his guitar, and both are complete opposites in terms of mood. 'Terrapin' is bluesy and tranquil, and the lyrics are really groovy. It's one of the nicest, catchiest songs here, in fact. 'Dark Globe', on the other hand, is one of the most chilling, disarming songs in Syd's career, and leaves you wondering really what sorts of problems <em>could</em> be running in his head.</p>

<p>Side B goes on a lighter direction, and has a stretch of 3 "one-take" acoustic performances, which Syd just played as his ex-Floyd mates requested him. They're nice songs and have very good melodies (especially 'Feel'), but what particularly bothers me is the decision to include an aborted take of 'If It's In You', in which Syd goes horribly out-of-tune - and not only that, but the whole performance is awfully unsure and rough, showing clearly that he hadn't rehearsed much, and probably wasn't even willing to play the song in first place. The songs would probably have yelded great performances if worked properly, but as they are, come off as nothing much more than sketches. The non-sketch songs, though, are really great! 'Long Gone', which in essence is also an "acoustic only" song, gets a fuller arrangement that works very well, and 'Golden Hair' - Syd's musical reading to a James Joyce poem - is outstanding, featuring a mantraic melody for voice and guitar, augmented by soft arrangements for vibraphones, cymbals and whatnot, while keeping the atmosphere it should have. The other two are big favourites of mine: 'Late Night' is a gorgeous little tune, with a rather eerie arrangement and a beautiful melody. And 'Octopus' is, quite simply, a pop masterpiece.Really, this song is among one of the best things Syd <em>ever</em> did, with a madly cheerful series of vocal lines, an exciting vocal delivery, a great work by the backing band and even a great guitar solo. This is one of those things that is hard to explain, but 'Octopus' is, to me, a prototype of a perfect pop song. Acoustic guitar jangling can't get much better than this.</p>

<p>Pink Floyd fans can hardly get on without this album, in short; even if this is the <em>only</em> Syd acquisition they'll make. It's very, very far from <strong>Piper At The Gates Of Dawn</strong>, but it's still a necessary listen. Get this not just to see the "mad" side of Syd Barrett, but to see his musical, talented side.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>13/15</strong></big> - Great songs all over it. Quite simply.<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>13/15</strong></big> - It's hard to think this stuff is not sincere. It's Syd at his most vulnerable and open.<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>13/15</strong></big> - There's hardly any stab at something <em>innovative</em>, but this is Syd Barrett, inimitable and unequallable.<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>13/15</strong></big> - This is <em>music</em>, man, nothing more than pure music.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>13/15</strong></big> - Even though it's not very smooth, it's a very complete record.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/13.png" alt="13" />
</p>

<p>Comments? Suggestions? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Send them in</a>!</p>

<h2 class="artistHeader">Roger Waters</h2>

<h2 id="hitchhiking">The Pros And Cons Of Hitchhiking (1984)</h2>
<p class="medium">
  Best song: <big>5:06 AM (Every Stranger's Eyes)</big>
</p>
<div class="medium">
  Track list:
</div>
<ol class="trackList">
  <li>4:30 AM (Apparently They Were Travelling Abroad) <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">4:33 AM (Running Shoes) ++</span></li>
  <li>4:37 AM (Arabs With Knives And West German Skies) <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>4:39 AM (For The First Time Today, part 2)</li>
  <li>4:41 AM (Sexual Revolution) <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li>4:47 AM (The Remains Of Our Love)</li>
  <li><span class="good">4:50 AM (Go Fishing) ++</span></li>
  <li>4:56 AM (For The First Time Today, part 1)</li>
  <li>4:58 AM (Duncarin, Dunroamin, Dunlivin)</li>
  <li>5:01 AM (The Pros And Cons Of Hitch Hiking, part 10) <span class="good">+</span></li>
  <li><span class="good">5:06 AM (Every Stranger's Eyes) ++</span></li>
  <li>5:11 AM (The Moment Of Clarity)</li>
</ol>

<p>As Pink Floyd finally came crumbling down to bits (that is, before David Gilmour promptly put it back up... er, sort of), Roger Waters went his own way to release his first fully solo release. As usual, this is a concept album, and the concept was actually developed just after <strong>Animals</strong>, and it was one of the options he presented to the band along with <strong>The Wall</strong>. The concept is... well, obscure, to say the least. And the music is... well,not very "user-friendly". As a result, this is one of the most hated Floyd-related releases of all time. And why? Who the hell knows!</p>

<p>Okay, I <em>can</em> see why. Firstly, the lyrics hardly ever make sense. They take all sorts of left turns and make all sorts of obscure references. Secondly, the music is repetitive <em>as hell</em>: and not just the individual songs, but the WHOLE album. Everything here is done in that trademark "bluesy" style, with Eric Clapton providing lead guitar,those female backing vocalists a la 'Not Now John', and Roger Waters, Roger Waters, Roger Waters and even more backing vocalists. And the same melodies are played all over the album. Heck! Everything sounds the same! Waters never stops whining! There are gimmicky sound effects everywhere! Argh. Yeah, it often goes like that. But you know what? This isn't really the case of the album being bad, but of the album having its own, well-defined style. Firstly, the storyline of the album follows a man's dream sequence, of getting involved with a hitchhiker, going to live with her in the country and getting completely fucked up until he finally realises that he's safe with his wife, at home, and that they still love each other. This is done in the most obscure way possible, with red family cars turning into green Lamborghinis, Arabs with knifes invading the man's bedroom, Yoko Ono encouraging a man to jump from an airplane's wing,and so on. And the actual lyrics only show <em>a part</em> of the story, with the overall storyline narrated on the liner notes. Anyway, say whatever you wish about the lyrics, you gotta give credit to the man who created the concept of a "real time" album way before <em>24</em> hit the TV screens. Awesome, huh? (yes, this is supposed to sound stupid)</p>

<p>But, anyway, the music. Yes, it "all sounds the same", but with a reason. The album isn't made of "songs". See the subtitle of track ten? It says "The Pros And Cons Of Hitchhiking, <em>PART 10</em>". See? All songs are merely parts of the same musical piece! So the repetition of themes isn't due to the lack of ideas, but a way to provide the unity of the whole thing. Now, I'm not saying that a 40-minute-long Roger Waters piece with nonsensical lyrics is necessarily a good thing and that the haters are all wrong. Everyone has the right to hate the album, and I'm not saying otherwise, you FUCKING NAZIS! All I'm saying is that, hey, the album is somewhat unique, and I LIKE IT A LOT. You ever had that feeling of not being so sure if you like an album or not - or worse, whether you SHOULD like it or not? Well, I've had.and further listens confirmed that, yes, I like this album a lot. Come to think of it, I like it better than <strong>The Wall</strong>. It's not quite as whiny, and the music is very beautiful pretty much all the way through. The old dogma that Roger Waters isn't a good songwriter, and thus relies entirely on lyrics, shows to be not quite right here. There aren't too many themes, but the are very good and very melodic (!). And despite the sameyness of it all, there are several standouts through the album.</p>

<p>Say, the wild "quiet/loud" dynamics help give the album a sense of motion and happening, such as on 'Running Shoes' and 'Arabs With Knives And West German Skies'. The opening track introduces the themes that are used all over the album, and it's very nice and well performed. The songs that break off from the overall formula are really good, such as the pounding, dramatic 'Sexual Revolution' (the song is radically different from what you'd imagine judging solely by the title, heh heh) and the also pounding and also dramatic 'Go Fishing', which I really like. For a change from the hazy, hungover atmosphere of it all, the snappy, upbeat, funny 'The Pros And Cons Of Hitchhiking, part 10' shows up almost as a blessing. A honestly catchy song at last! Yup, you heard it. Of course, it's STILL on that bluesy style with female backing vocalists and Eric Clapton, but it <em>does</em> stand out considerably. And to round things off, 'Every Stranger's Eyes' is one of the most beautiful ballads Roger ever wrote. The performance is very tender and poignant, and there's no overdoing of the "emotional" effect (okay, it gets close, at times). And it's plainly cool to have a song about those wholesome "moments of clarity" one experiences briefly before or after sleep. If you don't think so, well, go get yourself officially screwed. I <em>do</em> find it extra-cool, and the song is gorgeous, like I said.</p>

<p>Overall, the most striking aspect of this record is that it's a FUN, LIGHTWEIGHT release from the man of <strong>The Final Cut</strong> fame. And it really does sound like he and the band had a lot of fun recording it, and I appreciate that. In general, I can say that this album tramples <strong>A Momentary Lapse Of Reason</strong>, though that ain't saying much. Yeah, like I said, I like it better than <strong>The Wall</strong> and almost as much as <strong>The Final Cut</strong>, albeit in a different way. This is one of the best "not-give-a-damn" albums I have, and I'll always have fun listening to it. I think. I just don't recommend it to the faint of the heart. Consider yourself well warned.</p>

<p class="ratingHeader">
  Rating:
</p>

<p class="rating">
  <big>Fun factor:  <strong>13/15</strong></big> - A GODDAMN 13, yes. You saw that right.<br />
  <big>Resonance:   <strong>10/15</strong></big> - How the heck should I know? Is this sincerity or just a well-performed role in a play?<br />
  <big>Originality: <strong>10/15</strong></big> - Ehh...<br />
  <big>Richness:    <strong>12/15</strong></big> - I'll say it again: the musical themes, though they are few, are very good.<br />
  <big>Solidness:   <strong>12/15</strong></big> - Yes, it does work very well.
</p>

<p class="ratingFinale">
  Total: <img src="images/11.png" alt="11" />
</p>

<p>Comments? Complaints? <a href="mailto:sirmustapha@gmail.com">Mail them</a>!</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="index.htm">Back to the Reviews Page index</a></p>

<p>
  <a href="http://validator.w3.org/check?uri=referer"><img
      src="http://www.w3.org/Icons/valid-xhtml10"
      alt="Valid XHTML 1.0!" height="31" width="88" /></a>
</p>

</body>

</html> -->