<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<update-list>
  <update-title>Vangelis: All the way to Beaubourg!</update-title>
  <update-link>http://sirmustapha.0sites.org/reviews/vangelis</update-link>
  <update-text><![CDATA[Feel like wading through some REALLY obscure releases by one of the most important musicians in what we call "electronic" music these days? Hop in and check out! These reviews cover his career all the way to the point when he ended his contract with RCA, and the later ones shall arrive when I have the time. For now, I hope you enjoy them!]]></update-text>
  <artist ref="vangelis">
    <name>Vangelis</name>
    <text><![CDATA[
<p>Of all the considered "electronic" musicians, Evangelos Odysseas Papathanassiou certainly was one of the most prolific and versatile. Not only has he released a generous amount of albums in his more than 40 years of music making, but all the websites out there document the sheer, vast amount of soundtracks for obscure and rare films never released as LPs, collaborations with other artists, as well as releases that have never seen the light of day. And not only that, but he shifted effortlessly between avant-garde jazz, proto-ambient and proto-New Age explorations, sci-fi themed electronica, experimental electronics, classical music and pure good ole rock 'n' roll. These wild fluctuations were even more apparent in the 70's, but even after that he never stopped trying new things.</p>

<p>Prolificness and diversity certainly are nice, but not very good if there's no underlying quality, right? Well, just let me argue that Vangelis wouldn't be hired to make so many TV and film soundtracks for nothing. Let's just count the famous ones: <em>Chariots of Fire</em>, <em>Bitter Moon</em>, <em>Blade Runner</em>, <em>The Bounty</em>, <em>Missing</em>, <em>Alexander</em>, and the list goes on including everything from French wildlife documentaries (<em>L'Apocalypse des Animaux</em>, <em>L'Opera Sauvage</em>) to a Japanese film about the antarctic continent (<em>Antarctica</em>). And this is not simply a case of a musician being overhyped and valued by his "name": the man truly started from below. His genesis of his career was in a Greek pop band called Aphrodite's Child, in which he played keyboards. They hit it big in France, and lived there for some time. There, Vangelis made his connections and started to work making soundtracks and working with other artists, and back then he was still credited as Vangelis Papathanassiou. He wasn't there just for the cars and chicks, though: his greatest interests were in art, and soon he started investing in his own studio. Eventually he landed a record deal with RCA, finished his Nemo Studios in London, and put out his first proper solo records as simply Vangelis. And, from then on, he'd only keep growing to become this nice, gentleman-y chap with long hair and beard.</p>

<p>The style he is most associated with is the one he started with his classic trio of solo albums on RCA: [a]Heaven and Hell[/a], [a]Albedo 0.39[/a] and [a]Spiral[/a], and it defies categorisation. Of course you can just go the easy way and call it "electronic", but even though you can see dozens of pictures of him literally <em>surrounded</em> on all four sides by more than a dozen keyboards, only sometimes does he dare to make his sound totally electronic: he relies on sounds of "real" instruments, even when they are completely sampled. Fact is, Vangelis's music is a unique blend of influences and styles, drawing as much from classical music and jazz as it does from rock and whatever else Vangelis felt like being influenced by.</p>

<p>The nasty thing about the guy is that his discography, particularly in the 70's, can be an absolute nightmare. If you want to have all the CDs and LP's, well, good luck finding some of those super rare puppies. Either you have a wad of money <em>and</em> time to look out for those, or you look for some... alternative means. It also depends on how seriously you are into Vangelis: some of his most obscure items are just not worth getting unless you are a huge fan. His best records, in general, are easy to find. It can definitely be fun to dig into his more obscure catalogue if you have the means, though. The man is an amazing musician, and you <em>must</em> own at least his most important releases. If you're <em>really</em> unsure, just get [a]Heaven and Hell[/a] or [a]Spiral[/a] and decide for yourself.</p>]]></text>
    <album ref="power">
      <title>Sex Power</title>
      <year>1970</year>
      <high-points>I... don't think I have much of a choice here.</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>1ère partie</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>2ième partie</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Vangelis's first solo record is surely a strange and funny item, but only in what regards the things around it. Firstly, the title! Who on Earth would imagine that the debut of super-renowned Greek composer and keyboardist Vangelis is called not "[a]Heaven and Hell[/a]", but... "[a]Sex Power[/a]"? But worry not, folks, everything is perfectly explainable. This record is actually the soundtrack to the homonymous underground French film, directed by Henry Chapier and released in 1970. It used to be pretty much <em>impossible</em> to find, but it seems you can finally watch an extract of it in <a href="http://www.ina.fr/art-et-culture/cinema/video/VDD08000001/sex-power.fr.html">this link here!</a>. It is NOT, however, a pornographic film.</p>

<p>Vangelis's respective soundtrack album became about as obscure as the film itself, and it was only officially issued in vinyl by Philips, in 1970 (an issue which, as you can guess, is extremely rare). Therefore, any digital copy you obtain of it comes from vinyl transfers, and yeah, any CD of it being released is a bootleg. It's a mystery why Vangelis overlooks this record, as well as MANY of his early and unofficial releases, but that's how life goes. The fact is that, even though this is nowhere near a masterpiece, it is a surprisingly solid release by Vangelis, and a very important "missing link" on his transition between his Aphrodite's Child days (which were yet to end, as [a]666[/a] was released one year later) and his glorious "mainstream" output from 1975 onwards. Every fan needs this in his collection.</p>

<p>Don't be shied away or embarrassed by the title, then &mdash; you can label the MP3 files as "Soundtrack to some Obscure French Film" and it will work anyway. Problem is, the album title is basically the ONLY title you can work with here! Even though the songs were indexed as separate tracks on the LP, the label only identified side A (premi&egrave;re partie) and side B (deuxi&egrave;me partie), and the only place where you can gather some track titles are from an even more insanely obscure and rare 7&Prime; single (yes! They released a <em>single</em> out of this!!), and there we learn that the second song here is called [s]Djemilla[/s] and the fifth is [s]Third Love[/s]. That's IT, buddy. Now you see the position I'm in here??</p>

<p>But I carry on. Have I said this is not the soundtrack to a porn film? Well, the music sounds nothing like you would expect from a porn film, I assure you. The style ranges from very mellow and gentle balladeering played mainly on acoustic instruments, with just passing tinges of very rudimentary synthesizers and maybe a Mellotron, passing through some tracks with intriguing middle eastern influences, and ending on some freaked out experimental work-outs. The opening of the recrd, for example, is less than half a minute long and has fast, chopped organ chords countered by freakishly loud metallic screeching noises. Track 2 on side B is &mdash; gasp! &mdash; eight minutes long and is mostly an improvisation for various percussion sounds. It's not even a "drum solo", and more like a collage. I guess it worked well as film background, but on its own, it just meanders without much direction. And Vangelis would grow really fond of this stuff! Track 4 on side B, however, is <em>freaky as hell</em>, with a nightmarish background of metallic noises and an anguished falsetto vocal (probably Vangelis's bandmate Demis Roussos) singing a haunting melody. Eventually the metallic nightmare gives way to just an organ drone and the voice. Wow, creepy stuff.</p>

<p>But the melodic side is VERY rich in this record; thankfully, the meandering experimentation is kept to a (relative) minumum. The so called [s]Djemilla[/s], which is the second track on side A, introduces a gloriously beautiful theme with eastern rhythm and percussions, featuring Vangelis on piano and a choir singing wordless vocals. It's a simple, short phrase repeated through the track, but there's enough variation in the arrangements to keep it interesting and beautiful all the way through. The following track introduces a gentle waltz-like melody &mdash; played here on solo acoustic guitar over strange motorbike sounds &mdash; which seems to be the main theme of the film and reappears many more times in the album; in FIVE tracks, to be exact. The most full-blown arrangement is in track 5 ([s]Third Love[/s]), with Vangelis on what sounds like an immitation of a harpsichord, and the strangest arrangement is track 3 on side B, with what sounds like a very buzzy monophonic synthesizer playing the melody and assorted percussion effects "inherited" from the track before it. The two side closers are just solo piano pieces &mdash; track 6 having just the chords, closed off with a strange collage of sound effects.</p>

<p>I'm also fond of the eastern pieces here. The opener of side 2, in particular, is short and sweet, featuring a very pretty melody for woodwinds... or whistles, or whatever that thing is. Track 4 is more focused on rhythm, and has Vangelis banging out a fun groove on timpani. You could say that, in spite of featuring the same song five times, the album is fairly varied. It certainly is an oddity in Vangelis's oeuvre, and it's worth listening to &mdash; if only at least once. Check it out, if you will.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]Comment[/l]... if you DARE! Mwahahahaha.</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="nuit">
      <title>Fais que ton rêve soit plus long que la nuit</title>
      <year>1972</year>
      <high-points>It doesn't really apply here.</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Part 2</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>If Vangelis's debut was weird, check THIS one out! This record is not a soundtrack. In fact, it's something stranger: the cover refers to it as a <em>po&egrave;me symphonique</em> &mdash; a "symphonic poem". What exactly that is, I don't know, but it defitely sounds FAR from what "symphonic" traditionally means.</p>

<p>To speak in brief terms, the album is a collage of music, played by Vangelis on piano and a few other players, among them a violinist, as well as a choir of assorted people acquainted to Vangelis, field recordings and sound effects. The whole thing lasts a little more than 30 minutes long. It's all in French. Am I puzzling you already? Okay, let's contextualise it: Vangelis recorded this album as a sort of "tone poem" about the demonstrations and riots that took over Paris in 1968. Vangelis, along with Aphrodite's Child, were there at the time, so they DID experience plenty of it. So, those "field recordings" you hear are protesters and students, captured on tape during the time of the demonstrations; the "sound effects" are there to evoke the sounds of rioting and fighting &mdash; not as if the police were shooting tear gas at the students right there in your face, but as if it were playing like a film inside your mind; and the music consists of traditional tunes and pieces written around poems that were found in graffiti around that time. The title stands for "Let your dreams last longer than the night". So, there is a context for everything.</p>

<p>And is it evocative? Is it beautiful? I have to say, <em>yes, it is</em>. Vangelis isn't trying to be challenging or difficult of avant-garde here &mdash; on the contrary! Considering the format of the album, it's surprisingly listenable and accessible. The "collage" bits never get in your nerves, and the music bits at times become quite poignant. In many places you can already hear Vangelis learning to exercise that stately, majestic beauty he would perfect in the upcoming years. It's an interesting listen, and if you're in the mood for something different, it's worthwhile giving this one a try.</p>

<p>While it's difficult to consider this album as an album of songs, it's not fair to dismiss it as some "experimentation" or something derisive like that: this <em>is</em> a work of art, and it <em>is</em> a piece of music. What helps Vangelis's case considerably here is that this work is much more emotional than intellectual: this was made as a homage from someone who <em>felt</em> the whole thing going on, not as a "meaningful" masterwork of someone who's trying to rationalise it. After all, trying to "rationalise" through 30 minutes of avant-garde is cumbersome enough; leave the intellectuality to the folks who know how to make it appealing! So, I am not ready to dismiss this album and cast it into the dustbins of oblivion. The point is: I don't recommend this to anyone <em>but</em> those who are really into Vangelis, <em>or</em> for people who want to break away from the norm a little. It's wise to know a bit of the history beforehand <em>and</em> have a way to at least try to understand some of the words (not the field recordings, though &mdash; you don't need to be fluent in French), otherwise you might be under the impression that this is just a random heap of stuff. It is not. BUT don't put your hands on this LP if you're not fully sure what awaits your here. And don't throw it away in disgust; if anything, it's short.</p>

<p>Ah! It seems this album was released in CD only in a limited release in Greece. Other than that, it's only available on LP and in digital vinyl transfers. You'll have to either get a bootleg or listen on Grooveshark or something. Some packages include "bonus tracks" that are actually Aphrodite Child songs. The full album is just the two 15-minute-long tracks. And there are no "track titles": some sites list a few titles, but those are actually the verses of poems that got transformed into songs in the album, and were printed in the back of some LP issues.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>8</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Let your [l]comments[/l] be longer than the review</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="animaux">
      <title>L'apocalypse des animaux</title>
      <year>1973</year>
      <high-points>[s]La Petite Fille de la Mer[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Générique</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>La Petite Fille de la Mer</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Le Singe Bleu</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>La Mort du Loup</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>L'Ours Musicien</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Création du Monde</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>La Mer Recomencée</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Thankfully Vangelis's albums are becoming more "normal". You want some historical curiosity? Even though this record is still fairly obscure, it attracted the attention of Jon Anderson of Yes. This was effectively the beginning of their partnership, though the first Jon &amp; Vangelis album came out in 1979, and the partnership would last for many years &mdash; until Jon put out some recordings without Vangelis's consent and the partnership fell apart. Way to go, Jonny.</p>

<p>As for this record, it's another soundtrack. This time, it's for an obscure nature themed TV series. No, it's not a Canadian production, so no Boards of Canada connections here (unfortunately!). <em>L'apocalypse des animaux</em> (The Animals' Apocalypse) was directed by Fr&eacute;d&eacute;ric Rossif, and Vangelis was commissioned to do the soundtrack. The story for this soundtrack is radically different from what you'll hear about the far more successful soundtracks he would later do; instead of composing for the film, he just recorded some pieces and offered them to the filmmakers. These songs were actually recorded in 1971, making them almost contemporanous with [a]Sex Power[/a]! The album was compiled only after the series came out, and it seems Vangelis didn't participate in that process &mdash; not even the song titles were chosen by him, as they are closely related to the events they follow on screen, and Vangelis recorded the track without access to the videos, as they probably weren't even made back then.</p>

<p>The music you'll hear here is already quite different from the stuff we've been hearing so far: our Mr. Papathanassiou is flirting with things that would later on morph into "New Age", "Ambient", "Chill Out" or whatever you call that. Yeah, the music here is very peaceful and calming. Surprising indeed! Among other things, Vangelis plays here an electric piano that would eventually become a "trademark" of his. I can't confirm if it's the SAME piano, but it sounds damn similar. Pretty much every song is slow and peaceful, and there are even some jazzy overtones in a few tracks. Check out the trumpet playing in [s]Le Singe Bleu[/s], for example! The song structure is actually quite orthodox, having a main theme and some more free-form parts. Below the trumpet, you hear mostly Vangelis on the electric piano. It's a very calming and long song. Also we have a <em>very</em> short extract of [s]L'Ours Musicien[/s], in which we hear Vangelis playing around with some humourous ideas on electric piano and a monophonic synthesizer. I don't know why they selected a <em>one minute long</em> extract of the song, as it was originally much longer, but then again, there is MUCH music on the film that wasn't released on the record. If you want to hear a bit of it, including a different cut of [s]L'Ours Musicien[/s], check out <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WFtaqkX161U">this YouTube link</a>. And the full first episode of the series is <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jj3VZ8hhce0">here</a>. No need to thank me &mdash; thank the guys who posted it.</p>

<p>The only bit in the album that doesn't fall in that category is the first track, the theme of the TV series, a playful little tune with a very simple circular motif played on marimbas. A kind of "fan favourite" in here is the gorgeous [s]La Petite Fille de la Mer[/s], a piece played mainly on electric piano, but with many other embellishments and ambiences added to it. The main theme explored in the song is wonderful, and it's a great place to witness Vangelis flexing his compositional muscles. Brilliant. [s]La Mort du Loup[/s] is shorter and more melancholy (in the film, it followed scenes of hunters killing wolves), and features some guitar parts. It has a main theme as well, but instead of being developed like in the two previous tracks, it is just stated very slowly and sparsely. Consider that a bit of variety.</p>

<p>Side two, then, brings us the more "ambient" side of Vangelis, if you could call it that. I always have strong reservations against using the word "ambient" in songs like this; Brian Eno coined that term not in relation to what the music sounds like, but to its <em>purpose</em>, you see? Both of these tracks here are not meant as "furniture" music, but yes, they are already very much in line with the stuff Eno would put out in a few years. But Vangelis wasn't the only guy exploring these parts, anyway, so let's let it rest. [s]Cr&eacute;ation du Monde[/s] is particularly beautiful, made only with some string-like drones and ambience layers, with some little droplets of melody here and there. For the most part, the song is <em>very</em> meditative, and Vangelis throws a few disturbing dissonances near the end, but it actually sounds like part of the mood, not like a radical break. [s]La Mer Recomenc&eacute;e[/s] is similar, but less drone-like and featuring a few "developments" along the way.</p>

<p>Fact is, for a moderate Vangelis fan, this is already a great place to start. This record was unusually successful and is available in many CD issues, so you won't have to hunt out some obscure LP or some MP3 vinyl transfers in order to enjoy it. Even though this is still "early Vangelis", it already points the way towards some of his later music. It's certainly recommended, but don't expect and Earth-shattering classic from it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]Envoyer vos commentaires, s'il vous pla&icirc;t.[/l]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="earth">
      <title>Earth</title>
      <year>1973</year>
      <high-points>[s]Let It Happen[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Come On</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>We Were All Uprooted</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Sunny Earth</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>He-O</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ritual</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Let It Happen</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The City</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>My Face in the Rain</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>A Song</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Apparently we aren't yet ready to move on to the "normal" Vangelis records, so we still have to get to weird stuff like this! [a]Earth[/a] is, as if we haven't had enough, a quite unusual album. On the very, very surface, you could call this a <em>rock</em> album. Vangelis is backed by many musicians, some of them being old collaborators and people linked to Aphrodite's Child (as well as lead singer and bassist Robert Fitoussi, who would in the 80's become F. R. David and put out songs like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cll4uCLtDcg">Words</a> &mdash; I was SHOCKED to discover that, as this song was very familiar to me from my childhood), so this is an entirely different matter. But if you can call it "rock" on surface, below the surface there is a lot of non-rock stuff. The album is, actually, much more aligned to ancient Mediterranean music, with local instruments, earthly chanting and lots of percussive rhythms. But it <em>does</em> open with the wild rock 'n' roll call to arms of [s]Come On[/s]. It even has an ass-kicking power chord riff! It certainly is a fun starter, even if you want to make fun of the fact that the song title is the only lyric you'll hear on the song, but who cares?? There are much worse things we could hear than "Come on! Come on! Come on come on come on come on come on come on come on come on come on!", and if you don't agree, you need to hear more music.</p>

<p>To tell you the truth, I really like the effect that [s]Come On[/s] has on the album: it's like Vangelis is inviting you to take the more "ancient" songs not as some bizarre, "out there" music, but as something to take with your heart and with your body. Maybe I'm just making up crap, but it is nice to see it as that. As for what comes next, you definitely won't get more of those wailing guitar solos and bitchin' riffs. Already from the second track, you'll hear what this album sounds more like: [s]We Were All Uprooted[/s] is a lengthy, monotonous piece of ancient-like music with a brief bit of poetry reading. That song pretty much sets the tone for other tracks, such as [s]Sunny Earth[/s]: the strange vocalisations serve as an intro to a sort of freeform instrumental tune, that later turns into a fast, rhythmic dance. Other tracks are even more adventurous, such as [s]Ritual[/s], with its ominous chanting. Other songs, however, feature some quite poppy and cachy vocal melodies! [s]Let It Happen[/s] is the clearest example, featuring a jangly guitar rhythm and sing-alongey melodies. [s]He-O[/s], which wasn't written by Vangelis, sounds like a Greek folk song, while [s]My Face in the Rain[/s] is an airy, atmospheric ballad, carried much more by Vangelis's array of keyboards than by traditional instruments.</p>

<p>Of course, this IS a Vangelis record (or, to be more precise, a Vangelis O. Papathanassiou record), so there's no way the keyboards could be left off it. There doesn't seem to be, though, a huge effort in combining the modern sounds with the ancient influences. The album isn't really "experimental", you see. The atmospherics return on the closing [s]A Song[/s], with some more poetry reading, closing the album in a way completely opposite to the beginning. Anyway, all things considered, this record falls uncomfortably neatly in the dumpster that people nowadays tend to quickly label as "world music", which <em>sucks</em>. But worry not! You can still fish out this record and treasure it for all its worth; after all, it is a... well, it <em>is</em> an extremely solid offering, but it doesn't have anything going on in it to make it a classic or something. But it is about as worth having as [a]L'Apocalypse des Animaux[/a], only it is much harder to find. It was issued on CD only in Greece, so unless you have money for an expensive import or you have some acquaintances living in Greece, you'll have to hunt for a copy around the Interwebs or look for a vinyl copy or a CD bootleg. If you don't have patience for that kind of stuff, don't bother, but if you <em>do</em>, you'll certainly end up having much more than a merely "weird" Vangelis release. It is good, that is for sure.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Come on! Come on! Come on come on come on come on come on come on come on come on [l]come on[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="hell">
      <title>Heaven and Hell</title>
      <year>1975</year>
      <high-points>Movement 3 of [s]Symphony to the Powers B[/s], [s]So Long Ago, So Clear[/s], [s]12 o'Clock[/s], [s]Bacchanale[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Heaven and Hell, part 1</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>5</grade> <title>Bacchanale</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>4</grade> <title>Symphony to the Powers B, movements 1 and 2</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>5</grade> <title>Symphony to the Powers B, movement 3</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>5</grade> <title>So Long Ago, So Clear</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Heaven and Hell, part 2</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>3</grade> <title>Intestinal Bat</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>4</grade> <title>Needles and Bones</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>5</grade> <title>12 o'Clock</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>5</grade> <title>Aries</title></track>
            <track level="2"><grade>4</grade> <title>A Way</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Great things happened for our big bearded Greek dude: having secured a record deal with RCA records, he was finally free to release his first big solo effort in what would soon become his very own recording studio: [a]Heaven and Hell[/a] is the first record ever made in Nemo Studios, in London, and is probably his first record not released under the unwieldy name Vangelis Papathanassiou &mdash; from now on Vangelis does just fine, thank you.</p>

<p>Certainly he realised this was going to be his big moment, so he assembled all his composition, arrangement and production powers to produce his first classic. It's easy to see how he succeeded, as he already had years of practice, and writing music was nothing new to him (consider the TONS of music he wrote but never released officially, including film soundtracks that never saw a proper LP release). [a]Heaven and Hell[/a] is mostly entirely instrumental, featuring merely some nonsense vocals and wordless chants by the English Chamber Choir and female vocalist Vana Veroutis. It also doesn't really have track titles: in most issues, the sides were just labelled as Part 1 and Part 2, though there <em>are</em> proper titles to these pieces, and I'll make it clear which title relates to each part, don't worry. The only "song" that stands out from the whole album is the first collaboration with Jon Anderson, which was included at the end of side one as a kind of "bonus"; however, the song fits in <em>perfectly</em> with the overall mood and theme of the album. [s]So Long Ago, So Clear[/s] is an airy, very gentle tune with a memorable melody and a beautiful work by Jon Anderson on the vocals and lyrics. The instrumental break is something out of this world, however: it's painfully clear that Vangelis was trying to reach a whole new level of orchestration and layering of his many keyboard pieces. The sonic texture and the orchestration of the many different parts is stunning, and as it should be obvious by now, Vangelis doesn't do it only to show off. The music here is jaw-droppingly gorgeous, and the combination of Vangelis and Jon's songcraft is supreme.</p>

<p>Vangelis's solo work, however, doesn't come even <em>close</em> to falling behind. There isn't a single moment in which the album lets go. From the very opening, the album is determined to be a classic: [s]Bacchanale[/s] opens with a solemn, stately theme played on a synthesizer and soon followed by the choir. After this statement, though, the song explodes into a hell of a jazzy groove with a complex, twisty melody played on the synth, with Vangelis continously adding some breakneck fast embellishments on electric piano. The whole thing is played twice, and clears the path to the lengthy [s]Symphony to the Powers B[/s], the moment when Vangelis really tries to make his huge array of keyboards and percussion into a little orchestra. It <em>seems</em> to be a 3 movement piece, but the first two are quite similar and follow without a break. The first is centered around some very monotonous, plodding rhythmic patterns, in which the choir sings some pseudo-Latin nonsense words. I guess Vangelis is trying to make it sound like a solemn religious ceremony. Then, the music turns more "upbeat", with many exhultant, jubilant moments flowing from each other. During the whole piece, Vangelis has a firm grip on dynamics: the music goes from climax to climax, passing through complex passages for solo piano and whatnot. The thing is, even though the whole thing is quite bombastic, he keeps your attention the whole time. The third movement, then, breaks the flow with a soothing, mellow passage for solo piano, which is slowly joined by electronic synths and then... well, suffice to say, if you remember Carl Sagan's TV series <em>Cosmos</em>, well, THIS is the "theme tune" of the series. And it is so beautiful that it gives me shivers. There is this <em>moment</em> in which the little piano intro ends and he switches into the looping pattern that makes the bulk of the song: just that little transition is enough to make my spine tingle. From then on, the choir and the numerous synth layers start coming in one by one (including a little buzzy "trumpet" sound playing a tune that sounds eerily like a proto-<em>Chariots of Fire</em> theme!), until he switches the key and the whole thing takes off into a grandiose climax. Bombastic? Maybe. But maybe not: come to think of it, a "build-up and climax" thing like this is not miles away from what Mike Oldfield did on side A of [a]Tubular Bells[/a], right? And nobody complains about that one being "bombastic". Same thing here: this is masterful songcraft, not just pomposity for its own sake.</p>

<p>Side B is the creepy part of the album. The first few minutes, a portion called [s]Intestinal Bat[/s], is a free form percussive thing the likes of which Vangelis has already done before. It's particularly interesting here because it is framed as an integral part of the whole composition. And it's short and does its job well, setting a great atmosphere. It is followed by [s]Needles and Bones[/s], with a kind of bouncy melody played on what sounds like a synthesized immitation of marimbas. Hell, this tune actually sounds a bit humourous! In general, this shows very well Vangelis' skill of taking a very simple theme and repeating it multiple times, but always adding something different and interesting each time. The centrepiece here, though, is the eight minute long [s]12 o'Clock[/s]. It stards off with a really disturbing, dissonant march with thunderous tympani and a shrieking synthesizer. Then, it melts away into a beautiful, dirge-like melody sung by the choir and by Vana Veroutis. It's almost like the "dark" counterpart of [s]So Long Ago, So Clear[/s], except without lyrics. The final minutes of the album are occupied by the triumphant march [s]Aries[/s], which to me sounds like a raging battle between Heaven and Hell, and its conclusion is the "ambient", tranquil [s]A Way[/s], which depicts the victory of good over evil.</p>

<p>It's not hard to see why this is one of Vangelis's biggest classics, if not THE biggest one. You can think of it as his own [a]Tubular Bells[/a], and in terms of quality, both albums are really close. This is, in all respects, a classic indeed, and a necessary addition to your collection, even if you're only mildly interested in 70's progressive-instrumental-electronic music. It's also one of his most accessible records, so make sure not to miss it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>13</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Now [l]send your comments[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="aboyer">
      <title>Entends-Tu les Chiens Aboyer?</title>
      <year>1975</year>
      <high-points>Now I'm clueless!</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Entends-Tu les Chiens Aboyer? part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Entends-Tu les Chiens Aboyer? part 2</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>In case you haven't had enough of soundtracks to obscure French films, here's another one for ya! Actually, this isn't a French film; it was directed by Fran&ccedil;ois Reichenbach, but it's a Mexican production called <em>&iquest;No Oyes Ladrar los Perros?</em> (Can You Hear the Dogs Barking?). The album, though, was released with the French title, and is nowadays also released as [a]Ignacio[/a]. Unlike in [a]L'Apocalypse des Animaux[/a], Vangelis wrote the music specifically for the film; and also unlike that record, we are back to unlabelled and unindexed tracks! Even in CD issues, the most you get are the two sides on two different tracks, but in many issues, it's just a single track! And, again, no titles anywhere in sight.</p>

<p>This is, however, a "proper" Vangelis record, in the sense that it isn't just some cuts from the film slapped on a record. Vangelis likes having a firm control on his soundtrack albums, and many times the albums do not mirror exactly the music you hear on the film &mdash; he changes and tinkers the recordings until he sees them fit for an album release. But I'm not here to make comparisons, I'm not that much of an addict! I'm here to talk about the album. Along the two sides, Vangelis spreads six tracks, one of them being a recapitulation of a previous track. This happens in side 1, which is bookended by a slow, meditative, melancholy melody. First it is played just by Vangelis on his keyboards, electric pianos, celestas, glockenspiels and whatnot. It is a beautiful, beautiful song, and, believe it or not, it has a "personal significance" for me: long before I even knew of Vangelis, this piece was familiar to me, as well as many fellow Brazilian folks. It was used by a local TV network as soundtrack to a vignette depicting Jesus and a God-like voiceover threatening the poor viewers who were not doing acts of goodness, like the host of the program, who is incidentally the owner of the TV network. It was a program in which people sent in letters asking for wishes, and the host would select some letters and try to grant their wishes. At the end, you would get <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kmHXAUddxbw">THIS UNBELIEVABLY CREEPY</a> vignette. Even though it is in Portuguese, you can get an idea of how scary it is. In spite of that unhappy connection, the song is just beyond beautiful, and is a minor favourite of mine. It reappears at the end of the side, after a dramatic, heavy prelude played on a church organ, and followed by a choir.</p>

<p>The middle portion of the side is taken by a single, very long composition. Even though it doesn't have the "symphonic" pretentions of [a]Heaven and Hell[/a], it again showcases Vangelis' skill in developing themes and fleshing out a composition. It is very dramatic and solemn sounding, and alternates moments of heavy percussion pounding and synth stabs with more melodic, sweeping themes. It's a surprisingly solid, developed composition, and it wouldn't be unwelcome in a non-soundtrack album, that's for sure! Side A of this record, I can say, is a very neat, complete package. Side B brings quite a couple of surprises, though. The three tracks in here are completely different from each other, and the first one is the closest thing to "electronic rock 'n' roll" that Vangelis ever did, I guess: a pulsating synth gives the base to a frenzied improvisation, with some crazy soloing on a synth and percussion sounds sprayed all over the track. The next track, however, is an "experimental", nightmarish piece featuring, for the most part, percussion hits and blasts. I have to say, the "scary" factor of this track is quite surprisingly big &mdash; this isn't just Vangelis dicking around with percussion, but seriously trying to create a mood. Towards the end it becomes more atmospheric and synth laden, feturing even a theremin. It certainly won't please much the folks who like Vangelis's most melodic side, but don't get too scared yet: his "experimental" side was yet to give its wildest fruits. The final track is a full-blown rendition of a melody quoted on the middle of side A, and it has a breezy atmosphere with marimbas and an organ beatbox. An odd closer, but still beautiful and nice.</p>

<p>As a final veredict, I'll say that this album is half an great album, half an interesting curiosity. For a fan, it's probably that <em>both</em> things are desirable, so you'd better evaluate what exactly you are. This ain't a classic at all, but you can't simply discard the stretches of good music to be found here. Definitely give it a listen.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Can you hear the [l]readers commenting[/l]?</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="albedo">
      <title>Albedo 0.39</title>
      <year>1976</year>
      <high-points>[s]Pulstar[/s], [s]Alpha[/s], [s]Main Sequence[/s], [s]Sword of Orion[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Pulstar</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Freefall</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Mare Tranquilitatis</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Main Sequence</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Sword of Orion</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Alpha</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Nucleogenesis, part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Nucleogenesis, part 2</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Albedo 0.39</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Continuing his work on his full fledged Nemo Studios, Vangelis set out to record his second "full solo" album. Having proper track titles, [a]Albedo 0.39[/a] shifts away from the spiritual and religious thematics of [a]Heaven and Hell[/a] and focuses on science. Not only the track titles make lots of references to astronomy, but the sound and arrangements go for a more abstract, purely electronic approach. There are still the emulation of orchestral instruments, but they are woven together with the purely electronic sounds of the many, many keyboards, organs and synthesizers Vangelis commonly uses. The result of all that is simply the best Vangelis record of all time.</p>

<p>Not that I am rejecting contrary opinions, of course! You know I'm totally a nice guy.</p>

<p>Sometimes, at least. Sometimes I am a real asshole.</p>

<p>But this album? You'd have to be a real asshole to deny that it is an unabashed classic. You may dislike the guts out of it, but Vangelis's achievements in terms of arrangement, production and performance here are virtually without precedents. As usual, he performs basically all instruments here, and this includes more than simple keyboards: you get a very fair share of drumkit bashing, as well as tasteful gamelans and glockenspiels and whatnot. No guitars, though, as far as I am aware. But who cares about guitars? These tracks are all absurdly amazing. The trumpet immitating synth is heavily used here, as is that dreamy, swirly sound he takes out of his electric piano, but all over the album the man creates this thick, complex fabric of sound that should effectively shut the mouth of those philistines who say that electronic music has no "soul" and no "emotion". True, this album isn't 100% electronic, but the real triumph of the record is in the use of synthesizers and keyboards. And, oh yes, the songs.</p>

<p>The songs! For starters, there are two tracks here that became immortal for Vangelis &mdash; not as immortal as the <em>Chariots of Fire</em> theme, but pretty close. [s]Pulstar[/s] is built out of a fast, one-note synthesizer pulse and a terrific melody that is constructed, reconstructed and deconstructed in as many ways as you could imagine. What drives me wild, though, are those syncopated, fierce synth stabs and percussion hits: Vangelis really creates the feeling that there is something beyond all belief and all imagination happening right before you, in the shape of a majestic phenomenon that's constantly, endlessly unfolding. The mood is maintained all the way through, from climax to climax, right to the exciting, almost chaotic crescendo at the end that suddenly slams against a brick wall and dissolves into the recording of a talking clock. Who would have guessed! The second classic is [s]Alpha[/s], which also became famous after its heavy use in Carl Sagan's <em>Cosmos</em>: also built on an unbelievably simple five note melody, it grows out of a very sparse synthesized atmosphere evoking emptiness and darkness, adding layer over layer until a huge, symphonic celebration with some thundering drums and an immitation of brasses, culminating in a left turn towards an even more grandiose and majestic finale which, again, is cut short by a booming, reticent chord. It probably sounds a lot less amazing on paper than it does in pure sound.</p>

<p>Aside from these two, however, there is much, much more brilliance in this record. Side A, for example, features a "mini suite" that goes from the short, tinkling, meandering [s]Freefall[/s], featuring a repetitive, start-and-stop figure played on gamelans and followed by many synth layers, that segu&eacute;s into the slightly disturbing "ambient" piece [s]Mare Tranquilitatis[/s], alluding to the Apollo missions (even including actual recordings from moon landings), which is very dissonant and eerie. <em>Then</em>, it leads straight into the epic jazz/electronic work-out of [s]Main Sequence[/s], featuring a thick layer of syncopated, complicated drumming, crazy, bopping and pulsating synthesized tones and wheezing chords. It sounds clearly here that Vangelis got the synth parts first and <em>then</em> added the drumming, and his attempt at following the dozens of left turns and rhythmic breaks makes the whole ride even more exciting and unpreditable. Over that, he lays his keyboard soloing on his famous, expressive "trumpet" sound. Amazingly, the piece just never loses steam, and only at the end does it slow down towards a more peaceful, meandering, melodic pace, which serves mostly as a prelude to the extremely beautiful, tear inducing [s]Sword of Orion[/s], a short, side-closing piece with some of the most touching and sensitive playing in Vangelis's career so far. Who said science couldn't be touching?</p>

<p>Side B reveals to us the two-part [s]Nucleogenesis[/s], also built on a steadily pulsating rhythm. Instead of building steadily towards a grandiose climax, the first part is another of those rollercoaster rides over many ups and downs, sudden curves and breaks, massive percussion hits, unpredictable chord changes, dramatic breaks and majestic pauses, synth-trumpet soloing and ever other trick Vangelis can find. The ending leaves us suspended, ready to get into the drum-driven bluesy ride of part two, with more of those endless twists and turns and tensions and releases. Just when it seems ready to dissolve, sounds of phone dialing interrupt the music and launch into a big, victorious climax, with some of the most impressive orchestra immitations to ever come out of the 70's. It definitely is quite an accomplishment. The title track closes off the album in a peaceful, gentle synth meandering, but with actual progression and development, over wich the sound engineer Keith Spencer-Allen reads out data about the planet Earth, culminating in a strangely satisfying and cathartic reading of "albedo: 0.39". I have no idea why this particular information was chosen as the album's big conclusion, as well as its title, but the effect is somehow convincing. These four minutes don't feel <em>at all</em> like a dragged-out ending or wasted time &mdash; on the contrary, it gives a heartfelt ending to an album that is chockful of experiences and thrill rides. It's hard for me to control myself, because this album <em>really</em> grips me, and is one of my favourite pieces of electronic &mdash; or, more specifically, "semi-electronic" &mdash; music of all time. [a]Equinoxe[/a]? [a]X[/a]? [a]Trans-Europa Express[/a]? [a]Selected Ambient Works, volume II[/a]? [a]Oversteps[/a]? [a]Albedo 0.39[/a] is, to certain extent, the granddaddy of them all, and after all those years, it's still relevant and inspirational. Don't miss this album, for all that is sacred: even if it leaves no impression in you, you <em>need</em> to experience it at least once. And unless you hate it with all your passion, keep trying it: maybe someday you'll grow fond of it as much as I did.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>15</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Now [l]you send your comments[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="sauvage">
      <title>La Fête Sauvage</title>
      <year>1976</year>
      <high-points>I'll pass this one too.</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>La Fête Sauvage, part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>La Fête Sauvage, part 2</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Vangelis just isn't Vangelis without a soundtrack album every year, right? Fortunately, unless I'm terribly mistaken, this shall be the <em>last</em> instance of me being completely out of track titles and indexes. This soundtrack was commissioned for a wildlife film directed by the same maker of <em>L'Apocalypse des Animaux</em>. As you can see, though, this was not a matter of Vangelis giving away some pieces he had laying around. Instead, he wrote the music specifically for the film, and here we have with yet another pair of long tracks simply titled [s]La F&ecirc;te Sauvage[/s] &mdash; and, in some issues, <em>a single track</em>.</p>

<p>The music is miles away from that of [a]L'Apocalypse des Animaux[/a]. Even the main theme is different: instead of a circular little tune played on marimbas, we have a massive upbeat romp with african drums and a pair of synth melodies that are quite uplifting. Excellent way to start a "Savage Party", I say! These few introductory minutes are a highlight in the album, and may be a total shock for people less initiated in Vangelis's oddities: what, an <em>African rhythm</em>? Yes, indeed! And that African vibe lasts for the whole side: there is a lot of aboryginal chanting and drumming here, though for the rest of the side, we never reach the level of energy of that little opening tune. You know, I have mentioned that [a]Earth[/a] was very close to what people call "World Music" today, but this music fits <em>exactly</em> the stereotype of "World Music" perpetrated by the likes of Peter Gabriel: distant, exotic sounds from the jungle countered by studio technology and synthesized soundscapes. Of course, in 1976, this stuff was nowhere as commonplace. It wasn't revolutionary, though, and you can't say Vangelis was inventing something totally new here, but it would be foolish to put down this first half of the album for being "World Music New Age crap" or something. Thing is, it's not terribly exciting: it sounds way too sanitised to satisfy any interest in actual African music, and it sounds too alien to truly mesh in with the music as extraordinarily well as, say, Mike Oldfield had done in [a]Ommadawn[/a], and was yet to do in [a]Incantations[/a]. As a soundtrack, yeah, it may work, but as music on its own, it doesn't cause a strong impression in me at all. It is <em>pleasant</em>, but when it comes to Vangelis, that isn't really something to be too excited about.</p>

<p>The second side breaks radically from the first and embarks on the more melodic and atmospheric side of Vangelis. The first nine minutes of this side or so consist of a single composition that is elsewhere titled as [s]Theme d'Amour[/s], and THIS is definitely gorgeous stuff. The whole composition is bookended by a melody that features the vocal talents of Vana Veroutis, and it brings me close to tears. It is <em>that</em> beautiful, and in terms of "Vangelis giving a musical impression of the Paradise", this is up there with the best moments from [a]Heaven and Hell[/a]. No kidding! The middle portion has those impressive musical developments and we've come to known and love, but I say, even if it were completely bland and boring, that melody on its own would be enough to evelate it. If you need ONE reason to get this record, it's this song. The rest of the side is far less impressive, and gives us nothing surprising in terms of Vangelis, but it doesn't hurt either. This record, overall, is not among my favourites. Pretty much all of his records so far have something <em>interesting</em> going on, and somehow justify their existance. This one... well, the African stuff is more <em>curious</em> than <em>interesting</em>, if you catch my drift. Unless you're really wild about everything African sounding, get it for the opening theme and for the [s]Theme d'Amour[/s].</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]Bring your comments[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="spiral">
      <title>Spiral</title>
      <year>1977</year>
      <high-points>[s]Dervish D[/s], [s]To the Unknown Man[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Spiral</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Ballad</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Dervish D</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>To the Unknown Man</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>3 + 3</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Turns out Vangelis is a real fan of having overarching themes to his records, as this one is themed around... spirals? Yeah, it seems so. But in the end, it doesn't really matter, does it? Okay, so it did matter a bit in [a]Heaven and Hell[/a], and it mattered more than a bit on [a]Albedo 0.39[/a], but this record seems structured a lot more like "a collection of pieces" than a great conceptual whole. And since Vangelis' strength is in making <em>music</em>, not profound philosophic considerations, we're not losing much.</p>

<p>What we have here is another of Vangelis's widely celebrated albums. It's not really a classic, but come on, coming just off the heels of [a]Albedo 0.39[/a], it is a definite challenge to be a classic! What is it for sure, however, is one of his most accessible and immediately engaging albums: the melodies are very upfront here, there isn't any of his wild, uncompromised experimentations, and the long stretches of pure improvisation are pretty much gone. There are lengthy compositions, but they aren't overly complex. They <em>are</em> complex, but not as hard to follow as [s]Main Sequence[/s], for example. Of the tracks here, the catchiest is by far [s]Dervish D[/s], which has a &mdash; gasp! &mdash; <em>12-bar blues structure!</em> The rhythm is also unusually groovy and funky, and the main synth riff on the song is a real pearl of songwriting. It is smartly alternated with some <em>really</em> bluesy solos on Vangelis's oh so beloved synth trumpet sound, and even his soloing is catchy! This is another tune that is closely linked to my childhood memories, as it was the soundtrack to a cheesy short programme aired during commercial breaks to suck the balls of the president. You can watch an example <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=D1dsflt_7vE">here</a>. Can you imagine the shock I felt the first time I heard this song? I don't think you can!</p>

<p>The other tracks go more for the majestic, inspirational vibe of [a]Heaven and Hell[/a] and [s]Alpha[/s], like [s]To the Unknown Man[/s], that builds a big, beautiful anthem over a very memorable, catchy melody. Actually, I like the song because, even though it's big and inspirational, it's not exaggeratedly pompous and is even a little lighthearted, with a marching drum pattern and a lengthy, more subdued coda. Call me cheesy, but this song is a favourite of mine. It's not among the very top of the rank in Vangelis's catalogue (like [s]Dervish D[/s]), but it's high enough to deserve a honourable mention. [s]Ballad[/s], as the name says, is a gentler song, featuring a far more complex and fleshed-out structure, with Vangelis using his own, encoded voice for melody (probably for the first and last time in history &mdash; yes, he sang background vocals on [a]Earth[/a], but it's much harder to hear it precisely). There is a fair chunk of melody here, as well as a bit of meandering improvisation and some climaxes to keep the habit. It might turn a few listeners off because of its length and relative monotony, but give it a try. It's beautiful.</p>

<p>The bookending songs almost fall at extreme ends of the spectrum: the title track with its very dramatic and powerful grip, and [s]3 + 3[/s] with its lighter, more playful mood (and even some lighthearted synth solos!). They are great songs also, and complete the album nicely. One advice I can give you is that if you want to get "slowly" into Vangelis, this album is an excellent place to start. It sums up the friendlier side of his music very nicely, and yet it is an absolutely essential album. Isn't it great when an artist has a "classic" album that is also absolutely accessible? Yep, that is the case here.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]Send some comments[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="hypothesis">
      <title>Hypothesis</title>
      <year>1978</year>
      <high-points>I really have no choice here.</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Hypothesis, part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Hypothesis, part 2</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Now let's talk about an ILLEGAL release? Yeah, baby! We haven't had any of those, but here we are! This LP is a totally illegal, badass, no good unauthorised release of some tapes recorded way back in 1971 when Vangelis assembled some musicians in a London studio and got down to play. The recordings were supposed to be worked further, but after a series of misfortunes and bankrputcies, the original tapes ended (through rather questionable means) in the hands of the owner of one Charly Records, who put out this album, as well as [a]The Dragon[/a] in the same year, without consent or authorisation from Vangelis or any of the musicians involved. As soon as Vangelis heard about it, he filed a lawsuit and successfully took both albums off the shelves. Oddly enough, it's not an extreme ultra rarity, as several copies managed to get out. It's far easier to find than [a]Sex Power[/a] and [a]Fais que ton r&ecirc;ve soit plus long que la nuit[/a], at least. And once again, it was never released on CD, so you'll either find it on vinyl, MP3 copies or in bootleg CDs. But you aren't dumb enough to buy a bootleg CD of this, are you? Get it off the Internet, if you're curious!</p>

<p>But I am not endorsing that activity here, no siree. I'm a totally do good nice guy who follows the law and totally support the labels and greedy record executives getting absurdly rich out of stingy record contracts and the RIAA suing elderly people and underage kids.</p>

<p>So, what about this puppy here? This is a weird album. Yeah, of course, "weird" is nearly meaningless when it comes to early Vangelis records, but this is... this is free-form avant-garde jazz! Vangelis is backed by a violinist (Michel Ripoche), as well as the rhythm section that played on John McLaughin's first solo album [a]Extrapolation[/a] (Brian Odgers on bass and Tony Oxley on drums &mdash; no electric guitar!). It might not mean nothing to have two tracks labelled simply "part 1" and "part 2", as many other Vangelis records have the same "feature" even though they're consisted of different songs, but in this record, we really have two side long tracks that could be considered as two complementary parts of a thing. "Thing"? Yeah, "thing", as I have a hard time thinking of this as a "composition". Pretty much nothing here sounds properly composed or written beforehand &mdash; maybe a few bits were planned, but there is no overall theme, no unifying melody, nothing like that. These are simply musicians jamming along, trying to figure out where to go and what to do next. These are not monotonous, drone-like jams, like the groove-based fusion jazz records that were popping up around this time by the hands of Miles Davis, Chick Corea, John McLaughlin and so on. The band here sounds like they're trying to test everything they could do, every groove and every style they could afford to tackle.</p>

<p>But make no mistake: this is hardcore, atonal avant-garde, and it has <em>nothing</em> to do with the more accessible stuff like [a]L'Apocalypse des Animaux[/a]! Heck, even [a]Fais que ton really hug&ecirc; album titl&eacute; est tr&egrave;s unwieldieux[/a] sounds less experimental and adventurous than this. Mind you, I'm not saying this in a negative sense: there are people who really dig this thing, and heck, <em>I</em> like me some weird and unpredictable stuff too! Why? Do you think I'm some filthy backwards conservative? No, I ain't! But basically, yes, this stuff is very uncompromised and out-there &mdash; the band seems to be constantly searching for a groove to jump on, and once they seem to find something, they jump on it fiercely and solo their sorrows away. The question is whether it's <em>entertaining</em> or not, and personally, I don't think it is. It's not actively offensive and it doesn't annoy the hell out of me while it's on, but I find it hard to actually spend my effort to pay attention to the music. There's no doubt that the musicians are all very capable and extremely professional, and the performances are all top notch. The problem here is exclusively with the fun factor of the music.</p>

<p>Yes, it's quite probable that I do have a problem following this specific kind of music, but... eh, I don't know. I have seriously enjoyed albums of fusion and avant-garde jazz; it's just this one that doesn't cut it. But there's no reason not to recommend it if you're really curious: stuff like this is totally unique in Vangelis's catalogue, and you won't hear this kind of crazy, atonal finger-flashing anywhere else. It's worth listening only for how unusual it is &mdash; ah, and for that totally freaky intro with those ominous, scary chords hammering on your ears. Wow! Creepy.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>8</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[l]Send your hypotheses[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="dragon">
      <title>The Dragon</title>
      <year>1978</year>
      <high-points>[s]The Dragon[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Dragon</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Stuffed Aubergine</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Stuffed Tomato</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Now let's talk about <em>ANOTHER</em> ILLEGAL release? As was said in the review above, this album has the same origin, same history and same faith as [a]Hypothesis[/a]. The difference is that the band is slightly different, and the musical style is <em>very</em> different. And that's only for the better! In these sessions, the band is not completely out in the wild, looking for something to groove along to, but they jump into actual <em>compositions</em>: they have themes, melodies, riffs, chord structures, fixed rhythms and all you got. And they actually <em>rock</em>! The instrumentation and arrangements are far more rock oriented than jazz oriented (there's a guitarist here), and the result here is brutal.</p>

<p>For starters, we have three tracks here. The title track is 15 minutes long and occupies the whole first side. From the get go, it rocks and stomps, based on a slow, heavy rhythm, single droning chord and a mean, no-nonsense violin theme. It never gets old, as the band alternates the repetitive theme with some truly wicked guitar solos. This is seriously brilliant playing, and it sucks that Vangelis and the group were never able to create something finished and official out of this. It's not surprising that they were going to work on this further and that Vangelis wasn't pleased to see this recording go out in this state, as it is very raw and absolutely unpolished; but those characteristics only work in the music's favour here, even if it might not fit the artist's vision. I mean, maybe Vangelis thought these recordings were a complete piece of shit, but does that mean that I have to hold the same opinion? Yes, I have to <em>respect</em> his vision, and I have not the intention to treat this as an official release. But it's been put out! What can I do? Besides, the track <em>is</em> excellent just the way it is. I have to be frank.</p>

<p>The two tracks on side B aren't as weird as their titles suggest; regarding the significance of aubergines and tomatoes, your guess is as good as mine. They are fairly different from the title track, the first being far more downtempo and atmospheric, and the latter being less fierce and a wee bit more jazz oriented. In fact, [s]Stuffed Tomato[/s] starts out with a lengthy solo on a stringed instrument that <em>might</em> be an acoustic guitar but might as well not be, as the sleeve credits nothing but "guitar", and <em>then</em> goes into its main part, that, just like [s]The Dragon[/s], is based around a central melody. It unexpectedly goes off into a super fast break with Vangelis going really wild on the keyboards, which is really, really great. The rest of the song, though, is fairly tame. [s]Stuffed Aubergine[/s] is the only one here that suffers due to its length, because even though they do have some atmosphere going on, it's not really as interesting as it could have been. With further tinkering and some overdubs, it could have been way better, though. One thing I'll say: I'm not crying rivers by the fact that these two records went down the way they did. Yep, it would have been nice if they were released properly, but as much as we have a negative side to such a sneaky release followed by such an abrupt removal, we have the positive side of having a direct, clear, unadulterated view into a world of Vangelis that we just would hardly see otherwise. Yes, I'm talking more about the style of music than about the style of playing: you can say Vangelis is obsessed with planning, calculating and meticulously elaborating his music, but you cannot accuse him of not being spontaneous. Heck, spontaneity is one of his strongest points in relation to other similar musicians! So, yeah, you don't need to listen to these records to hear Vangelis going loose: he <em>is</em> loose and passionate in his regular studio albums as well! Check out [s]Main Sequence[/s] if you doubt it.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Stuffed [l]Comments[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="beaubourg">
      <title>Beaubourg</title>
      <year>1978</year>
      <high-points>Either it's the whole thing or it's none, and frankly, I have no idea.</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Beaubourg, part 1</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Beaubourg, part 2</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>If you think you've heard of Vangelis going "experimental" so far in this page, think again. Even if you were an obsessive Vangelis fan already way back in 1978 and trying to track down every obscure and rare release he put out, NOTHING, absolutely <em>NOTHING</em> could have prepared you for [a]Beaubourg[/a].</p>

<p>The inspiration for the record came from a time when Vangelis lived in the homonymous street, near the Centre Georges Pompidou in Paris, the famous complex that houses all kinds of modern art installations and expositions. This album was recorded when he moved back to London afterwards, and reportedly was done very quickly, in a rush of inspiration. Well, you heard "modern art" there, and that's a good clue as to how experimental and uncompromised this piece sounds: forget about the thick layers of keyboards and synths, the percussion blasts, the transcendental melodies and complex structures. No, don't simply "forget": throw those things in the garbage before you venture here. This piece consists of Vangelis soloing on a single Yamaha CS-80 synthesizer, in which he goes to extreme lengths abusing the ring modulator and other filgering effects. If he used other synths, they are very hard to find; mostly, this is a collage of small fragments of improvisations. Nothing here seems written, there doesn't seem to be <em>any</em> overarching theme or structure, and there is virtually <em>no melody at all</em> here. This is pure sonic experimentation.</p>

<p>It's not true that it is all ugly, dissonant and atonal, as some parts are definitely harmonic, and Vangelis is not aiming for pure and unadulterated <em>ugliness</em>. That doesn't mean it's quite hard on the ears at times and difficult to follow, of course, but this is not a guy randomly poking keys and knobs in his synths: it is the work of an inspired, serious and well-meaning musician who <em>knows what the hell he's doing it</em>, as hard as it is to believe. You'll hear theories that this album was a joke, a rushjob for him to get rid of his contract with RCA, but that is not true: Vangelis himself always showed absolute earnestness in relation to this record, and his trusty engineer Keith Spencer-Allen confirms that this is a honest, serious album.</p>

<p>In one sense, that is bad, because I have the feeling that the artist must always have a slight pinch of lightheartedness, or even humour, when it comes to doing such a massively confrontational work: you <em>know</em> you are breaking every convention there is, and if you go with an absolutely straight face, you're running the risk of collapsing under your own weight. I'm not saying Vangelis was a grumpy and humourless guy, but the album is <em>extremely</em> thick and dense, and therefore hard to swallow. But in another sense, it's good, because you can have the absolute certainty that you're not being put on or ripped off. This is, by all means, <em>music</em>, and you're intended to listen to it as such.</p>

<p>I don't want to sound like a hopeless fanboy, but we're not talking about some pretentious hack showing the world what is "real music": we're talking about goddamn Vangelis, a man who has given more than sufficient proof that he is a talented and brilliant musician. Yes, he is only human, he is infallible and he is capable of making some real garbage as any other human being is, but he is not there to make some quick cash with as little effort as possible. You might despise [a]Beaubourg[/a] with all your might, but I doubt it will make you despise Vangelis as a musician, let alone as a person. You kidding me? The guy is a true gentleman! You can't hate a guy like Vangelis! He is the kind of man you'd want to have as your grandpa!</p>

<p>Okay, enough garbage: what do <em>I</em> think of the album? Have I listened to it? Do I love it or hate it? For starters, yes, I have listened to it all the way through at least three times. On headphones. One time I fell asleep on the bus as I was listening to it, but that was the only time. I don't know the whole album by heart (as I know [a]Albedo 0.39[/a], for example), but I remember some distinct moments (as the freaky side openers; some moments when Vangelis plays some mellow, beautiful chords; a part when he suspends a high note and slowly defaces it with a ring modulator; and a hilarious part in which he plays a thumping "BLAM! BLAM! BLAM! BLAM! BLAM" thing and uses the pan knob to make it alternate between the speakers, but the thing is so obviously manual that you <em>hear</em> them tail off towards the other speaker), and I do have an overall impression of the album. I don't hate it. I don't think it's the ugliest, most unpleasant record ever. It IS difficult for me to hear it, and I definitely have to be on a certain mood in order to endure it in one sitting. If I said I <em>like</em> it, I'd be lying; but depending on my mood, I definitely can enjoy it. That's more than I can say about Mike Oldfield's [a]Tubular Bells III[/a]: try as I might, I can't even enjoy it in a "so bad it's good" fashion. As for [a]Beaubourg[/a], I don't consider it a bad album <em>at all</em>. I give kudos to Vangelis for the sheer amount of guts it took him to put out this record, endangering to ruin the reputation he got from [a]Heaven and Hell[/a], [a]Albedo 0.39[/a] and [a]Spiral[/a]: it goes to show that he is courageous and honest. But I won't praise this music. I could give it a more modest rating based on the fact that I have enjoyed it a little before, but I have to be honest here: I don't get any urge to listen to this album. I listened it a few times for the curiosity, for the want of knowing it better and finally for reviewing purposes, and the last time I tried, I had to turn it off. So, I reserve the higher ratings for albums that I <em>do</em> feel like listening on occasion.</p>

<p>Gee, am I being too defensive?</p>]]></review>
      <rating>7</rating>
      <comment-phrase>Thoughts? [l]Send them in[/l]!</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="china">
      <title>China</title>
      <year>1979</year>
      <high-points>[s]The Tao of Love[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Chung Kuo</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Long March</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Dragon</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Plum Blossom</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>The Tao of Love</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Little Fete</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Yin &amp; Yang</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Himalaya</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Summit</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>China, eh?</p>

<p>Okay, so apparently making China-themed stuff is very cool. I can live with that. But I have to say: putting out an album like this is the ultimate way of passing yourself off as a complete dork. And this is something I wouldn't like to see coming from Vangelis. So, IS this album dorky or not?</p>

<p>Partly, yes. But first, a pedantic note: there was an indexing error on the CD issues of the album, because [s]Chung Kuo[/s] is only the one-minute-and-a-half introduction of the album, and everything that comes after it, including track two, is [s]The Long March[/s]. I'll be honest, [s]The Long March[/s] bores me. The melody is beautiful, the textures and arrangements are all absolutely Vangelis-like, but it sort of goes nowhere. Only the piano solo at the end (which was indexed as track 2) truly gets to me. Unfortunately, moments like these are not the rule in this album. I think Vangelis relies too much on "atmosphere" and "feeling" in this album, and even employs several guest musicians playing assorted instruments (both traditional Chinese instruments and Western ones), but it doesn't help. Maybe I'm not very "in line" with this more atmospheric side of Vangelis, after all?</p>

<p>Well, it's unfair to call this album "completely atmospheric". Only side two truly goes down that path, with the almighty [s]Himalaya[/s] and the quasi-ambient [s]Summit[/s] rounding off the trip. Side one, on the other hand, has the fast and furious [s]The Dragon[/s]. In terms of being a show-off of Vangelis' skills, well, he already showed off a lot more than this in the past, so it sounds pretty "typical". The two following songs are more melody oriented and have those climaxes with percussion clashes and whatnot. [s]The Plum Blossom[/s] has a very atypical, flourished melody played on a violin. It's only a little marred, however, for trying harder to sound "exotic" than "beautiful". Thankfully that doesn't happen with the gorgeous, delicate [s]The Tao of Love[/s]
      ]]></review>
      <rating>10</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Multi-[l]Comment[/l] Suggestion[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="opera">
      <title>Opéra Sauvage</title>
      <year>1979</year>
      <high-points>[s]The Tao of Love[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Hymne</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Rêve</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>L'Enfant</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Mouettes</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Cromatique</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Irlande</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Flamants Roses</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
      ]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Multi-[l]Comment[/l] Suggestion[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="later">
      <title>See You Later</title>
      <year>1979</year>
      <high-points>[s]Suffocation[/s], [s]Memories of Green[/s], [s]See You Later[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>I Can't Take It Anymore</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Multi-Track Suggestion</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Memories of Green</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Not a Bit / All of It</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Suffocation</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>See You Later</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>Apparently, there's a bit of a convoluted story behind this record. It started off as one thing, and ended up as... another thing. Some tracks remained, some were replaced. But the end product is basically the <em>strangest</em> Vangelis album so far. And I mean it: we've had oddities like his French "po&egrave;me symphonique", those two illegal jam-ish "albums" recorded in London, a Mediterranean rock 'n' roll album... and then I call <em>this</em> the strangest album so far? Yes, exactly, and the reason is that this is <em>not</em> an oddity. This is a perfectly regular and "normal" Vangelis album: it's not a soundtrack, not an illegal bootleg, and not an obscure and forgotten LP released in Greece only. This is a regular release, and a hell of a strange one.</p>

<p>Strange because the songs themselves are strange, the ordering is strange, and they don't seem to make much sense together. There's some off-kilter humour and some pretty anguished songs; a short vignette-like oddity and two long and multi-part epics; a disco song with studio jargon in the lyrics and a composition about a chemical catastrophe in Italy. Weird, huh? The nasty thing, though, is that this is a <em>very</em> hit-or-miss album. But then again, with such a convoluted origin and story, it would have been a miracle if it were anything but. Yet, I like it. Quite a lot, in fact. Okay, so the opening tracks are <em>a bit</em> too strange and odd for my tastes. I do like the agonising atmosphere and tension of [s]I Can't Take It Anymore[/s], with Vocoder'd singing, tension mounting and those numerous mini-climaxes Vangelis is so fond of. Even still, the song never resolves into anything: it's just left hanging. And is there any context to it? What <em>exactly</em> is it that Vangelis can't take anymore? I don't know. [s]Multi-Track Suggestion[/s], with its disco groove, is entertaining but unremarkable. Unremarkable, in this case, is good: Vangelis could have done way, way worse. And then, what's with [s]Not a Bit / All of It[/s]? Listening to it, I'm pretty sure it's meant as a piece of satire. He introduces a strangely nostalgic tune smelling of S&eacute;rgio Mendes or something, with a female voice making disconnected voice-overs, including a <em>very</em> obviously sarcastic advert for "cosmetics". Then, a baritone starts to sing along to the melody and she says "this man is a professional singer! We hope his voice will develop". <em>Huh?</em> Either way, the whole thing is so strange and nonsensical, that I can't help but enjoy it. But maybe I'm weird.</p>

<p>The three remaining tracks, however, oh boy! What tracks! [s]Memories of Green[/s] is nothing short of stupendous. It consists entirely of Vangelis on the piano delivering a performance that only he could possibly pull off. The only eccentric things are the flanger effect the piano is run through, and the sounds of Vangelis's sound engineer Raphael Preston playing a portable video game, the title of which I've unfortunately forgot. This song was used in <em>Blade Runner</em>, and was the only Vangelis piece used in the film that wasn't written specifically for it. It is <em>that</em> great. [s]Suffocation[/s] is my favourite: written about the Seveso Disaster, it is constructed entirely on a synthesizer groove, but through six minutes or so, it grows and unfolds in a multitude of different ways, and it just never loses steam. It's like a dancier, more laidback version of [s]Main Sequence[/s], and almost as brilliant. Near the end, the song becomes plaintive and dirgey, and Jon Anderson's singing announces the sad outcome of the disaster, with dialogue recorded by the two members of the Italian band Krisma round off the composition. Brilliant! Finally, the title track is far more dramatic and heavy, rocketting off into a frenzied groove, and slowly settling back into a dramatic conclusion with Jon singing some more. I hate to be so cryptic and undescriptive, but this is the kind of stuff that could only come out of Vangelis's hands. I love these songs, but I'm willing to admit: this album is not for everyone. Some tracks here may seriously put you off, and depending on your tastes, the whole album will displease you. But if you're fearless, give this one a spin. And if you're becoming a fan, do get it eventually.</p>]]></review>
      <rating>11</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s]Multi-[l]Comment[/l] Suggestion[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="fire">
      <title>Chariots of Fire</title>
      <year>1981</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="antarctica">
      <title>Antarctica</title>
      <year>1983</year>
      <high-points>[s]Theme from Antarctica[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Theme from Antarctica</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Antarctica Echoes</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Kinematic</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Song of White</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Life of Antarctica</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Memory of Antarctica</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>Other Side of Antarctica</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Deliverance</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>For whatever reason, Vangelis seems to have a certain fascination with making soundtracks to obscure films. Or maybe it's the simple fact that he produces so much music in such short periods of time that he's able to take pretty much any offer. By this point, Vangelis was already a big name. In purely financial terms, I believe he could easily only take "major" offers. Nonetheless, he wrote the score to this obscure Japanese documentary about... well, you can guess what the film is about. Apparently, it's difficult to get a hold of the film, and the opinions I've read about it are pretty negative. Basically the consensus is: the film does not do justice to the music.</p>

<p>This album features only part of the soundtrack, as is usual for Vangelis's standards. I've once heard a bootleg featuring the full (?) score to the film, but in my humble opinion, it's better to have this album, which at least contains Vangelis's own vision of what the album should be. It is coherent, complete and rewarding. And it features one of Vangelis's very best compositions of all time: [s]Theme from Antarctica[/s] is obscenely, ridiculously gorgeous. In other words, it is seven minutes of absolute, transcendental glory. The mix of elements somehow capture perfectly not only the sight, but the <em>feel</em> of an antarctic landscape, with a brutally simple, stately 4 note theme, a slow, sparse rhythm and a gradual, beautiful structural unfolding. Call me exaggerated as you wish, but I love it <em>that</em> much. And what's better is that the four note melody serves as a leitmotif through several other tracks.</p>

<p>It's easy to guess that many of these songs are slow, ambient, spaced-out explorations, and you'd guess partially right. There <em>are</em> such tracks, but they aren't very numerous. [s]Antarctica Echoes[/s] is the best example, employing the main theme again with a beautiful result. [s]Memory of Antarctica[/s] is similar, but the choice of sounds and instruments make it sound like it's about to turn into [a]Ignacio[/a] at any time. Finally, [s]Song of White[/s] is a solo for a synthesized woodwind sound, immitating a Chinese instrument. What I don't understand is that, halfway through, it turns into [s]Theme of Antarctica[/s] all over again. And it isn't even a different rendition: it's the exact same recording copy-and-pasted into the track. A "reprise" of sorts, I guess?</p>

<p>However, a surprisingly large portion of the album is dedicated to dramatic, agitated tracks such as [s]Life of Antarctica[/s], which is carried by a tense, constant descending synth arpeggio, and [s]Kinematic[/s] has a breakneck, unstoppable rhythm and explosive, bombastic percussion clashes all over it, while [s]Other Side of Antarctica[/s] is slower and more ominous. It's great stuff, though none of it can compare to the power of the first track; only the optimistic, piano laden [s]Deliverance[/s], which gives a glimpse of that glory, closing the album off beautifully. I don't know what it is about this album that truly touches my emotional strings; but this is Vangelis we're talking about! This is the guy that can take a three note melody and build a massive epic on top of it, and I believe this album is one of the finest examples of that, because the very nature of the music is minimalist. I dare say that this is one of the best opportunities of seeing the very essence of Vangelis's music distilled to the highest degree possible. Okay, so we don't have quite the catharsis of [a]Heaven and Hell[/a] or [a]Albedo 0.39[/a]; but if you have one iota of soul left inside you, just [s]Theme from Antarctica[/a] will suffice.</p>
      ]]></review>
      <rating>12</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s][l]Comments[/l] of Antarctica[/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    <album ref="festivities">
      <title>Soil Festivities</title>
      <year>1984</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="portraits">
      <title>Silent Portraits</title>
      <year>1984</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="mask">
      <title>Mask</title>
      <year>1985</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="connections">
      <title>Invisible Connections</title>
      <year>1985</year>
    </album>
    <album ref="direct">
      <title>Direct</title>
      <year>1988</year>
      <high-points>[s]Message[/s], [s]Intergalactic Radio Station[/s], [s]Glorianna (Hymn à la Femme)[/s], [s]Elsewhere[/s]</high-points>
      <tracks>
        <disc>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Motion of Stars</title></track>
          <track><grade>3</grade> <title>The Will of the Wind</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Metallic Rain</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Elsewhere</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Dial Out</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Glorianna (Hymn à la Femme)</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>Rotation's Logic</title></track>
          <track><grade>4</grade> <title>The Oracle of Apollo</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Message</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Ave</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>First Approach</title></track>
          <track><grade>5</grade> <title>Intergalactic Radio Station</title></track>
        </disc>
      </tracks>
      <review><![CDATA[
<p>One silly imposition I gave myself in these reviews are: every artist must have <em>one</em> album that's rated higher than the others. Why? I have no idea. I think it's the need for having a <em>"home"</em>, you know? A point of certain return, a place I can always recur to, a "favourite" that I can use to represent the artist as a whole. You might have noticed that [a]Albedo 0.39[/a] already got that honour, but this album is one <em>hell</em> of a rival. It's like marriage, you know? Your wife is your favourite, will <em>always</em> be your favourite, and it's simply unthinkable that you'll replace her for someone else... yet that does not mean you won't have very special people in your life, people that are so special that you may catch yourself wondering "wait! can there POSSIBLY be more than one?", but then, yes, you always remember that your wife will always be the one, and <em>the</em> one. Same thing happens here: no matter what, [a]Albedo 0.39[/a] stands tall and proud above all others, but every once in a while I catch myself wondering "wait, but what it [a]Direct[/a] was just as good?"</p>

<p>But enough crap already! This album is quite different from [a]Albedo 0.39[/a]. Firstly, there is no unifying theme, and if there's anything that unifies these tracks, it's their outstanding quality. These songs are amazing. Some more, some less, but all of them are brilliant. The sound has also been updated: at this stage, Vangelis depends pretty much entirely on keyboards, synthesizers and samplers, so the sound is a lot more uniform and, umm, "digital". But don't take that as a put-down: in this case, digital does not mean "cold and distant" in opposition to the "warm and present" of analogue. For Vangelis, digital is just another way of doing amazing music. The album has a certain "hollow", metallic quality to it, but that only adds to the atmosphere. The sound here is very nighttime-like, very starry and deep. And the songs? Goodness, where did Vangelis take this songs from? God's brain? They are out of this world.</p>

<p>And they are fairly varied, in terms of mood. Not in terms of style: there isn't any genre-juggling here, and Vangelis neber needed that. The more impatient guy may label this as "New Age", but don't take that seriously. This is far from New Age, though many songs here are downtempo and contemplative, and the faster songs don't "rock out" that much. But, just like [a]Albedo 0.39[/a], this is a thrilling album, not a "meditative" one. This album will shake you deeply, not with speed and rocking, but with power and resonance. And dynamics. The album flows extremely well and never settles in a comfort zone. In fact, it starts off almost deceptively: [s]The Motion of Stars[/s] may give you the impression that the big "schtick" here will be swirly arpeggios and bombastic "PLAM!" synth stabs, and you'll be "oh, it's [a]Mask[/a] all over again", and [s]The Will of the Wind[/s] may even remind you of easy-listening instrumental lift music, with that "ethnic" woodwind sound that Peter Gabriel used in the introduction of [s]Sledgehammer[/s] (remember it? that little oriental flute that "breaks" a little in the middle?), while [s]Metallic Rain[/s] should give you a sample of the "rocking" side of the album. Those songs are all solidly written (especially [s]The Motion of Stars[/s], which once again builds an impressive composition out of very simple and minimal themes), but they can barely give you a clue of what's coming up. Starting with [s]Elsewhere[/s], the album gets into a stride that won't be broken until the very last second of the album.</p>

<p>Amazingly, [s]Elsewhere[/s] should be the most "New Age-y" track so far, but its melody is God-like, the arrangements are smart and dynamic, and the gradual unfolding of the song's climax should suffice to show you that this is no "relaxation" bullshit. From then on, the album is triumph after triumph. The only piece of "rocking out" is concentrated in [s]Dial Out[/s], which is fun and jazzy, and the only "meditative" track is [s]The Oracle of Apollo[/s], built on a gorgeous melody and a set of developments played on a sampled harp, with just a few background embellishments. All other compositions are extremely meaty, with [s]Message[/s] being, in my honest opinion, the crowning achievement of the whole album. If you look at it coldly, you can even say there is no proper "melody" here at all, and the song is entirely based on its "orchestral ensemble", with a steady, ruthless rhythm underpinning a series of mini-climaxes and developments, with a constantly growing tension, oscillating from uplifting to dramatic. Eventually, the song reaches a boiling point, and then erupts into a gut-wrenching, unbelievably dramatic catharsis. And it's only a modulation! How on Earth does he <em>do</em> that? There's no need to crank up the volume of the instruments from "loud" to "TEAR-YOUR-EARDRUMS-APART" (I'm looking at <em>you</em>, Mike Oldfield!), no need to bring in syrupy and bombastic arrangements, no cheap tricks, nothing! Just an unexpected turn of phrase, and blam!, the whole song crashes around you like a storm. The effect is unbelievable.</p>

<p>Yet, it's the only seriously dramatic moment in the album. The other tunes lay more in the "uplifting" side of the spectrum, such as the wonderful [s]Glorianna[/s], with an uncredited soprano singer (Markella Hatziano, as Wikipedia informs us &mdash; but without citations! which means that it could be a big fat lie! If it were a citation from, say, Bill O'Reily, then it would be an unquestionable truth) delivering a powerful melody that tugs at all the warm and giddy strings of my soul. It's beautiful! And, again, the climax at the end does not fall in <em>any</em> of the predictable pitfalls: it's powerful and extremely tasteful. Meanwhile, [s]Ave[/s] is just endlessly cheery &mdash; and groovy! You can dance to this stuff! And sing along, if you want. It's that nice! And then, <em>wham!</em>, you're taken by surprise by the tear-inducing [s]First Approach[/s]. Goodness, that cello! It's damn close to emotional torture! Remember the effect of [s]Sword of Orion[/s] in [a]Albedo 0.39[/a]? If you could extend that effect for a whole five minutes, you'd get [s]First Approach[/s]. It is <em>that gorgeous</em>. And as the final blow, we get [s]Intergalactic Radio Station[/s], which defies descriptions. Suffice to say, it is mighty, heroic and cathartic, featuring a drum beat that gradually morphs from martial to jazzy (I know &mdash; it puzzles me too) while the arrangement follows suit.</p>

<p>There is no possible way this could get anything less than a 14, and if I didn't have the need to mark <em>one</em> favourite album, this would get an easy 15. Oh, well. Who cares? These ratings are not ultimate veredicts anyway! They're just a guide, remember? What matters is, if you only have a passing interest in Vangelis, do not skip this one. In fact, I'd say that, if you only want three Vangelis albums, this should be among them &mdash; along with [a]Albedo 0.39[/a] and [a]Heaven and Hell[/a]. Ratings don't do it justice; reviews don't do it justice. Just listen and enjoy.</p>

<p>For your information, both [s]Dial Out[/s] and [s]Intergalactic Radio Station[/s] are exclusive to the CD issues. The former isn't <em>really</em> such a loss, but [s]Intergalactic Radio Station[/s] is a must have. Make sure you own a digital copy of the album, even if you're a hardcore vinyl enthusiast.</p>]]>
      <rating>14</rating>
      <comment-phrase>[s][l]Message[/l][/s]</comment-phrase>
    </album>
    
    
#####
ALB
vangelis
city
The City
1990
#####
ALB
vangelis
paradise
1492: Conquest of Paradise
1991
#####
ALB
vangelis
runner
Blade Runner
1994
#####
ALB
vangelis
voices
Voices
1995
#####
ALB
vangelis
oceanic
Oceanic
1996
#####
ALB
vangelis
greco
El Greco
1998
#####
ALB
vangelis
mythodea
Mythodea
2001
#####
ALB
vangelis
alexander
Alexander
2004
#####
ALB
vangelis
elgreco
El Greco Original Motion Picture Soundtrack
2007
#####